<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Character of a Whig, under several denominations to which is added, The reverse, or, The character of a true English-man, in opposition to the former.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12278449</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12278449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58572</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58572)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 863:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Character of a Whig, under several denominations to which is added, The reverse, or, The character of a true English-man, in opposition to the former.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by the book sellers of London, and Westminster ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 134.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whig Party (Great Britain) --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:58572:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>speakers addressing a crowd</figDesc>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ter Days at hand my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q>
                  <q>Down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall be Mayor or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58572:1"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF A WHIG, Under Several DENOMINATIONS.</p>
            <p>To which is added, The <hi>Reverſe,</hi> or the <hi>Character</hi> of a true ENGLISH-MAN, in Oppoſition to the former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58572:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58572:2"/>
            <head>THE CHARACTER Of a Sowre, Malcontented <hi>WHIG,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>OF all Men living, they are the fitteſt Perſons to delineate their their own Accompliſhments; for when a Sowre <hi>Whig</hi> deſcribes a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> he is drawing his own Picture, and they act as uniformly, as if the Soul of the <hi>Ignatian</hi> Tribe, did Tranſmigrate after Death, into the Bodies of that <hi>Stickling</hi> Party. Contradiction is their Original Sin, the Peoples Ignorance ſupports their Cunning, Intereſt is the Dagon they both Idolize, and give them but <hi>Power</hi> to their <hi>Wills,</hi> they'd Bridle all <hi>Mankind,</hi> and Ride them into <hi>Sedition</hi> here, and to <hi>Hell</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. A Sowre <hi>Whig</hi> has more Shift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings than a <hi>Weezle,</hi> more Doublings than a <hi>Hare,</hi> more Shapes than <hi>Proteus,</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Colour ofter than a <hi>Camaelion,</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> may more eaſily contrive a <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teau</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58572:3"/>for the <hi>Moon,</hi> that is always Increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or Decreaſing, than any Pen circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe this <hi>Multifarious</hi> Animal in a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Character; and therefore I ſhall take the <hi>Machine</hi> into Pieces, and ſhew him in variety of Colours, Shapes and Poſtures: And firſt as</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Buſie, Impertinent, Intermedler in Government: <hi>Or,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AN Empty <hi>Polititian</hi> fit for nothing, but to make a Common-Council Man at <hi>Goatham,</hi> to Drown the <hi>Eel,</hi> or Hedge in the <hi>Cuckooe.</hi> A Sucking <hi>Coffee-houſe</hi> Stateſman, a Little Great Man of no <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> that wanting Imployment of his own, troubles all the World with his <hi>Idleneſs.</hi> He is haunted with a Spirit of <hi>Government,</hi> and wants nothing but a <hi>Call</hi> into an Office, to ſhew his <hi>Rare Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> in turning the World <hi>Upſide Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Ingratitude,</hi> and <hi>Dulneſs,</hi> will for ever be his Character: Which with a Mixture of <hi>Confidence</hi> ſets him up for a <hi>Patriot,</hi> which in our Modern Phraſe, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies nothing elſe but a <hi>Stickling Diſguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Fop,</hi> that thinks he deſerves ſome good place or other, which <hi>Heaven</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> knows he is not fit for. He pities
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58572:3"/>the World that has no greater Inſight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Parts, and like the <hi>Chynoiſes,</hi> thinks all the World is Blind but himſelf. He is ingaged in a Confederacy with <hi>Hypocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driack Clubbers,</hi> to admire one another, who think they have as much <hi>Wit</hi> as they <hi>want,</hi> and more than e'er they will have. He is Eternally <hi>Vain,</hi> becauſe he is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Thoughtful,</hi> and that Vanity makes him fancy himſelf of an <hi>Unfathomable</hi> Capacity, as <hi>Wine</hi> makes the <hi>Beggar</hi> think himſelf a Man of <hi>Quality.</hi> He is a Lump of combuſtible <hi>Ignorance,</hi> whom the leaſt Spark of <hi>News</hi> kindles in a Blaze of <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely,</hi> and prepoſterous <hi>Conjectures;</hi> and then the reſt of the <hi>Rooks</hi> and <hi>Daws</hi> take Wing, and fill the Town with <hi>Incredible</hi> Fears, and <hi>Inviſible</hi> Dangers. His Talk is like <hi>Benjamin</hi>'s Meſs; five times more than comes to his ſhare. All are <hi>Fools</hi> that are not of his <hi>Opinion,</hi> but he eſteems him a Man of extraordinary <hi>Wiſdom</hi> that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaudes his Conjectures, and puts him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Laughing at his own <hi>Shadow</hi> for want of a more Ridiculous Subſtance. His <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> is but the Viſor of his <hi>Policy,</hi> and whatever Vertue he has, Craft is the Keeper of it. All his Diſcourſes are Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and Enigmatical, like the Devils in the <hi>Delphick</hi> Oracle; you may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his Words, but never reach his Meaning. The Corruption of <hi>Reaſon</hi> was the Generation of his <hi>Wits,</hi> and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58572:4"/>of Lying and Slandering, is the height of his Improvement. He is a perfect E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to <hi>Monarchy,</hi> for want of an <hi>Office,</hi> and hates every <hi>Courtier,</hi> becauſe he is not one of the Number. In ſhort, he is a kind of Sucking Traytor, and the older he grows in his Diſcontents, the more is the Government endangered, by his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentations of Publick Actions. He creeps by degrees from want of an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,</hi> to advance a <hi>Lawleſs Liberty;</hi> from <hi>Petitioning</hi> to <hi>Remonſtrating;</hi> from queſtioning the <hi>Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city</hi> of his Superiors, to ſeizing the <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,</hi> into the Hands of the <hi>Populace.</hi> His Maxims in Government are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to <hi>Common Senſe,</hi> and ruinous to the <hi>Monarchy.</hi> He Aſſerts the way to make a King <hi>Great and Glorious,</hi> is to give him no <hi>Money;</hi> that the means to ſupport Forreign <hi>Allyance,</hi> is to Impoveriſh the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and the beſt way to keep the Government upon the <hi>Wheels,</hi> is to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the <hi>Axle-tree;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Whigs,</hi> and their New Aſſociates, the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been long troubled with the Spirit of <hi>Contradiction,</hi> the Devil of <hi>Nonſence</hi> is got among 'em alſo. Humor them and you <hi>Diſappoint</hi> 'em. Every <hi>New-fangled</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thruſts out a former Exception, and give 'em full poſſeſſion of what they Ask, and they ſoon grow weary of the <hi>Toy</hi> they Whimper'd for. They Declaim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58572:4"/>Arbitrary Power, and yet <hi>Uſurp</hi> it; againſt the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and erect an <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary</hi> Power above it; againſt <hi>Grievances,</hi> and yet <hi>Promote</hi> them; againſt <hi>Miſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagements,</hi> and yet produce no <hi>Inſtances</hi> of their Being. They carry <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> upon the Tip of their Tongues; but dare ſwallow neither, for fear they ſhould choak them. They complain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ill Miniſters</hi> to colour a <hi>Faction</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>State,</hi> and to Enſlave Free Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects under the <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Impoſitions of a prevailing Party; but I fear I have kept them Company too long, and therefore will pay a Viſit to</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Hypocritical Preaching <hi>Whigs</hi> under every Denomination.</head>
               <p>WHom I will deſcribe in their Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Poſtures, and other top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Qualities, that recommended them to a Deluded People, and raiſe their <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes</hi> in the World. Some of them, whoſe Abilities could not among Underſtanding Men, advance them above a <hi>Groom,</hi> a <hi>Porter,</hi> or a <hi>Threſher,</hi> have gain'd a more comfortable <hi>Maintainance</hi> (their Port con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) than an Ordinary <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> and all a better <hi>Allowance</hi> than the generality
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58572:5"/>of the <hi>Orthodox</hi> Learned Clergy. They are at little or no <hi>Expence</hi> in their Education. Pretended <hi>Gifts</hi> ſupply the Defect of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Knowledge.</hi> The latter are the leiſurely Effects of <hi>Labour, Sweat</hi> and <hi>Reading;</hi> the former are only ſtrong <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes,</hi> and Fortunate <hi>Incomes</hi> which gives a ſhort Turn upon their Trade of <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> A heavy <hi>Phlegmatick</hi> Blockhead, that could never get Learning enough at <hi>School,</hi> to enable him to undergo an <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> for Admiſſion into the <hi>Univerſity,</hi> let him have but a ſtrong Averſion to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of a <hi>Mechanick,</hi> or the <hi>Induſtry</hi> of a <hi>Tradeſman.</hi> That is, let him be Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>Lazy,</hi> and enrich'd with a convenient proportion of <hi>Duncery,</hi> 'tis a good <hi>Call</hi> to the great Affair of <hi>Holding forth</hi> among the Brethren; then let him Board a while at Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi>'s, Mr. <hi>Doelittle</hi>'s, Mr. <hi>Meade</hi>'s, Mr. <hi>Cyffin</hi>'s, Mr. <hi>Pen</hi>'s, and now and then take the <hi>Air</hi> at the Phanatick Academies of <hi>Newington, Croydon, Hammerſmith,</hi> or <hi>Nettlebed:</hi> Wear a Black <hi>Jump,</hi> and his <hi>Hair,</hi> and <hi>Ears,</hi> of the <hi>Smectymnian</hi> Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, to ſhew him a <hi>Divinity</hi> Intender; it matters not whether he Read any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, <hi>Sacred</hi> or <hi>Profane,</hi> provided he takes <hi>Notes,</hi> or ſtand <hi>Gaping</hi> upon a Form, or Stool, to receive a Meaſure of the <hi>Light,</hi> that an old <hi>Squeaking</hi> Tubſter is ſcattering among the <hi>Juvenile</hi> Fraternity. Let him but <hi>Repeat</hi> in the Afternoon, till the Pit,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58572:5"/>Boxes, and Galleries are full, and till he has attained a juſt <hi>Confidence</hi> in <hi>Speaking</hi> in Publick, and a <hi>Profound, Engaging,</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> Method in <hi>Managing</hi> his <hi>Poſtures,</hi> Sighs, Groans, and Grimaces. Then up ſtarts the <hi>Ah Lard</hi> Stripling into the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, or other Mouthing Place; and tho' he be as Fat as a <hi>Porpus,</hi> his firſt Text is, <hi>O my Leanneſs, my Leanneſs:</hi> Or, <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel;</hi> tho' by his Uncouth and Ignorant <hi>Managery,</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of him. <hi>Age, Example,</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> improves him in all the Arts of <hi>Mimical Geſtures,</hi> Affected Tones, Shuffling his Cloak; Fingring his Band, Coughing with an Emphaſis, Spitting with a Grace, Folding, and Unfolding his Handkerchief according to the <hi>Original,</hi> and Wiping his Mouth <hi>a la mode de Lake Lemain;</hi> and now he has gain'd the Reputation of a Soul-ſaving, Heaven-gaining, Sin deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Hell-confounding, Pious, Precious, Zealous, Painful, Preaching Brother. From theſe Improvements he at length arrives at the height, and perfection of <hi>Mimick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and gives Laws to all his Inferiors, for a <hi>Pedantick Behaviour,</hi> in carrying on the Work of the Day, to the Satisfaction of the Beloved Secret Ones.</p>
               <p>The Demureneſs of his Looks in the Desk, Sanctifies his <hi>Incoherent</hi> and <hi>Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox</hi> Expoſitions on the Chapters. When he aſcends the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and puts on his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58572:6"/>
                  <hi>Praying Face,</hi> he <hi>Drawls</hi> out his Words, as if they wanted Fellows, and muſt be <hi>Hem'd</hi> up from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is <hi>Lower Venter,</hi> before he could be furniſh'd with a <hi>Prologue.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in a <hi>Lowe</hi> and ſcarce <hi>Audible</hi> Tone, as if the Griping in his Guts had caus'd a Grumbling in his Gizzard, he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys,
<q>
                     <l>Lard we dare not Ope our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Winks</hi> for fear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lling of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ies.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In naming his Text, he turns over as many Leaves in his <hi>Bible,</hi> as if <hi>Chance,</hi> or <hi>Inſpiration</hi> muſt direct him to't; and that he knew not whether the Text wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the <hi>Old</hi> or <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> that he muſt <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld forth</hi> upon. The Text being found, he <hi>Leans</hi> and <hi>Reaches</hi> over the Pulpit, as if he would take off the <hi>Wigs</hi> and <hi>Head-Dreſſes</hi> of his Under Auditors, for the eaſier En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of his Doctrine into their <hi>Perri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oraniums.</hi> His one and twenty Points are Tagg'd with <hi>Wry Faces,</hi> for want of <hi>Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> his <hi>Reaſons,</hi> with <hi>Railing,</hi> for want of <hi>Argument;</hi> and the labour of all his <hi>Preachments</hi> is chiefly in the <hi>Lungs,</hi> and all he made of them himſelf, was the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> His <hi>Actions</hi> are all <hi>Paſſions,</hi> and his Words <hi>Interjections.</hi> He cajoles his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in <hi>Bemoaning</hi> and <hi>Sainting</hi> 'em, and ſhews his own Parts, in Blowing his <hi>Noſe</hi> with abundance of Diſcretion. At <hi>Application-time,</hi> he ſtands bolt up-right;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58572:6"/>with his Arms on <hi>Kembow,</hi> like the Ears of an <hi>Iron Pot,</hi> which makes him look very <hi>Magiſterially,</hi> and faſtens the Uſes of <hi>Reproof</hi> in the Sculls of his Auditors, like <hi>Hob-Nails</hi> driven into the Poſts of a <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows;</hi> then he ſhifts the Scene into a loud thick <hi>clapping</hi> of his Hands, which ſerve to the driving home, and clenching the <hi>Farthing Tack</hi> of an Argument. After this he ſtretches himſelf forward on the Pulpit-Cuſheon, made of a Siſters decayed <hi>Velvet-Petticoat,</hi> which he ſometimes <hi>Hugs</hi> in his Arms, as if he was in a Rapture; then in a Zealous Fury, <hi>Thumps</hi> the Duſt out o'th' Cuſheon, into his <hi>Eyes,</hi> which makes him <hi>Weep</hi> and <hi>Wink</hi> affectionately, for the Backſlidings of the Zealous Party; then falls to contracting and expanding his Arms, as if he had been <hi>Swimming,</hi> and all to ſhew himſelf a Painful Preacher. By and by he Weaves from one ſide o'th' Pulpit to the other, in a Uſe of <hi>Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and contracts the Muſcles of his Face, into an Obliging <hi>Grin;</hi> which raiſes the Drooping Spirits of his <hi>Auditors,</hi> into Extaſies of <hi>Joy,</hi> and Stomachs to their <hi>Dinners.</hi> Laſtly the <hi>Hats</hi> of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation being all of a ſudden turn'd a-wry, like Ballad-ſingers in a Country Fair; but with the open ſide to the <hi>Tubſter,</hi> leſt what goes in at one Ear, ſhould go out at t'other, gives you notice the Holder forth is falling into his concluding Prayer;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58572:7"/>where he <hi>Winks, Kneads</hi> the Cuſheon, and is in as many <hi>Notes,</hi> as a pair of Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipes. Sometimes in a deep hollow <hi>Grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he noiſe of a Stone ratling down a <hi>Well;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>n a loud Stentorophonical <hi>Bawl,</hi> which is preſently rais'd into a high <hi>Scream,</hi> upon the Key in which a Nice Lady <hi>Squeaks</hi> at the ſight of a <hi>Frog;</hi> and by and by a <hi>Maudlin</hi> ſort of a <hi>Whine,</hi> in which he continues ſo long, till the Tears drop from his Noſe, and he Sweats like a Greaſy Hoſteſs in <hi>Dog-Days,</hi> and would have <hi>Brayed</hi> longer, if the Clock, and Chimes of his Guts crying Cuboard, had not ſtopt him.</p>
               <p>This Exerciſe of his <hi>Lungs,</hi> and his Auditors <hi>Patience</hi> being over, happy is the <hi>Man,</hi> and more happy his <hi>Wife,</hi> that can have the Favour of this Heavenly Man's Company at <hi>Dinner.</hi> In the way home, the Diſciple thanks the Good Man for his <hi>Pains,</hi> commends his <hi>Voice,</hi> and his <hi>Memory,</hi> but not a Word of the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:</hi> For he ſlept all the time as ſoundly, as if he had heard a <hi>Carnal Dean</hi> or <hi>Biſhop.</hi> The Wife ſends the Apprentice before, to warm the <hi>Towels</hi> to Rub him down, and that a <hi>Tankard of Sack</hi> may be ready to <hi>Drench</hi> him, for fear his <hi>Greaſe</hi> ſhould be <hi>Melted.</hi> Theſe accuſtomed Neceſſariums being ended, the Cropſick Holder-forth approaches the Table, with fear there ſhould not be Food enough; and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58572:7"/>to the Miſtreſs of the Houſe, and her <hi>Chinſe</hi> Gown and Petticoat, then bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the <hi>Quaking-pudding,</hi> becauſe <hi>Eſau</hi> ſold his Birthright for a Meſs of <hi>Porridge;</hi> the <hi>Leg</hi> of <hi>Mutton,</hi> becauſe he might pull the <hi>Pope's-Eye</hi> out; the <hi>Shoulder,</hi> becauſe <hi>David</hi> was a <hi>Shepherd.</hi> The <hi>Capon,</hi> becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> was converted by a <hi>Cock;</hi> and the <hi>Cuſtard,</hi> becauſe it was a <hi>Scape-Goat</hi> from the <hi>Lord-Mayor's</hi> Table. Now he lays out himſelf ſweetly, upon the Creature Comforts, and ſhews his Abilities in Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, oppos'd the Miracle in feeding five Thouſand; for if he had been a Gueſt at that Meal, there would not have been ſo many <hi>Fragments</hi> left, as would have Dined a <hi>Sparrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From ſtuffing his Paunch at the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, he returns to air his Lungs, and give himſelf <hi>Breath</hi> in an Afternoon's Exerciſe, where he ſpeaks more with <hi>Eaſe,</hi> than a wiſe Man can hear with <hi>Patience.</hi> In the Morning he was a Son of Thunder, but for fear of diſpleaſing their Haughtineſſes, and loſing his own Contribution, he muſt now be a Son of Conſolation; and therefore knowing their Inclinations to <hi>Democracy,</hi> preaches up Popular Doctrines, ſuch as <hi>Baxter</hi> and <hi>Jenkins</hi> begun the Civil-War with: The Liberty and Power of the People, and the Privilege of Rebelling, if ever the Prerogative of the Crown ſhould check
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58572:8"/>the Licentiouſneſs of the Conventicle: For then the <hi>Hydra</hi> may, in their Opinion, ſet up againſt <hi>Hercules,</hi> and, if poſſible, fetrer <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelf. By theſe Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the <hi>Old Bell-wethers</hi> of every <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal</hi> Flock, from the infamous Title of <hi>Traitors</hi> were dignified with that of <hi>Saints,</hi> and wallow'd in Wealth and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Having thus plaid the <hi>Paraſite</hi> to a Popular Ambition, he Acts the ſame part as a Preacher, and has a <hi>Salve</hi> for every Sore, and an <hi>Excuſe</hi> for every Sin, till none at all is to be found among his <hi>own Peaple;</hi> and if any of them ſhould complain, he has <hi>Crums of Comfort</hi> for the <hi>Hungry; Sips of Sweetneſs</hi> for the <hi>Thirſty; Crutches</hi> for the <hi>Weary; Porter's-Blocks</hi> for the <hi>Heavy Laden; Apples of Gold</hi> for the <hi>Poor; Iron Cheſts</hi> for the <hi>Rich; High Heel'd Shooes</hi> for <hi>Dwarfs in Duty,</hi> and a thouſand other <hi>Knick Knacks</hi> to ſeduce the Eaſy and Ignorant Multitude; and therefore they ſeldom or never apply to their Hearers <hi>Reaſons,</hi> but to their <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors</hi> and <hi>Fancies;</hi> and inſtead of taking pains to enable themſelves to <hi>Speak Senſe,</hi> for the improvement of the <hi>Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of their Congregations, (which good end, if attain'd, would put their Craft in danger to be ſet at nought) they take the readier way of Addreſſing to their <hi>Paſſions</hi> and <hi>Tempers,</hi> and thereby rendring themſelves Maſters of their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58572:8"/>
                  <hi>Weakneſſes,</hi> and <hi>leſſer</hi> Inclinatious, they ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure an <hi>Implicit approbation</hi> of their Words and Actions; and when this is once at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieved, the poor <hi>Diſciple</hi> is miſerably Ridden into all Incoveniences. Nothing muſt be too good for the Men of <hi>Cap, Cloak</hi> and <hi>Handchercheif</hi> o're the <hi>Band.</hi> If he's Cropſick, out comes the Rich <hi>Jellys, Dry'd Sweet-meats, Cordial-Waters,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Moore</hi>'s Drops, to ſupply the place of the Bitter Draught, Cow Piſs, or a Pepper Poſſet; beſides, ſomething muſt be laid down <hi>in hand</hi> for Entrance, a conſtant <hi>Rent</hi> for a <hi>Pew,</hi> Proviſion for often Viſits of the demure zealous <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> who muſt never be diſmiſs'd empty <hi>Bellied,</hi> nor empty <hi>Handed,</hi> for fear he ſhould ſhake the <hi>Duſt</hi> off his Feet, and leave a Curſe behind him. From hence the <hi>Senior Soph</hi> adjourns to ſome other <hi>Rich</hi> Members of the Faction, where his firſt Salutation is, <hi>Peace to this Houſe,</hi> but is ſure to raiſe a War in the Family be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his departure, that may gain him the opportunity of another Viſit, a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Purſe; and a large ſtuffing his Paunch to Reconcile them. To theſe may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, Repeated <hi>Contributions</hi> to <hi>Itenerate</hi> Apoſtles, that want <hi>Booths</hi> to hold forth in; and what is more than all this, the continual <hi>Drainings</hi> on the Wives part: So that a <hi>Wealthy</hi> Diſciple, that is duly qualified with a <hi>zealous ſilly Wife,</hi> is a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58572:9"/>good <hi>Farm</hi> to a Cunning, Canting <hi>Tub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Converſation in mixt Company is, Railing againſt the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> as Papiſts in Maſquerade. Againſt Human <hi>Learning</hi> in Sermons; and highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends (what is truly) <hi>the Fooliſhneſs of Preaching.</hi> A ſignificant <hi>Ceremony</hi> frights him into a <hi>Frenzy;</hi> a Diſcourſe of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>Decency</hi> is a Mark of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and turns him <hi>Topſy Turvy;</hi> and rather than not be <hi>Singular,</hi> if other Men go to <hi>Heaven</hi> upon their <hi>Feet,</hi> he'l (for <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> ſake) take the other way upon his <hi>Head.</hi> He loves none of the <hi>Prelates</hi> but Biſhop <hi>Fox,</hi> whom he Applauds for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his <hi>Book of Martyrs;</hi> but more for his Diſcretion in keeping himſelf from being one of the Number of thoſe that ſuffer'd the Pains and Perils of <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot. Simulation,</hi> is his <hi>Sanctity; Gain,</hi> is his <hi>Godlineſs;</hi> and all his Actions are govern'd by a kind of <hi>Political Wiſdom,</hi> abſtracted from the Rules of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> In ſhort, he ſeems one of the <hi>holieſt</hi> Men <hi>Heavenward</hi> that you can meet with, but the <hi>Illeſt Man</hi> among his Neighbours in the whole Pariſh. A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence is due to the very appearance of <hi>Piety;</hi> but whenever we find this <hi>Holy Man to Godward,</hi> to be no better than <hi>Ferg—n,</hi> a <hi>Jugling Knave,</hi> among Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that's the very <hi>Hypocrite</hi> we find
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58572:9"/>Stigmatiz'd among the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> in the Goſpel; and as ſuch we'll leave him to take a view of</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Factious, Seditious, Illiterate <hi>Whig</hi> Lawyer.</head>
               <p>WHo came to <hi>Town</hi> recommended from the Scatter'd Churches of the <hi>Whigs</hi> in <hi>Hibernia,</hi> Equipt in a kind of <hi>Kent-ſtreet</hi> Mourning. A <hi>Frize-Coat,</hi> as tatter'd as a <hi>He-Goat.</hi> A <hi>Hat</hi> well Blockt, but ſcarce half a Crown to it. His <hi>Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet</hi> and <hi>Breeches</hi> ſo alike, that a Dark Morning was enough to make him mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake the one for the other. His <hi>Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens</hi> without Feet, like a Chandlers draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sleeves, and he durſt not truſt them off his Legs, for fear of Crawling from him; and in ſhort from <hi>Head</hi> to <hi>Heel,</hi> was a thing made up of ſo many ſeveral <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,</hi> that you'd have taken him at firſt ſight for a <hi>Frontiſpiece</hi> of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and enquir'd of him, how the <hi>Whigs</hi> were diſpoſed of in the other World; but a <hi>Collection,</hi> and his Uncle's <hi>Charity</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Rig'd him into <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Shape, and a ſmall charge in pounding <hi>Tobacco-Pipes,</hi> and mixing them with the <hi>Juice of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and <hi>Fullers-Earth,</hi> to take out the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58572:10"/>Stains of his <hi>Wild-Iriſh</hi> Education, he ſoon brisk'd up into a <hi>Confident Thing,</hi> as like a Man as a Boyiſh <hi>Bog-Trotter</hi> could arrive to. His early Pretences to <hi>Zeal, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and <hi>Nonconformity,</hi> ſhew he ſuckt in the Principles of <hi>Sedition</hi> with his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Milk, and that in him were all the <hi>Seeds of Miſchief,</hi> only they wanted form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and therefore it was ſoon reſolv'd upon the Queſtion, that having all the Requiſite Qualifications of <hi>Lelap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> Snarl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the <hi>Poor,</hi> Fawning on the <hi>Rich,</hi> and Glavering with all he could but get a <hi>Mouldy-Cruſt</hi> by, he ought to be hewed out into <hi>Log</hi> called a <hi>Lawyer;</hi> which being <hi>primed</hi> with <hi>Impudence,</hi> and <hi>gilded</hi> with <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> might in time be a Pillar to ſupport the <hi>Whigs</hi> ſinking Cauſe, and raiſe it to the height of Forty One, to <hi>Forty Eight.</hi> To accompliſh this End ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already the Gifts of a <hi>Whig,</hi> and the Graces of the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> he never gave himſelf the trouble of Studying the <hi>Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Arts,</hi> to qualifie himſelf for a Man of <hi>Sence;</hi> but for want of <hi>Learning</hi> entitles himſelf a Man of <hi>Buſineſs.</hi> He never drudged Seven cold Winters, and as many ſweaty Summers, in reading the <hi>Statutes,</hi> collecting <hi>Reports,</hi> digeſting <hi>Cooke</hi>'s <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> and forming <hi>Common-Place</hi> Books; but entred at the Back-Door of an <hi>Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Clerk,</hi> to ſet up for a <hi>Counſellor.</hi> He put his Name, 'tis true, in the Burtery-Books
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58572:10"/>of the <hi>Temple,</hi> but with a Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on never to trouble the <hi>Society,</hi> with <hi>Mooting Caſes, Dancing</hi> in <hi>Maſquerade, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling</hi> at <hi>Chriſtmas;</hi> or ſo much as Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Commons in the <hi>Hall;</hi> but as a ſhorter cut to cheat the World, Pinnion'd himſelf like a <hi>Gizzard</hi> under the Wing of an Experienc'd <hi>Petty-fogger</hi> of the <hi>Party,</hi> where he learn'd more of the <hi>Liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious part</hi> of the Law in a Year, than he could have done without the help of ſuch a <hi>Tutor,</hi> by ſtudying in the <hi>Inns of Court,</hi> or <hi>Chancery</hi> all his Life time. By this <hi>Arſward</hi> Method he was able to walk without a <hi>Goe-Cart,</hi> or the help of <hi>Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſtrings;</hi> and was more expert in <hi>Hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Candle to the Devil,</hi> than thoſe that have ſtudied the Point with more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Auſterities: And no wonder, for all theſe kind of <hi>Whigs</hi> manage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by <hi>Trick</hi> and <hi>Confederacy,</hi> and have a nearer <hi>way</hi> to Ruine the <hi>World,</hi> than all the reſt of Mankind. The Vogue of being a <hi>Conventicler,</hi> gives a greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to any Lawleſs <hi>Profeſſer,</hi> among the Party, than Seven Years Study in a <hi>Univerſity:</hi> For being Litigious in their <hi>Natures,</hi> as well as <hi>Practiſes,</hi> no thing is ever thought to be well ſaid, or done, 'till it is ſtampt with the Opinion of an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty-Headed <hi>Dul-man.</hi> As ill uſed the Study of the Law is no Liberal Science; but a meer <hi>Mechanical</hi> Myſtery,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58572:11"/>introduced into the World, as one of the great <hi>Grievances</hi> of Mankind; attain'd without Speculation of the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or the Aſſiſtance of an illuminated Genius, but is a meer <hi>Heap</hi> and <hi>Chaos</hi> of undigeſted <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Fallacies,</hi> practiced to ſqueeze Money out of <hi>Litigious</hi> Fools, to fatten a Crew of <hi>Miſerly Muck-worms,</hi> of which our new Law-Intruer is a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sighing</hi> at a Conventicle, having <hi>Cough'd</hi> him into a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and taking Notes at <hi>Dicks,</hi> or the <hi>Graecian</hi> Coffee-Houſe, having Ear-mark'd him for an <hi>Antimonarchiſt,</hi> which are the only Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonials to Recommend a <hi>Confident Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niatre</hi> to the Practice of the Law, and make him <hi>Paſs Mnſtre,</hi> among the <hi>Holy Brethren.</hi> This <hi>Nitt</hi> of the Law, ſoon ſwells himſelf into an <hi>Elephant</hi> in his own Conceit, and tho' he knows not the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the <hi>Nodder</hi> and the <hi>Nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee,</hi> Nor a <hi>Deed</hi> in <hi>Tayle,</hi> from a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Ejectment,</hi> yet by Learning a little <hi>Phanatick</hi> Addreſs, a <hi>Buſy</hi> look, and a <hi>Starch'd</hi> Behaviour, he grows as <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure and Dull as a Recorder,</hi> and wants nothing but a <hi>Barr-Gown,</hi> to Cheat the World <hi>cum Privilegio.</hi> A Friend being made to the Approbator, who <hi>greaſing</hi> him in the <hi>Fiſt,</hi> gets his <hi>Hand</hi> to a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial of the Block-head's Sufficiency; and by promiſing his great Acquaintance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58572:11"/>among the <hi>Quarrelſom Whigs,</hi> would bring many good <hi>Griſts</hi> to the Mill at <hi>Weſt minſter,</hi> he is call'd to the <hi>Barr,</hi> and paſſes among the <hi>Crow'd</hi> by an Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <hi>Tranſmigration,</hi> from an Illiterate <hi>Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifogger,</hi> to be call'd a <hi>Councellor learn'd in the Law.</hi> The Firſt News of his Dignity is publiſh'd among the <hi>Siſter-hood,</hi> who Simper at his Preferment, in hopes to lick their Lips in a Bowl of <hi>Beveridge,</hi> to Handſel his caſt <hi>Gown</hi> and <hi>Cap,</hi> and to wiſh him good luck at the next <hi>Goal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery:</hi> Whilſt the Baſtard Son of <hi>Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſtruts among the Women, like the <hi>Major Domo,</hi> of the <hi>Turkiſh Seraglio.</hi> Every Street, Lane and Alley in the City, receives his Viſits with his Gown on, and his great Buſineſs there, is but to ſhew it. If he has a <hi>Companion</hi> in his Walk, he makes as much Noiſe with Clattering out Law, as an Inceptor in his <hi>Slap Golo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia</hi>'s. Inſtead of turning over <hi>Books</hi> in his Study, he exerciſies his <hi>Gifts</hi> on his <hi>Bed-maker,</hi> and Commits Fornication with the <hi>Duſt</hi> of his Chamber, to gain her good Word for an <hi>Able Practitioner.</hi> He Traverſes the Walks of the <hi>Temple,</hi> more duly than a Penny-leſs <hi>Alſation,</hi> and on the ſame Errand too, to ſee who will ſhew their good breeding in Inviting him to Dinner, but is often diſappointed. To force a Trade, he once bought a <hi>Sheep</hi>'s-<hi>Head,</hi> Horns and all, of a Butcher, for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58572:12"/>for his <hi>Sunday</hi>'s Dinner, and deſired him to give him a <hi>Receipt</hi> for the dreſſing of it; which while the <hi>Butcher</hi> was Dictating, a <hi>Dog</hi> runs away with his Staring Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Mutton; and the Mob crying out, <hi>Lawyer, Lawyer,</hi> the Dog has ſtolen your Sheep's-Head; and he ſeeing him ſo far <hi>Eloped,</hi> that he could not <hi>Attack</hi> the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, and have his Body in <hi>Arcta Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odia,</hi> to appear next Term <hi>Coram. Dom. Reg. apud Weſtmonaſterienſis,</hi> he ſaid, let him go like a <hi>Fooliſh</hi> Cur as he is, 'twill do him no good, for I have the <hi>Receipt,</hi> and he knows not how to dreſs it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides I have a good <hi>Action</hi> at Law againſt his <hi>Maſter,</hi> of <hi>Trover</hi> and <hi>Converſion,</hi> by which I ſhall gain <hi>Coſts</hi> of Suit, and <hi>Treble</hi> Damages. Many Terms together he Trudg'd to <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> without any <hi>Cauſe</hi> for his going thither, unleſs to <hi>ſee</hi> and be <hi>ſeen</hi> among the <hi>Monkeys</hi> and <hi>Lap-Dogs,</hi> and <hi>Walking-Trees,</hi> that come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ſold, as he to be Hired for a <hi>Rat-catcher.</hi> But this not ſucceeding, a more hopeful Stratagem enters his <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> Perricranium, and he immediately puts it in Execution. He frequents <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles</hi> and <hi>Lecture Sermons</hi> Devoutly, makes an Intereſt among <hi>Attornies, Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citors,</hi> and that Herd of filthy <hi>Swine</hi> that the Devil entered into; and the Crawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Vermine,</hi> worſe than all the <hi>Plauges</hi> of <hi>Egypt, Splitters</hi> of Cauſes, and <hi>Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58572:12"/>Devils, that make no more of Swearing upon the <hi>Holy Bible,</hi> than of laying their Lips upon <hi>Renald</hi> the Fox, or the <hi>Seven Wiſe Maſters.</hi> For theſe <hi>Vipers</hi> never ſting one anather, tho' they gnaw their way in to'th World, through their Dams Bellies. This Confederacy, and giving Attornies leave to make uſe of his Name, when they wanted a <hi>Counſels</hi> hand without a <hi>Fee,</hi> as they often do, and letting them go <hi>Snips</hi> in all the <hi>Fees</hi> they bring him, quickly brought him into Vogue, eſpecially among their own <hi>Party,</hi> who always Meaſure <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Wrong,</hi> by their Intereſts; like the <hi>Turks,</hi> they call every thing good or bad, by the Succeſs that attends it, and every Man a <hi>Proficient</hi> in his <hi>Art,</hi> that <hi>Boggles</hi> not at doing any thing they would have him: In which our Lurcher has as conſiderable <hi>Qualifications,</hi> as any Lawyer in <hi>Kent</hi> or <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> That which prevents ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny honeſt Men from being <hi>Lawyers,</hi> viz. <hi>a Scrupulous Conſcience, and an inflexible Honeſty,</hi> never hinders him, for he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries no ſuch things about him. His Soul is meer Senſe, and as he has no knowledge of <hi>Vertue,</hi> ſo while he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged among the malcontented <hi>Whigs,</hi> he has no occaſion to make uſe of it. He has a <hi>Braſs</hi> Towel, and a <hi>Steel</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and never wants ſo much <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> in his <hi>Green Bag,</hi> as to be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58572:13"/>at any Undertaking, and never cares whether a Cauſe be Good or Bad, ſo there is but money to be got by it. He is a ſworn Enemy to <hi>Arbitrators</hi> and <hi>Umpires,</hi> and the words <hi>Peace</hi> or <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> he looks upon as <hi>Apochryphal,</hi> and ought to be torn from our Bibles, and <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Contention</hi> inſerted in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. He has a kind of a <hi>Sea-faring Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> that Sleeps more quietly in <hi>Hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricanes, Storms</hi> and <hi>Tempeſts,</hi> than in a Popular <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Tranquility.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Qualifications and Advantages Records him a Saint in the Whiggiſh Calender, tho', in truth, he is nothing but a <hi>Feind</hi> with a Glory about his head, to dazle the Eyes of a <hi>Bifarious</hi> Mobile, tho' it anſwers the <hi>Deſign,</hi> increaſes his <hi>Practice,</hi> multiplies his <hi>Clients,</hi> and fills his <hi>Empty</hi> Pockets. The Firſt day of the Term finds him Trotting on Foot to <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> in a Dagled Gown, a Dangling Wig, <hi>Papers</hi> in his Hand, a <hi>Bag</hi> under his Arm; and a Cluſter of <hi>Durty</hi> Country Clients, like <hi>Burrs</hi> Sticking to the <hi>Rump</hi> of our <hi>Paris Garden</hi> Pleader. In addreſſing to the <hi>Barre;</hi> he bids an Eternal farewell to his Modeſty and Conſcience, as <hi>Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Notions,</hi> next door Neighbours to <hi>Beggery,</hi> and ſupplies thoſe Vacancies, with Confounded <hi>Jargon, Billingsgate Rhetorick,</hi> and a large Stock of <hi>Impudence.</hi> His Prologue to the Farce, is, <hi>May it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58572:13"/>pleaſe your Lordſhips, and you Gentlemen of the Jury,</hi> for want of a better, <hi>I am of Conncel for the Plaintiff</hi> A, <hi>in an Action of Aſſault and Battery: Setting forth that the Defendant</hi> B, <hi>Simul cum</hi> C. D. E. F. G. <hi>with Swords, Staves and Knives, Wounded, Hurt and Maimed us, in a Principal Member of our Body,</hi> Anglice our little Finger, <hi>and put us in danger of our Lives,</hi> and hopes of a Hundred Pound Damages. This my Lord, we could have proved <hi>Temp. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur,</hi> by Twenty Witneſſes, <hi>Bon. et Legal. Hom.</hi> But <hi>Nineteen</hi> of 'em being Dead, or knowing nothing of the matter, we ſhall Trouble the <hi>Court</hi> but with one. Cryar, call Mr. <hi>Bartholemew Braſs Girdle,</hi> Inholder, <hi>Anglice</hi> an Ale-houſe Keeper, where the Quarrel began with <hi>Ale,</hi> and <hi>Ale</hi> wou'd have ended it, if the dextrous Management of the Country <hi>Common-Barreter,</hi> had not brought it in a <hi>Cloke Bag</hi> behind him to <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another <hi>Artifice</hi> to bring more Game into the <hi>Net,</hi> is, by Clubbing with a Non Con Holder-Forth, and taking a Houſe between them <hi>conjunctim et Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratim,</hi> with a Convenient Room next the Street to <hi>Pray in,</hi> which Toles in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to the <hi>Tubſter,</hi> and Clients to the <hi>Lawyer. Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> now join <hi>Hand</hi> in <hi>Hand,</hi> to promote each others <hi>Intereſts. Law</hi> Stalks for the advantage of <hi>Non Conformity,</hi> the <hi>Directory Setts</hi> for the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58572:14"/>benefit of <hi>Cooke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> and both like <hi>Monkies,</hi> cruſh their <hi>Fondlings</hi> into nothing, by Hugging and Embracing them in the Arms of <hi>Flattery.</hi> Popularity is always the Nurſe of <hi>Self Deſigns,</hi> and our brace of Beagles, being Maſters in that Art of <hi>Dolt catching,</hi> they purſue it with all manner of <hi>Craft</hi> and <hi>Induſtry.</hi> In Vacation time, when their <hi>Bellies</hi> and the <hi>Town</hi> are Empty, theſe narrow Soul'd Wretches make frequent Viſits among the <hi>Whigs,</hi> to ſave charges at home; for they keep a Houſe would ſtarve a <hi>Cat,</hi> and the <hi>Rats</hi> and <hi>Mice</hi> have deſerted it, and taken Sanctuary in the <hi>Church</hi> to mend their <hi>Quarters.</hi> Now they ſet up for <hi>Peace-makers,</hi> and reconcile all <hi>Differences</hi> and <hi>Diſputes</hi> among thoſe that have no <hi>Money,</hi> at the Price of a <hi>Supper</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, at the Expence of both Parties. If a wealthy <hi>Whig</hi> be ſick, the Holder-forth goes to viſit him, and being paid for <hi>Groaning</hi> by his Bed ſide, perſwades the <hi>Decumbent</hi> to ſend for our <hi>Whig-Lawyer,</hi> to make his Will, and <hi>ſet his Houſe out of Order,</hi> which he'l be ſure to do, to all Intents and Purpoſes; by making ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Ambiguous</hi> Clauſes, and <hi>dubious</hi> Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo's in the Will, as, after the <hi>Teſtator</hi>'s deceaſe, ſhall make his <hi>Relations</hi> ſpend the <hi>Fee-Simple</hi> in Quarreling about the <hi>Title,</hi> and conſume their <hi>Legacies</hi> in Suites with the <hi>Executors,</hi> where our Man of Law is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58572:14"/>ſure to be of One, if not both ſides, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Belphogor</hi> that rais'd the <hi>Devil</hi> is the fitteſt to <hi>Lay</hi> him. In making the <hi>Teſtament,</hi> he is obliged in Gratitude to put down <hi>Five Pounds</hi> for a Funeral <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> no matter whether the <hi>Sick-man</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires it, or not, 'tis but skipping that <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph</hi> when he reads it over; and by theſe under-hand Arts they <hi>Claw</hi> and <hi>Cram</hi> one another, in the Language of an Old <hi>Phanatick</hi> Poet:
<q>
                     <l>One <hi>Good Turn</hi> another Eeches,</l>
                     <l>Mend my <hi>Coat,</hi> I'le Patch thy <hi>Breeches.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> And that every <hi>Whig</hi>-Bird may have the plucking off of ſome Feathers from this languiſhing <hi>Fowl,</hi> towards making himſelf a <hi>Neſt,</hi> the Medicaſter <hi>Nomlas</hi> muſt now be ſent for, with his <hi>Roſy crucian Pantar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va's,</hi> and then <hi>Conſummatum eſt;</hi> you may write upon the Dying-man's Door, <hi>Lord have mercy upon him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Whigs</hi> engroſſing all the Arts of <hi>Money-catching</hi> among themſelves, our Lawyer is ſoon grown <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Opulent,</hi> and ſo <hi>Stiff</hi> and <hi>Proud,</hi> that he'd take it for an Affront that the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> ſhould call him <hi>Couſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this time he has purchaſed himſelf a Country-Seat, which he ne're intends to pay for, and <hi>Tuckled</hi> himſelf to a <hi>Wife,</hi> an Attorny's Daughter, that he bred up
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58572:15"/>himſelf by hand to make her fit for his Humor, which is as <hi>Croſs</hi> and <hi>Peeviſh,</hi> as ill Nature can make him. Among his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-Neighbours</hi> he Reigns with more Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than <hi>Nero</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the leaſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that is given him, or his Doxy <hi>Sara, Ruins</hi> whole Families. If a <hi>Horſe</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits a Treſpaſs, but one half hour, upon his Premiſes, the Price of a <hi>Writ,</hi> and a <hi>London</hi> Journey on the <hi>Beaſt</hi> muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure for the <hi>Damages,</hi> with many <hi>Hats</hi> and <hi>Scrapes,</hi> and <hi>God bleſs his Worſhip</hi> into the bargain. If a <hi>Cow</hi> does but look o're his <hi>Hedg,</hi> a Quarter of her <hi>Fat Calf,</hi> and the charge of a <hi>Latitat ad Reſpondend A Predict, in Placit Tranſgreſs,</hi> muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound for the Offence, or <hi>Take him Jaylor.</hi> The Country <hi>Wives</hi> ſo dread his Tyranny, that they Sew <hi>Shooes,</hi> on their <hi>Poultries</hi> Feet, for fear the <hi>Grim Sir,</hi> ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence a <hi>Suit</hi> againſt their Husband, for their <hi>Geeſe</hi> going <hi>Barefoot,</hi> and wiſh that <hi>Term</hi> time might laſt all the Year, ſince they can have no quiet but in his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, but are forc'd to <hi>Worſhip</hi> him as the <hi>Indians</hi> do the <hi>Devil,</hi> becauſe he ſhould not <hi>Devour</hi> them. But of all in the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinage, within the Reach of his Power, the <hi>Vicar of the Pariſh,</hi> is ſure to feel the weight of this Parchment Squires Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, tho' the Poor Eccleſiaſtick preſent him with more <hi>Tyth Pigs</hi> and <hi>Geeſe,</hi> than he can afford to eat in his family, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58572:15"/>purchaſe his own Peace and Quietneſs. However, his Innate <hi>Averſion</hi> to an <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox</hi> Clergy-man, and a Man of <hi>Sence</hi> and of a <hi>Genercus</hi> Education, will not ſuffer him him to be <hi>Juſt,</hi> nor <hi>Civil</hi> to a Man of that Character; and therefore diſparages the <hi>Vicar</hi>'s <hi>Preaching,</hi> tho' he never came to hear him, and teaches his <hi>Pariſhioners</hi> how to defraud him of his <hi>dues</hi> by <hi>Tricks</hi> and <hi>Quarks</hi> in Law, to ſupport an Interloping Seditious <hi>Canter;</hi> but he is ſtole up to the Term in a <hi>Stage</hi> Coach, and thither I muſt follow him, for being long ſince made a <hi>Knight,</hi> for being a Toole in the hands of a <hi>Duke,</hi> to revenge his quarr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l on an Innocent Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Gentlem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> and now growing near hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd; 'tis time for him, one would think, to lay aſide halting between <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney</hi> and <hi>Councel</hi> to vex the World, for if he conſult his Honour or Fame, 'tis hoped he will amend, and make Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe he has injur'd cauſleſly; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince having <hi>Ruin'd</hi> many Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and ſent Innocent Children a <hi>Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging;</hi> the Curſe is fallen upon himſelf, and his own, and that which was got o're the <hi>Devils back</hi> by the <hi>Father,</hi> is in a fair way of being <hi>Piſs'd</hi> againſt the <hi>Wall,</hi> or ſpent under a <hi>Whore's belly,</hi> by his two <hi>Ungratious</hi> Sons, that are become the greateſt <hi>Rakes</hi> and <hi>Debauches</hi> in the World, and not fit to be named where <hi>Vertue</hi> has a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58572:16"/>being; but inſtead of repenting, the Old <hi>Ape</hi> grows worſe and worſe; ſpends his time in watching his <hi>Wife,</hi> his <hi>Mony,</hi> and the <hi>Cupboard;</hi> is Retain'd in every <hi>Cauſe,</hi> only, <hi>to Annay the Enemy, perplex the Cauſe, and confound the</hi> Court <hi>with Noiſe and</hi> Nonſence; and let him enjoy his Humor in adding Oppreſſion to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Violence to Injury, Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to Wickedneſs, while he <hi>Lives;</hi> and then he needs not grudge to go to the <hi>Devil</hi> when he <hi>Dies;</hi> and ſo Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel Old <hi>Iſtra Daukes,</hi> and Levol Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Bold, Treacherous, Whig At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney.</head>
               <p>IS an Animal deſcended from the <hi>Plough Tail,</hi> ſwept out o'th' <hi>Shop,</hi> or kick'd from a <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the Peace's, or Lawyer's <hi>Clark</hi> into Gentleman, to <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize</hi> the Profeſſion of honeſt and fair Practiſing <hi>Attornies: Monſtrum horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum informe ingens cui lumen adeptum.</hi> A Writing-School is the height of his <hi>Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: Latin</hi> is his utter Averſion, and therefore cuts it off in the middle, for fear it ſhould accuſe him of breaking <hi>Priſcians</hi> Head, and crack his own
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58572:16"/>Credit in the Country, where for want of being a Scholar, he has taken great pains to make them believe he is one. Frequenting Conventicles has made him bold and ſaucy. His <hi>demure</hi> Looks ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated him into the acquaintance of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions,</hi> and writing <hi>Bills, Bonds</hi> and <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittancs</hi> from Preſidents at the fag end of an <hi>Almanack,</hi> has made him impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough, tho' but a Pen-feather'd Prig, to call himſelf an <hi>Attorney,</hi> and to eat the Bread and Cheeſe out of Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner's mouths, that are <hi>Regularly</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified for that Employment. He began to look toward the Law, by Soliciting for Criminals at the <hi>Quarter Seſſions,</hi> where the favour of his Maſter Juſtice, who went <hi>ſuips</hi> in his <hi>Fees,</hi> gave him the Reputation of a Man of Knowledge. Thence like a Butter-fly Adulterated into a Maggot, he became an <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney</hi> in Wapentake, Leete, and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Courts, and at laſt by employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an able <hi>Entring Clark,</hi> commences an Attorney at large, without being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Read a <hi>Writ,</hi> or diſtingdiſh a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Proceſs</hi> from an <hi>Execution:</hi> And the People always favouring every Limping Profeſſor of their own <hi>Creation,</hi> he is ſooner employ'd than a Clark fit for his Buſineſs. He has little more in him than <hi>Garbage,</hi> and the <hi>Shape</hi> of a Man, and when you have beheld his Leather-<hi>Ears</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58572:17"/>and <hi>Shabby</hi> Outſide, you have ſeen him through, and need employ your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery no farther. His Reaſon is meerly <hi>Whig</hi> Example, and his Actions are not guided by his <hi>Underſtanding;</hi> but he ſees what other Men of the fame <hi>Cut</hi> do, and 'tis his whole Buſineſs to immitate them. The chief Burden of his <hi>Brain,</hi> is the <hi>Whiggiſh</hi> Carriage of his Body, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Face in a Frame of <hi>Nonconformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> advances his Renown among the Crop-Ear'd Brethren of <hi>Bands and Bugle-Cuffs,</hi> who will go to Law with their <hi>Fathers,</hi> rather than this Muſhroom Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Quill</hi> ſhall be deſtitute of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. Among Knowing Attornies, he looks a Tripe-Man's Aſſs, loaded with Offal and Excrements; but among the Vulgar Try, like a Sage Common-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor. All his Diſcourſes are Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims in Law, and Definitive Decrees, with a <hi>Thus it is, and thus it muſt be;</hi> but will never humble his Authority to give a Reaſon for it, unleſs he ſtumbles on a Text to his purpoſe, and then he proves it by Dint of <hi>Scripture.</hi> Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Words are <hi>Hebrew</hi> Characters; if he ſays he will do any thing for you, it is as much as if he had Sworn he would not, and you muſt always Spell him back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward before you can Read him. He has neither the Theory, nor Practice of the Law; but his own Villanous Arts except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58572:17"/>is wholly ſteered by the Compaſs of his <hi>Entring-Clerk:</hi> He is at beſt but two ſteps above a <hi>Fool;</hi> a great many below a Wiſe and Honeſt Man, but the <hi>Phanatick Knave</hi> has predominancy over all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Faculties; and ſo he is leſs dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in the appearance of a <hi>Devil</hi> than a <hi>Saint.</hi> If he ſays he Loves you, be ſure he hates you; for he has the Art of Laughing in your Face, whilſt he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning to cut your Throat with a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. All that are ſo weak as to <hi>truſt him,</hi> he is ſure to <hi>betray</hi> them; will ſpoil a good Cauſe by his Treacherous Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Sell the beſt Clyent he has to his <hi>Adverſary,</hi> when he has made the moſt of him. In <hi>London</hi> he frequents all the Seditious Coffee-houſes to find out Quarrels, or make 'em, and at the Price of a <hi>Penny</hi> gains a <hi>Pound</hi> in ſetting Friends at Variance, and under pretence of knowing ſomething of the matter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or having managed the like Cauſe for another, firſt kindles the Coal into a Blaze, and then gets Money on both ſides to quench it. A <hi>Conventicle</hi> is his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> where he hears the News of who is at <hi>Law,</hi> and there he employs his and the <hi>Devils Brokers, Solicitors and Splitters,</hi> to keep up the Market of Quarrels at <hi>Common-Law,</hi> till he can bring the Liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Fools into <hi>Chancery,</hi> and be the Factor to ſell both the <hi>Parcels</hi> by <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58572:18"/>at the Price of <hi>Who bids moſt</hi> by an Inch of Candle. The <hi>Mayors</hi> and <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs</hi> Courts, and the <hi>Marſhalſea,</hi> are his leſſer Mints, for Coining Cauſes of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where he Squeezes his Clyent for a while, and then by a Writ of <hi>Habe as,</hi> removes <hi>Corpus</hi> to the Jayl and <hi>Cauſa</hi> to be new Alloyed by a <hi>Melius Inquirendum</hi> at the Melting-houſe at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> He knows nothing but the Guts and Querks of the Law, and in that is ſo great a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that he ſeldom fails of Succeſs, for where he cannot Snap the Adverſe Attorney, he ſupplies all the Defects by Repeated <hi>Affidavits,</hi> and prolonging Suits by theſe Tricks and Shifts, at laſt makes them ready for <hi>Arbitration,</hi> where a Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Mutton and a Capon, and ſome Naſty Red, buries a Cauſe in an Hour, that if the Clyents had not been quite <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted,</hi> might have lived ſeven Years lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and run another <hi>Wild-Gooſe Chace</hi> through all the Courts in <hi>London, South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> by the Dextrous Management of our Upſtart, Ignorant, Knaviſh Attorny. In the Country a Conventicle is his Chimical <hi>Elabaratory,</hi> where from Calves-Brains, and the Gall of Diſſenters Spleens, ſteep'd in the Sour Milk of the Miſs applyed word, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> and <hi>Edibile,</hi> which fix'd in his Pockets, ſerves for all other purpoſes. Here he takes Notes from the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58572:18"/>
                  <hi>Holder-forth</hi> againſt the Biſhops, and <hi>Fees</hi> from the Auditors to cheat the <hi>Parſons</hi> of their great <hi>Tythes,</hi> and the <hi>Vicars</hi> of their <hi>Grunting</hi> Offerings, to Thatch the <hi>Boors</hi> heads with <hi>Bob</hi> Wigs, and <hi>Ring</hi> the Siſter Married <hi>Sowes</hi> on their <hi>Thumbs,</hi> and the yet Unexerciſed <hi>Shoates</hi> on their <hi>Middle</hi> Fingers. Like <hi>Pick Pockets,</hi> he haunts all the <hi>Markets</hi> and <hi>Fairs</hi> in the Country to get a Prize; and if his other <hi>Gins</hi> and <hi>Lime</hi> Twigs, does not catch the <hi>VVood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks</hi> by day light, at night he makes 'em <hi>Drunk,</hi> and ſets them a fighting to create Actions of <hi>Battery,</hi> and ſo gets <hi>double</hi> Fees, as <hi>Witneſs</hi> and <hi>Proſecutor,</hi> and when he has <hi>Wrack'd</hi> 'em ſufficiently himſelf, turns 'em over to the Lawyer for <hi>Execution.</hi> Two Desks and a Quire of Paper ſet him up. Sighing and Diſſembling in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle got him <hi>Practice;</hi> and he laugh'd at their Credulity in his Cloſet. <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Wrangling</hi> made him <hi>Rich,</hi> and he is thankful to his Benefactors by Cheriſhing them. His buſineſs would never give him time to caſt away a thought upon his <hi>Conſcience;</hi> therefore as he has liv'd by <hi>Cheating Men,</hi> now approaching towards the Grave, he intends to Cheat the <hi>Devil</hi> alſo; for having Early given him his <hi>Soul</hi> to aſſiſt him in getting Money, he he has now diſpoſed of it by <hi>Will</hi> another way, without relation had to the <hi>Prior</hi> Grant, and ſays, if the <hi>Devil</hi> ſhould make
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58572:19"/>his Claim at <hi>Doomeſday</hi> and Recover, he had yet a <hi>Trick</hi> left to <hi>Reverſe Judgment,</hi> but whether 'twill hold or not I much Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and know not how to ſend to have Mr. <hi>Sim</hi>'s Opinion in it, who by this time is able to reſolve the doubt infallibly. There is ſtill more filth in this Dung Cart, which I dare not ſtir, for fear of Infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Air, and poyſoning Mankind; and therefore all I ſhall adventure on at preſent, is, to tell my Reader in Sober ſadneſs, that the Practices of ſuch <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi> and <hi>Attornies,</hi> as I have been deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of, are ſo <hi>foul,</hi> and their <hi>Numbers</hi> ſo <hi>many,</hi> that in the Opinion of all ſober Men, they are become <hi>Nuſances,</hi> and <hi>Plagues</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Jugling <hi>Whig</hi> Phyſician</head>
               <p>IS a <hi>ſomething</hi> made of <hi>every thing,</hi> and ſignifies <hi>nothing;</hi> for let a <hi>Wretch</hi> be never ſo <hi>Miſerable,</hi> his <hi>Birth</hi> never ſo <hi>mean,</hi> his <hi>Fortune</hi> never ſo <hi>Low,</hi> his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> never ſo <hi>deſpicable,</hi> and his <hi>Parts</hi> never ſo <hi>Contemptible,</hi> and the Senſleſs Creature ſcarce worth any thing on this ſide <hi>Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> yet among ſome ſort of Men or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he paſſes Muſter for a good <hi>Phyſician,</hi> which lays and Indelible Blot upon the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58572:19"/>more <hi>Judicious,</hi> when they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by compariſon; but this is not the inſignificant centure of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the Univerſities alſo have but mean opinions of this ſort of Amphibious Animals. When their Students <hi>Merits</hi> will not entitle them to an <hi>Election</hi> among the Learned Tribes of Mathematicians, Aſtronomers, Divines, Civilians, nor Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, their Tutors <hi>Reprobate</hi> them to the Study of Phyſick: To have buſineſs at <hi>Bed-ſides,</hi> to Converſe with <hi>Cloſe-ſtool-Pans,</hi> and <hi>Urinals,</hi> and to live and Thrive by other Peoples <hi>Sickneſs;</hi> ſo it is abroad in the World, if a <hi>Farrier</hi> is too great a <hi>Dunce</hi> to live by his <hi>Blooding Stick, Dren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching-Horn,</hi> and taking out the <hi>Soles</hi> of Founder'd Horſes; let him but lay aſide his <hi>Leathern Apron,</hi> put on a <hi>Pluſh Coat,</hi> talk of <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Alkaly</hi>'s, tell the Men they are troubled with the <hi>Spleen,</hi> and the Women with the <hi>Vapours,</hi> tho' he employs no other Medicines for the Cure of them, than he did for his <hi>Horſe Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> yet he's ſoon call'd an <hi>Incomparable</hi> Phyſician, whoſe ſucceſs anſwers his Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated Judgment; and if to this Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, we add the Number of decayed Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Lame Surgeons, broken Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, Confident Mechanicks, Seventh Sons, Strawling Mountebanks, Licens'd Quacks, Sharking Empericks, Pox Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders, with all the goodly Gang of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58572:20"/>
                  <hi>Midwives,</hi> and <hi>Skilful</hi> Women, one would be tempted to think 'twas unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſary to ſtudy that <hi>Faculty,</hi> and that the whole pretence is a <hi>Cheat,</hi> ſince all Man and Womankind were Fools enough to make <hi>Phyſicians.</hi> Their Names you ſee are <hi>Legion,</hi> and ſince it would be the Works of an age, to deſcribe all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders; I ſhall only account for the Heads of the <hi>Herd,</hi> and bequeath the <hi>Hides</hi> of the reſt to the <hi>Tanner;</hi> and firſt I will ſingle out,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Univerſity Toping <hi>Whig</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</head>
               <p>WHO having the <hi>Annuity</hi> of a <hi>Youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> Brother, and but the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an <hi>Elder,</hi> a Latudinarian in his Life, and at beſt a <hi>Septick</hi> in Religion; finding his <hi>Income</hi> would not anſwer his <hi>Expences,</hi> he reſolves upon eſpouſing ſome Employment; and being told by his <hi>Tutor,</hi> that the Practice of <hi>Phyſick</hi> was the eaſieſt, and oftentimes the moſt <hi>Advantagious,</hi> for the uſe he intended it. Our Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man immediately ſets his Face towards the <hi>Phyſick Garden,</hi> and by taking a <hi>Turn</hi> there now and then, with an <hi>Herball</hi> in one Hand, and a <hi>Woman</hi> in the other,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58572:20"/>he ſoon Commences a <hi>Botaniſt.</hi> His next Step is to the <hi>Anatomy Lecture,</hi> where he has the <hi>Patience</hi> to hear all, and the <hi>good Nature</hi> to carry away nothing, but what he brought with him, <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> a <hi>Torn</hi> Gown to ſhew his <hi>Standing,</hi> and Mony in his Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket to treat the <hi>Reader</hi> at the Tavern, to ſhew his <hi>Underſtanding.</hi> From the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern he returns to his <hi>College,</hi> and covers the Table in his Study, with <hi>Galen, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> for the ſake of his <hi>Problems.</hi> Next in order, are laid open <hi>Veſlingus Bartholinus</hi> and <hi>Riolanus,</hi> and Contemplating a while upon the <hi>Naked</hi> Gentlefolks, goes to ſleep upon his Couch to improve his Contemplations, and thence to <hi>Barnwel</hi> to put his Notions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Practice;</hi> where an unhappy accident, produced a good Effect, made him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience a Cure upon himſelf, before he <hi>practiſed</hi> upon others; and gave him a greater opportunity of <hi>Reading,</hi> than ever he allowed himſelf before, ſince he ſaw the <hi>Univerſity;</hi> being emancipated from the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> hands, and at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, all his Diſcourſes ſmell of the <hi>Gally Pot,</hi> and his Chamber converted into a <hi>Slaughter-Houſe</hi> of <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Cats,</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove himſelf in <hi>Anatomy,</hi> and give him the Name of a <hi>Student</hi> in <hi>Phyſick!</hi> Never did Man take a degree to leſſer purpoſe, for he was <hi>Doctor</hi> without the Charge of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58572:21"/>the <hi>Sham Dignity,</hi> and it added nothing to the Credit of his Learning afterward.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Cambridge</hi> he removes to a City or Market Town, and with a <hi>Degree</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Back, ſets up for killing Men, Women, and Children, <hi>Secundem Artem,</hi> and makes his practiſe a Confirmation of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Idiom, where the ſame Word ſignifies <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and <hi>dead Men,</hi> and were no way beneficial to the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> but by Uſurping the Office of the <hi>Plague, War,</hi> or <hi>Famine,</hi> in ridding the Nation of its <hi>Infectious</hi> Inhabitants. Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians time out of mind were all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Beaſts by <hi>Degeneration,</hi> if <hi>St. Luke,</hi> and a few others, had not been exceptions from that general Rule, and to wipe out the reproach of <hi>Athiſm,</hi> our Mr. <hi>Doctor,</hi> being no further from an Atheiſt, than from himſelf, ſaw a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Engaging in a <hi>Party,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a <hi>Shew</hi> of Religion to advance his Intereſt, but where to fix was the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. The Church of <hi>England</hi> party, he knew were for the Learned in all Profeſſions, and there his <hi>Cake</hi> was <hi>Dowe;</hi> but knowing the <hi>Whigs</hi> were all ſtiles, and Props to another, and that the Skin of an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> was as fit for the Shoulders of a <hi>Phanatick,</hi> as if it were made for him, it ſoon determined his choice, and now <hi>fall down Atheiſt, Riſe up Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi> till he is able to reaſſume his proper
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58572:21"/>Character. That is, till he has made his <hi>Fortune,</hi> and is ſo much above the World, that he can ſcorn and Laugh at all below him. <hi>Hypooriſy</hi> is now his <hi>Theme,</hi> and, with the help of the <hi>Devil</hi> and his Agents he ſoon acquires perfection in it, and Mimicks a <hi>Preciſian</hi> as exactly, as if <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſon</hi> had been his Father, a Jeſuite his Grandſire, his Mother a Quaker, and all his Relations Independents. He patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bears the Reproofs of the Female Sex, when they bring him Patients, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes Reformations. If a Siſter tells him ſhe hear's he's a <hi>Great drinker,</hi> he anſwers he is of a <hi>Hot</hi> Conſtitution, and very <hi>Thirſty,</hi> but for time to come, he'd drink <hi>Water</hi> with his <hi>Wine,</hi> to allay the <hi>Scandal.</hi> If another repimands him for being a <hi>continual Smoaker,</hi> he ſays (with ſome Emotion) he'l go home and burn all his <hi>Pipes</hi> and <hi>Tobacco.</hi> If his <hi>Cravat</hi> be a Size too Long, there's enough o'th own to make it Shorter, and ſo banters, befools, and humors them both at once, and ſets them a <hi>Goſſiping</hi> from Houſe to Houſe, to cry up the Skill of their New <hi>Convert,</hi> and Pump <hi>Guineas</hi> into his Pocket, till they have made him as Proud as <hi>Lucifer,</hi> as <hi>Salacious</hi> as a Pamper'd <hi>Cardinal,</hi> and as <hi>Inſolent</hi> as a <hi>Baud</hi> in a Brandy Shop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58572:22"/>
               <head>The Decayed Gentleman <hi>Whig</hi> Phyſician.</head>
               <p>HAving Squander'd away his <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> and wearied out his <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and Acquaintance, by thruſting in his <hi>Elbows</hi> at the lower end of their <hi>Tables,</hi> and borrowing Money out of their Pockets, finding his <hi>Hawk,</hi> his <hi>Gun,</hi> and his <hi>Setting-Dog,</hi> the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of <hi>Spend thrifts,</hi> and younger <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> will no longer maintain him, he begins to Study the neareſt way of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king others greater <hi>Fools</hi> than himſelf, and having long hung in the balance of ſeveral Opinions, without throwing his whole ſelf into either Scale, at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to be a <hi>Whig</hi> in <hi>General,</hi> ſo that no party ſhall call him abſolutely their own, and yet all live in hopes of his <hi>Converſion,</hi> from a Sharking <hi>Rake</hi> into a Diſſembling Hypocritical <hi>Reformiſt.</hi> Having gain'd this Point, in being thought a <hi>Whig</hi> in General, and ſeeing himſelf that the World had Caſheir'd him as a <hi>Needy,</hi> Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome <hi>Intruder,</hi> now <hi>clas'd</hi> again in a more hopeful Predicament, like a Man a Drowning, faſtens upon any thing next at hand; and among other of his <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack'd</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58572:22"/>Qualities, having happily loſt <hi>Shame</hi> and common <hi>Modeſty,</hi> he borrows a Shillings of his Brother's Footmen, buys him a <hi>Urinal,</hi> and with a few unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellible Receipts, found after her Death in his <hi>Grandmothers</hi> Cloſet, among other precious Receipts of <hi>Diſtilling, Chirurgery,</hi> and <hi>Cookery,</hi> he ſets up for an <hi>Emperical Phyſician,</hi> and ſtumbling on a Cure by chance, or being by, when beneficial. Nature relieved her ſelf, he was Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as the Agent, and immediately gets the Reputation of an <hi>Excellent Phyſician;</hi> and all ſorts of Whigs cry him up, in hopes at laſt he will eſpouſe their Intereſt, and credit their <hi>Barn</hi> with the Company of a <hi>Doctor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now he thumbs <hi>Culpeper</hi>'s <hi>Engliſh</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, and his <hi>London Diſpenſatory,</hi> and having retrieved as much Latin as will compound a Bill for a Purge or Vomit, that names him as Learned, as if he had been a Member of the College, or had bought a Degree of Doctor at <hi>Leiden,</hi> or <hi>Mentpelier.</hi> He is a very vain Creature, but above all things hates to be thought ſo, tho from Head to Heel he is his own <hi>Cryer,</hi> and makes Proclamation of it. The Profeſſors of all other <hi>Crafts,</hi> are commended, or decryed, by a veritable Character; but <hi>Phyſitians</hi> are ſafe under every Denomination; for the Good pleaſe ſome, the Bad others, and the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58572:23"/>Worſt have their Admirers. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Fate</hi> and <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> is his great Aſſylum, for when with his Inarti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial <hi>Slaps</hi> and Emperical <hi>Noſtrums,</hi> he has emptied his Patients Pockets, and exhauſted his Vital Spirits, he leaves him Gaſping, ſaying, <hi>His Time is come, God will have it ſo,</hi> cover him up, and ſend for the Parſon to give him his <hi>Viati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Mechanick, or Scoundrel <hi>Whig Phyſician</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IS a mixture of Broken Tradeſman, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Serving-Man, and Diſcarded <hi>Horſtler; Party per pale</hi> Black Coat, and Blue Apron, who from curing Cut-Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Kib'd Heels, or from adminiſtring <hi>Tobacco Clyſters</hi> to cure Horſes of the <hi>Bottes,</hi> falls to practiſing upon Men, to get the Women new <hi>Husbands,</hi> and upon <hi>Women</hi> to recruit their Husband's craſie Credit, with another <hi>Marriake Portion;</hi> and in this kind of Piking both Sexes o'er the Perch, ſucceeds ſo luckily, that he ſoon arrives at the Honour of being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Phyſician.</hi> He has no Learning, can ſcarce write his Name, but is well ſtockt with what ſerves his Purpoſe better, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58572:23"/>Ignorance and Impudence,</hi> for which he is indebted neither to Men nor Books, for they were Born with him, and he has only fortified them by Uſe and Cuſtom, and ſo there is as much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween what he appears, and what he is, as between a Hot Whore in a Vizard Mask, and a Natural and well-temper'd Beauty. However he has his Excellency, and that is in <hi>Holding forth</hi> ſometimes in a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> and eſpecially in <hi>conjuring</hi> with a Urinal, and ſhaking it into a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Diſcovery of the Patient's Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; when all experienced Men in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick know, that this Pretence is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Cheat,</hi> and no certainty at all to be gather'd from it, tho' you glare in the <hi>Piſs-pot</hi> till you are blinded with the Steem of it; and yet ſo abominably fond are the deluded Mob of theſe Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that inſtead of communicating their Diſeaſes to the Doctor by an Intelligible Meſſenger, or Writing, they Piſs their Minds in their Water, and hazard their Lives on an Ambiguous Anſwer, which he Pumpt from, and returns back by her that brought it.</p>
               <p>In this Cheating Bubling Trade, our Mechanick by his Pump, Screw, and Knaviſh Arts of <hi>Confederacy,</hi> has gain'd more Credit than is due to ſuch an Illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Aſs,</hi> who by peeping in the <hi>Urinal,</hi> preſumes to tell you whether a Holy Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58572:24"/>be gravidated, the Sex in the Womb, who got it, the Parties Name, the place where ſhe lives, and even what <hi>Religion</hi> ſhe is of, with other <hi>Secret Diſeaſes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Women, not fit to be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd but in their Bed-chamber. If you ſend your Urinal to this <hi>Piſs Prophet,</hi> you muſt reſolve to be ſick, for he'll ne'er leave handling it, till he has ſhaked it into a Diſeaſe. If he viſit a <hi>Patient,</hi> he tells him his Diſtemper will be <hi>Nothing,</hi> and at the ſame time tells all his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he cannot eſcape without a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; ſo that if the Patient recover, after the <hi>Urinal-Jugler</hi> has ſentenced him to Death, 'tis imputed to his powerful <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies,</hi> and if he Dies, it cries up the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his Judgment in <hi>Fortune-tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and that knew well enough what would become of him. See this <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Hangman</hi> ſtanding at a Sick Man's Bed ſide! How Magiſterially he looks, ſaying, <hi>All is well,</hi> when his Patient is Languiſhing by the Medicines he has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him. If the Poor Man complains he is ſcorched with Heat, <hi>'Tis all for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Nature is caſting out the Heat to cool the Vitals: If he ſays he is benumb'd with Cold, and Aguiſh Shiverings, <hi>'Tis a good Sign,</hi> he knew his <hi>Juleps</hi> would quench that extream Fire: Nay, when the Patient is almoſt dead, and has loſt his Speech, he ſays his Feaver is at extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58572:24"/>and leaving him; and then ſteals off, and leaves the Patient Dying, with abundance of <hi>good Signs and Tokens.</hi> The Sick Man's Friends ſtop him, to ſee the Fit over. No! He cannot ſtay, Death and he have a Quarrel, and muſt not meet for fear of Blows, when he was only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid the Corps ſhould Bleed, becauſe the Murderer was preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Traveller, or Strawling <hi>Whig Phyſician.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving Idled away a Hundred and Thirty Days, and Nine Hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, and brought Home a Fool at laſt; to quench the heat of his Phanatick Zeal and Lechery, he takes himſelf to a Wife without a Fortune, for a Cooler; and then as his laſt Shift, the poor Devil profeſſes the <hi>Practice of Phyſick</hi> to maintain her. Here the <hi>Medick</hi> and the <hi>Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant</hi> are united in the ſame Perſon; and we may treat him like the Medicaſter in <hi>Plautus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Grip. <hi>Num Medicus quaeſo es?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lab. <hi>Imo adipol una litera plus ſum quam Medicus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Grip. <hi>Tum tu Mendicus eſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lab. <hi>Titigiſti Acu.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58572:25"/>
               <p>And ſo like the Phyſitian <hi>Eudemus,</hi> is only qualified for a Pimp to ſome Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Perſonage, or to drudge out his Days in Miſery. 'Tis a Wonder among all the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> that he ſhould want pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; being <hi>Whig</hi> Born, <hi>Whig</hi> Bred, <hi>Whig</hi> by Education, <hi>Whig</hi> by Practice; and as a Meritorious Act for the Propation of the Species is ingeminated into the <hi>Right ſtrain</hi> of Factious <hi>Breeders,</hi> who ſeldom fail to promote the Intereſt of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. He has alſo made an Intereſt among all the <hi>Noncon Tubſters,</hi> to promulgate his Abilities among all the <hi>Qualmiſh Siſters;</hi> which like <hi>Pocky Bills</hi> plaſtred upon <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Poſts,</hi> cry Work for a Mender of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy Skins, Ulcers, or Fiſtula's in <hi>Ano.</hi> He is alſo at Fee with <hi>Bowds, Midwives,</hi> and Mercenary <hi>Nurſes.</hi> He runs about with News and Lyes againſt the Court. Hangs at the Fagg-End of <hi>Whiggiſh Lords.</hi> Speaks Cramp Words to the <hi>Ladies,</hi> ſtands Bare to the <hi>Chamber-Maids,</hi> Careſſes the <hi>Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> but is ſuch an egregious <hi>carry-Tale,</hi> and <hi>Lyar;</hi> ſuch a common <hi>Makebate,</hi> and <hi>Diſſembling Hollow-hearted Fawing Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> that he is fit for no Company but his Brother <hi>Notſallows,</hi> with whom I'll leave him, till he that owns them both, ſhall call for 'em.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:58572:25"/>
               <head>The Bluſtering Pendantick <hi>Poetical Phyſician.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IS a greater Proficient in Rhiming than Reaſoning, and underſtands quantity in Verſe, better than in <hi>Pharmacy;</hi> for tho' one be his Trade, the other next to Courting and Drinking is his Buſineſs. He ſets up for a <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> by affronting <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hypocrates;</hi> for a <hi>Gentleman</hi> in abuſing his <hi>Betters,</hi> and for a <hi>Wit</hi> by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his want of <hi>Manners.</hi> He Rakes into other mens Lives, and ſtains their Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Reputation, makes them look like himſelf. By Sordid <hi>Flattery,</hi> and Vile Abuſes, he ſtrives to get himſelf a <hi>good</hi> Name, tho' all in Vain, for he has a Bad one already, that will laſt him his Life time. I know not whether to call him <hi>Papiſt, Church-man</hi> or <hi>Whig,</hi> being Specializ'd by no Name, but qualified for the worſt of all, which I would not gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify him in, if any other appellation could render him more infamous. The <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance</hi> of being a <hi>Scholar,</hi> has made him a degree and half above a Mad-man, and nothing but a ſevere <hi>Bedlam</hi> Courſe can bring him to his Senſes. The <hi>Preſs</hi> is ſometimes his <hi>Mint,</hi> for want of a Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58572:26"/>
                  <hi>Patient,</hi> and Stamps him now and then a <hi>Six-pence</hi> or two, in reward of the baſe Coin his Poetical <hi>Pamphlet.</hi> He is an <hi>Ubiquitarian</hi> in his Walks, and may be found any where, ſooner than in his Study. He has much time lying by him, and knows not how to ſpend it; and were it not for the <hi>Tavern,</hi> the <hi>Play-houſe,</hi> and the <hi>Bawdy-houſe,</hi> he would die for want of <hi>Employment.</hi> In Phyſick he acts like a <hi>Fencer,</hi> and kills Men in <hi>Teirce</hi> and <hi>Quart,</hi> and then like a Poet, covers their <hi>Groves,</hi> and his own <hi>Miſdoings,</hi> with an <hi>Epitaph.</hi> He is very familiar and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickſom with his <hi>Apothecary</hi>'s Wife, and becauſe the Doctor is <hi>Agent,</hi> the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary muſt be <hi>Patient,</hi> whom he makes amends, by writing long <hi>Bills,</hi> and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſick <hi>Patients</hi> in long diſeaſed <hi>Sheets,</hi> to do <hi>Pennance</hi> for the Doctor's <hi>Lechery.</hi> His Practice is wholly among the <hi>Female Sex,</hi> whom he <hi>Ogles</hi> and <hi>Bunters</hi> in the Pit, and wire-draws them into Sin, that he may ſhare in their <hi>Gaines,</hi> by curing the <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> that attend it. To recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend himſelf to the <hi>Ladies,</hi> he has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a <hi>Diſtich</hi> ready, in commendation of their <hi>Lap-Dogs,</hi> and often wiſhes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in their Places. He pulls off his <hi>Gloves</hi> to ſhew his <hi>White</hi> hand, <hi>Laughs</hi> at all things, pleaſant or ſerious, to ſhew his <hi>White</hi> Teeth, and throws back his <hi>Wig,</hi> to ſhew his <hi>Eares</hi> are on, and well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58572:26"/>Sometimes he <hi>Sings,</hi> to delight the fair Sex, and ſometimes <hi>Sighs</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> or that the Devil keeps a <hi>Dancing-School</hi> in his Pocket, whom the Women are oblig'd to eject, by the appearance of an <hi>Angel</hi> for a retaining Fee, againſt they have occaſion to be <hi>Sick,</hi> or lye from their <hi>Husbands.</hi> In ſhort, he is <hi>Duplices Profeſſiones,</hi> both <hi>Merry Andrew</hi> and <hi>Mountebank,</hi> and all his Art is <hi>Deluſion;</hi> and if he's diſpleas'd with that Character, he muſt thank himſelf; for as he began to <hi>Draw</hi> without occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion given, ſo he's like to put up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Aſtrological <hi>Whig</hi> Phyſician.</head>
               <p>THAT has Twelve Houſes of his own in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and never a one upon <hi>Earth,</hi> to Eat, Drink, or Sleep in, is a meer <hi>Inſect</hi> of Idleneſs, a Stationary <hi>Gipſy,</hi> a <hi>Maggot</hi> bred in <hi>Lily</hi>'s Noſe, or <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s Poſteriors, and ſmells as Rank of <hi>Fool</hi> and <hi>Knave,</hi> as the Bub of a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge</hi> at Pairing-time. He can't be rankt among the <hi>Whigs</hi> in point of Religion, for he has none at all, and 'twould ruine his Practice of <hi>Figure-flinging</hi> to be thought to have any; and therefore muſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58572:27"/>be placed among the Politick <hi>Whigs,</hi> that fright the fooliſh World with incredible Fears, and inviſible Dangers; that talk of nothing but <hi>Earth-quakes, Blaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Stars, Dreadful Comets,</hi> and raiſe ſuch <hi>Predictions</hi> from them, as will gratify the Itch of a Seditious Party, and kindle Combuſtions among a mal-contented People, who delight to hear of <hi>Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and Diſturbances, rather than en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a continued <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Proſperity.</hi> This <hi>Sot</hi> pretends to know every thing, but what concerns himſelf, and in that is the ignoranteſt Aſs in the Kingdom. He knows (if you have ſo little ſenſe to believe him) all the Tranſactions in the <hi>Starry</hi> Regiment, can Calculate the Fate of Kingdoms, and calls himſelf a <hi>Privy-Councellor</hi> in the Superior Regions; but knows not when propitious <hi>Jupiter</hi> will oblige him with a New Pair of <hi>Shooes,</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> bring him Money to mend his <hi>Old ones.</hi> He can direct other Men to find <hi>Hidden Treaſure,</hi> while himſelf wants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairs both at <hi>Heels</hi> and <hi>Elbows.</hi> He knows all the Intrigues between <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus;</hi> but not the <hi>Chandler</hi> that Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colded him for a Farthing worth of <hi>Oat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal.</hi> He knows who broke his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Houſe, but not who laid his <hi>Tail</hi> at his own Door. He knows all your wants and wiſhes, and can Infaliblly reſolve all your doubts, by a <hi>Horary
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58572:27"/>Queſtion.</hi> If your <hi>Wife</hi> or <hi>Miſs,</hi> be Six Months gone with <hi>Child,</hi> he can tell you, that in three more, in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, ſhe will be <hi>Delivered;</hi> and if your <hi>Houſe</hi> be ready to fall on your Head, that 'tis time to remove to another. He knows all the Grand <hi>Secrets,</hi> and <hi>Occult</hi> Qualities in <hi>Nature;</hi> as why a <hi>Fly</hi> ſhould have <hi>Six Legs,</hi> and an Elephant or Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medary but <hi>Four!</hi> why a <hi>Cat</hi> when ſhe is pleas'd Erects her <hi>Tail,</hi> and a <hi>Dog</hi> Wags his croſs his Stern? Why <hi>Crabs</hi> go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and <hi>Lice</hi> move forwards? With other uſeful and wonderful <hi>Phenomena's.</hi> If the Queſtion be in <hi>Phyſick,</hi> he knows all your <hi>Diſtempers</hi> as perfectly by his <hi>Aſtrological Scheme,</hi> as if he had travell'd through your <hi>Stomach</hi> and <hi>Guts</hi> to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perviſe your <hi>Intrails.</hi> He can Cure <hi>All</hi> Diſeaſes tho' a Hundred miles off, by <hi>Sigills, Charms</hi> and <hi>Teleſmans;</hi> but is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to drop to Pieces with the <hi>Pox,</hi> and cannot <hi>Cure</hi> himſelf. In brief, among all the Fry of <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Knaves, Sharks</hi> and <hi>Cheats</hi> that pretend to be <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> is the moſt incurable <hi>Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb,</hi> and erranteſt <hi>Impoſter:</hi> From o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers you have ſomething for your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but from him nothing but <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Damnation</hi> for Deſerting your God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Directions of his Holy <hi>Oracles,</hi> to Conſult with the Devil by Proxy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58572:28"/>
               <head>The Chimical Whig Phyſician.</head>
               <p>IS an <hi>Extract</hi> of <hi>Enthuſiaſtick</hi> Foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of a Formal <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite;</hi> the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of a Broken <hi>Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> the Elixir of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> diſtilled from the <hi>Acida Inſipida</hi> of <hi>Paracelſus's</hi> Noſe in the height of his <hi>Lunacy,</hi> when he boaſted of making Man <hi>Immortal,</hi> and died himſelf at <hi>Two and Thirty:</hi> All theſe <hi>Petrified</hi> in the Lake <hi>Lemain,</hi> at length produced the <hi>Lapis Infernalis</hi> of a <hi>Chimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Phyſician;</hi> which gilded over with the <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Saintſhip</hi> of a ſtarch'd <hi>Whig,</hi> has advanc'd many Impudent and Illiterate <hi>Mechanicks</hi> to the Dignity of <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> and they think it as much their <hi>Due,</hi> as if they had Learning to deſerve it. The moſt remarkable of them all, is the Canting, Confident Whig <hi>nomlaS,</hi> who by obliging the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> with a Heap of Corrupt <hi>Tranſlations</hi> and <hi>Family Pills,</hi> has work'd himſelf into an Eſtate, by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Brother <hi>Whigs</hi> on <hi>Dead</hi> Mens Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands. He has Rummaged all the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuries of <hi>Nature,</hi> to find out the <hi>Gas ſive Ens Sulphuris,</hi> which he gives in large quantities to his Brethren, that by accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their Bodies to the uſe of <hi>Brimſtone</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:58572:28"/>here, they may better endure it in another World; for ſo <hi>Mithridates</hi> made himſelf <hi>Unpoyſonable.</hi> By Eves dropping a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave of <hi>Newington Phyloſophers,</hi> he has attain'd the Art of making <hi>Eeles</hi> of <hi>Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hair</hi> ſteep'd in Water, and will oblige the <hi>Royal Fiſhery</hi> with the <hi>Proceſs,</hi> for the good of the Subſcribers. By Indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pains, and continual Study in Hidden Sciences, he has grop'd out the <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> Art of <hi>Coſchinomancy,</hi> Anglice <hi>the Seive and Sciſſars,</hi> and intends to publiſh it next <hi>Term,</hi> as a Supplement, to help ſell his <hi>Practice of Phyſick;</hi> that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion may not be converted (like his other Works) into <hi>Waſt Paper.</hi> How much are we obliged to this <hi>Semi bovem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Virum,</hi> and <hi>Semi virumque Bovem,</hi> half <hi>Quack,</hi> half <hi>Tubſter,</hi> or <hi>Kirleus</hi> and <hi>B—ges</hi> blended into an <hi>Individuum Vagum.</hi> He that ſhews the height of his Learning, in Canting, Snaphling, and commending himſelf and his <hi>Medicines</hi> in an unintelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Dialect: Which muſt be attributed to the Heat of his Furnace, and the Fumes of <hi>Piſs, Sutt,</hi> and <hi>Sulpher,</hi> which have <hi>Exſiccatted</hi> his Brains, and ſence can't be expected from him, till they have been <hi>Refrigerated</hi> in the <hi>Ditch ſide Auqasduct.</hi> He has more <hi>Quixotiſms</hi> in <hi>Chimiſtry,</hi> than Prince <hi>Butler</hi> in Politicks, or his Brother <hi>Dick Stafford</hi> in Divinity: Is as near gaining the <hi>Phyloſophers Stone,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:58572:29"/>as <hi>Van Helmont</hi> the <hi>Univerſal Medeicine,</hi> and nothing but <hi>Fleet-Ditch</hi> ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him, and Mountains of <hi>Diamonds.</hi> All his Medicines are <hi>Hermetical</hi> Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to name them looks like <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring.</hi> He has an <hi>Eſſence</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> a <hi>Milk</hi> of the <hi>Moon,</hi> an <hi>Extract</hi> of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Stars,</hi> the <hi>Humidum Radicale</hi> of <hi>Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> the <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Flint,</hi> the <hi>Magiſtery of Pearls,</hi> the <hi>Elixer</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Roſy Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Pantarva,</hi> and the <hi>Soul</hi> of this World, and that in the <hi>Moon:</hi> All which are to be ſold in his <hi>Elaboratory,</hi> at the price of your <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> if you ſwallow them; and will keep good (if ever they were ſo) as long as a <hi>Whig</hi> can retain a <hi>Secret,</hi> a <hi>Poet</hi> keep <hi>Mony,</hi> or <hi>nomlaS</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf within the Bounds of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty,</hi> who is no more to be <hi>believed,</hi> when he boaſts of his <hi>Cures,</hi> than the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> if he ſhould expound upon the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> but I have taken more pains with him, than he is worth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt ſet him aſide, to make room for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58572:29"/>
               <head>The Stately <hi>Methodical Whig</hi> Phyſician, or</head>
               <p>A <hi>Grave</hi> Sir in a Gilded <hi>Chariot,</hi> with two Laced <hi>Liveries,</hi> to beſpeak his <hi>Grandure,</hi> and raiſe the Price of his <hi>Viſits,</hi> who boaſts that with <hi>Opium,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> he can cure all Diſeaſes, which he but <hi>Pallitates</hi> for a time, and then ſends them to <hi>ſleep</hi> with their <hi>Fathers.</hi> He enters your Chamber with a <hi>Cloſe</hi> Mouth, but an <hi>Openhand,</hi> for like <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lams Aſs,</hi> he will not ſpeak, till he has ſeen three Angels; and then leaving a <hi>Scrawl</hi> to his <hi>Apothecary,</hi> which he can <hi>Read</hi> but cannot <hi>Conſtrue,</hi> the <hi>Don</hi> is in haſt to go to a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> but has order'd his <hi>Lacquey,</hi> to call him out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as ſoon as he is ſet, as if to a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient; when 'twas only to <hi>Bubble</hi> the Congregation into an Opinion that he is a Man of <hi>Great Practiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Holder-Forth</hi> takes the <hi>Hint,</hi> and prays aloud for his Succeſs: Which in the Modern Phraſe of Phyſicians, is crying Work for the <hi>Tinker.</hi> For this Service the <hi>Non Con</hi> has his Dinner with the <hi>Doctor,</hi> and they drink Wine ſo long, till both their <hi>Noſes</hi> are as <hi>Red</hi> and <hi>Fiery,</hi> as if they had been made
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58572:30"/>by a Drunken <hi>Smith,</hi> that after he had <hi>Forg'd</hi> them, forgot to <hi>Quench</hi> 'em, and then the <hi>Vultures</hi> take their Flights for New Quarrey, to make work for one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Among one Hundred of theſe <hi>Methodical Quacks,</hi> you ſhall ſcarce find five <hi>Rational Phyſicians:</hi> Their <hi>Ne plus Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra</hi> in <hi>Acute</hi> diſeaſes are <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Bark, and <hi>Opium.</hi> In <hi>Chronical</hi> Diſtempers, the <hi>Milk</hi> Dyet, the <hi>Steel</hi> Courſe, and <hi>Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Waters. As for Purging, Glyſtering, Bliſtering, and Bleeding, they are fortui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly Directed according to the <hi>Doctors</hi> Caprichio; and laſtly the <hi>Cordial</hi> Courſe, which is Spirit of <hi>Harts-horn,</hi> and Spirit of <hi>Piſs</hi> Succinated. Now for <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> who pretend to be <hi>Medici Legales dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tici, Rationales,</hi> and <hi>Veri Methodici,</hi> and yet tye up themſelves only to five <hi>Spuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Remedies, is as much <hi>Muntebanking</hi> in their <hi>Coaches,</hi> as vending <hi>Or vietan</hi> on a <hi>Stage</hi> is. Our <hi>Patient</hi> is now in a Courſe, and as the <hi>Dutchman</hi> ſays, being Ship'd with the <hi>Devil,</hi> muſt go over with him; however, finding the <hi>Veſſel</hi> is over-laden with <hi>Bark,</hi> a Conſult is deſired to drive out the <hi>Jeſuite;</hi> who after laying their Learned Heads tog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther, ſeeing the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> would not afford them a remedy againſt the <hi>Jeſuites Bark,</hi> the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> ſhall, and now comes in the <hi>God Stone,</hi> tho' they neither know what it is, nor the uſe of it, it muſt be thrown at the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58572:30"/>
                  <hi>Jeſuite.</hi> The Conſult are agreed, being all in a Confederacy, to employ none but thoſe of the ſame Gang. <hi>Flectere Si ne quo, Superos Acheronta movebo.</hi> He can but <hi>dye,</hi> and therefore they take the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of making <hi>Experiments,</hi> at the coſt of the <hi>Patients Life;</hi> and theſe Doctors having the Supreme Authority of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi> none dare queſtion 'em, for fear of falling into their <hi>Phyſick Inquiſition:</hi> Whereas another would have been hang'd for half the Barbirity they uſed againſt him: For theſe and many other <hi>Reaſons,</hi> (I ſuppoſe) the <hi>Babilonians</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Herodot</hi> l. 1.</note> Baniſh'd all Profeſſors of <hi>Phyſick</hi> out of their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; and <hi>Rome</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bodinus de Republ.</hi> p. 513.</note> likewiſe kept out all <hi>Phyſicians</hi> Six Hundred Years together, and in that time enjoy'd a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter degree of <hi>Health,</hi> by the Natural Dictates of their <hi>Reaſons,</hi> and Experience of <hi>Familiar</hi> Remedies, and Regulating their <hi>Diet,</hi> than ever they did ſince their <hi>Admiſſion;</hi> and therefore I ſhall pray with <hi>Parſon Ball,</hi> at the tying on of his <hi>Sword, pray God I may never have occaſion to uſe them,</hi> for to live <hi>Phyſically</hi> is to live <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erably.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:58572:31"/>
               <head>An Amphibious <hi>Latitudinarian,</hi> Aldermanlike <hi>Whig.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Country he wears the Title of a Right Worſhipful <hi>Sir Something,</hi> that Sprung up from <hi>Nothing;</hi> but being laid Croſs the Shoulders with a <hi>Knight-hood;</hi> his Horn is exalted above his Neighbours. His Father was a Man of good <hi>Stock,</hi> tho' but a <hi>Graſier;</hi> he bought the <hi>Land,</hi> and his Son the <hi>Title;</hi> and the next Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration returns his Family into their Original. His Study is the Faſhion of his <hi>Cloaths.</hi> His Religion <hi>Whiggiſm,</hi> which like <hi>French Pottage</hi> is made up of every thing. A <hi>May-Pole</hi> is his apt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, which is <hi>Rootleſs</hi> for want of <hi>Principles, Sapleſs</hi> for want of <hi>Wit,</hi> and <hi>Fruitleſs</hi> for want of <hi>Charity,</hi> with a <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cock</hi> on the Top, changing with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Wind of <hi>Doctrine;</hi> who being now level'd with the Ground, I muſt ſeek his <hi>Counterpart</hi> in another <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Station.</hi> In a <hi>City</hi> our <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> has clim'd up into <hi>Alderman;</hi> and being wrapt in <hi>Furr,</hi> and tyed to a <hi>Gold Chain,</hi> becomes Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in his Authority, and Right Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orable among the <hi>Whigs,</hi> for his Native Inſtability, and Neutrality, and his <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58572:31"/>in Bending either in the Houſe of God or Rimmon.</hi> To ſhew he is of no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, he profeſſes to be a Friend to all, and thinks there is not a Pin to chooſe, between the <hi>Bible</hi> and the <hi>Alcoran!</hi> He would be wholly a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but that he is ſomething of an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> and would be wholly an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> but that he is partly a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> He would be a <hi>Churchman,</hi> but for the Severities of <hi>Mortification,</hi> and the Doctrine of <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> and cannot be a <hi>Preſthyterian,</hi> becauſe he has not a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> fit for <hi>Long</hi> Prayers, nor the <hi>Stool</hi> of Repentance. <hi>Independant</hi> Expoſitions, and Lectures, would take up too much of his time; and the <hi>Quakers</hi> Silent Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in a <hi>Barn,</hi> would unqualify him for ſhewing his <hi>Oratory</hi> and <hi>Eloquence</hi> on the <hi>Bench;</hi> and therefore he calls himſelf a <hi>Latitudinarian Whig,</hi> and that anſwers all things. Every <hi>New</hi> Religion Scares him from a former, but none has power to perſwade him to it ſelf. He finds <hi>Reaſon</hi> in all Opinions, but Truth in none, and leads his Life accordingly. His <hi>Eſtate</hi> alone has Elected him into the Higheſt <hi>Poſt</hi> in the Common <hi>Hall,</hi> for had he not been worth <hi>Thouſands</hi> in Caſh or Ware, he never have roſe above the Degree of a <hi>Beadle,</hi> by his Underſtanding or Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. However he is Ambitious of a <hi>Name,</hi> and therefore lays no ſtreſs upon <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Conſcience;</hi> but Wags his Tail upon
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58572:32"/>every mean <hi>Cit,</hi> that Spits in his Mouth by Flattery; and is never any thing, but what his <hi>Profit</hi> and his <hi>Company</hi> make him. Among <hi>Churchmen,</hi> he is what they ſay of Chine of <hi>Beef, Pout, Pheaſant, Partridge,</hi> or whatever elſe will Reliſh with their curious Palates. The <hi>King</hi>'s Health in their Company goes down as Glibly as his <hi>Miſtreſſes;</hi> which at other times would go down with as much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, as his <hi>Wive</hi>'s, or a Cup of Sour <hi>Sixes,</hi> If a <hi>Courtier</hi> makes him a <hi>Viſit,</hi> the <hi>Velvet</hi> Chair, and a Flask of <hi>Florence,</hi> ſhews how kindly he takes it, and to make him ſome Requital, there ſhall be no diſcourſe againſt the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> or <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>managements,</hi> at his Table for Four and twenty hours afterward. He tells the <hi>Courtier</hi> how well the City and their Wives are Govern'd, and forgets not to mention his own ſhare in the Settlement; but no ſooner are his <hi>Gown</hi> and <hi>He</hi> remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into an Apartment where the <hi>Whigs</hi> are ſtowed, but he lays aſide his <hi>'To'ther end o'th Town Face,</hi> and ſlips on his Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <hi>Phiz,</hi> and Salutes his Brethren in <hi>Mood</hi> and <hi>Figure.</hi> If they repremand him for going ſometimes to <hi>Church,</hi> he excuſes it, as being a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and muſt Act <hi>Politickly:</hi> That he is in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> againſt the <hi>Church,</hi> and goes thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only for his <hi>Conveniency,</hi> to be a <hi>Spy</hi> upon that <hi>Party,</hi> and askes God forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58572:32"/>for going to <hi>Prayers</hi> among them; and goes to the <hi>Conventicle</hi> in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, to make one part o'th day <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize</hi> the other. Thus like a State <hi>Jack of all Trades,</hi> he appears Godly from the Teeth outward, by putting the <hi>Cheat</hi> upon himſelf, and his Admirers. He ſees two <hi>Parties</hi> conteſting for ſuperiority, and therefore thruſts his Noſe in the back-ſides of both the <hi>Pretenders;</hi> that whoever Wins the day, he may put in for a Friend to the <hi>Prevailing</hi> Party. His <hi>Politicks</hi> have alſo the perfections of the <hi>Whig:</hi> He cannot take the <hi>Oaths</hi> to the <hi>Government,</hi> nor the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> from a <hi>Church Man,</hi> but as a Qualification to an <hi>Office of Profit,</hi> and ſo he would take it in <hi>Lambs Wool,</hi> and at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> would be <hi>Circumciſed</hi> with a <hi>Reſervation.</hi> He diſcovers his <hi>Allegiance</hi> by repeating <hi>Miſdemeanors,</hi> and in finding Faults with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any deſire to mend them; but on all occaſions, takes advantage to <hi>Cramp</hi> and <hi>Canker</hi> all Men of a Steddy <hi>Loyalty.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he divides his Life, between <hi>Reſtleſs</hi> apprehenſions, <hi>Doubts</hi> never to be reſolved, <hi>Deliberations</hi> that can never take effect, and ſtarting Notions in <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> that no mortal Man under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands any further, than a Superinducing one <hi>Confuſion</hi> upon another, and encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring <hi>Leſſer</hi> Evils with <hi>Greater:</hi> Which has given him the Character of a <hi>States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58572:33"/>Revers'd, or a Chriſtian with the wrong ſide Outward.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Senceleſs, Upſtart, <hi>Whig</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Gentleman.</head>
               <p>IS an Animal begot betwixt <hi>Enthuſiaſtick</hi> Dulneſs, and <hi>Sophiſticated</hi> Reaſon, and ſtole into the World when the Eye of <hi>Providence</hi> was a ſleep, to <hi>Ridicule</hi> the whole <hi>Creation,</hi> and out-do <hi>Africa</hi> with a Monſter of a new Edition. His Name in the <hi>Lapland</hi> Dialect is <hi>Wotſallon.</hi> He has the Natural Privilege of a <hi>Viſor-mask,</hi> and his own <hi>Face</hi> effectually deſcribes him. His Strength is in his <hi>Back,</hi> and his Weakneſs in his <hi>Brain,</hi> as if Nature had cut him out for a <hi>Stallion</hi> to a <hi>Brothel-Houſe.</hi> His <hi>Heels</hi> are better mounted than his Head, and for the Figure ſake might ſerve for <hi>Baſis</hi> or <hi>Capitol.</hi> When he walks, he Grunts like a <hi>Sow</hi> in Queſt of Sun-Cake, Waddles like a <hi>Bear</hi> in ſtate, and wants nothing but a Rout of <hi>Bors</hi> and <hi>Bag-pipes</hi> to grace his ſolemn Entry to a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> anglice, the <hi>Bear Garden.</hi> When he Eates, you'd think all the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morants</hi> in the Univerſe were united in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one devouring <hi>Cerberus,</hi> to famiſh the reſt of Mankind, and when the <hi>Booby</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58572:33"/>laughs you'd think a <hi>Mandrake</hi> groan'd, or a Bed of <hi>Wormly Toads</hi> were croaking their <hi>Veſpers.</hi> His <hi>Rickety</hi> Head is ſwoln beyond a Symetrical Proportion, and was naturally adorn'd with <hi>Carrots</hi> of a right <hi>Sandwich</hi> Hew, but now is cover'd with <hi>Puntack</hi>'s caſt white <hi>Wig</hi> to diſappoint the <hi>Hoggs,</hi> and keep his Fool's head from the Weather. His <hi>Face</hi> looks as if ſome ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <hi>Carver</hi> had cut it out of a <hi>Dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Turnip, Skin'd</hi> it with the Hexagongy of a <hi>Hony-comb,</hi> and embelliſh'd his <hi>Cheeks</hi> with the <hi>Blue</hi> from his Eyes, to make the Figure more aſtoniſhing. His <hi>Lips</hi> are as green as a <hi>Leek,</hi> and have the Vertues of it alſo, in preſerving his <hi>Rotten Teeth</hi> from <hi>Gracing</hi> the Shoulder-Belt of a <hi>Corn-Cutter;</hi> but if this Deſcription be too brief to know him by, you cannot miſs the <hi>Rake</hi> every Noon hanging at a Lord's Arſe in an <hi>Eating-houſe;</hi> with a Soul full of <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> a Heart full of <hi>Treachery,</hi> a Mouth full of Commendation of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Uſurpation, and <hi>Lyes</hi> againſt the preſent <hi>Court.</hi> A <hi>Belly</hi> full of <hi>Claret,</hi> a white <hi>Wig</hi> full of <hi>Powder,</hi> a <hi>Pocket</hi> full of <hi>Papers</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Government,</hi> and a <hi>Head</hi> Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of <hi>Emptineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heraldry</hi> knowns nothing of his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors</hi> on either ſide, for like <hi>Muſhrooms</hi> they grew up in a Night of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> by Plundering the <hi>Loyal Party,</hi> and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to his <hi>Stock,</hi> had this Miſcellany of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58572:34"/>
                  <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Publican</hi> his Education. When <hi>Bulk</hi> and want of <hi>Brains,</hi> rendred him fit for <hi>Indentures,</hi> he was put <hi>Apprentice</hi> to a <hi>Woodmonger,</hi> and when Seven Years of Eating and Drinking, and now and then a little Ditch-ſide <hi>Whore,</hi> to enter him, were accompliſh'd, he ſet up at <hi>London,</hi> Maſter of a great <hi>Dogg,</hi> a ſmall Stack of <hi>Faggots,</hi> and a Lighter of <hi>Coals</hi> about the bigneſs of a <hi>Hogs Troffe;</hi> but this Sickly ſhew, not being able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his <hi>Extravances,</hi> according to the Laudable Cuſtom of the <hi>City,</hi> ſome Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man muſt be <hi>Cheated.</hi> To a Marriage Broken Brother he Complains for want of a <hi>Wife,</hi> to exalt his <hi>Hornes</hi> to an Equal Height with his Neighbours, who on paying the <hi>Prime Coſt</hi> for <hi>Procuration,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Scruples</hi> Fee for aſſiſting the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, a Plump <hi>Tarpolins</hi> Daughter, newly <hi>Rig'd, Waſh'd,</hi> and <hi>Tallowed,</hi> is found out, and Attack'd: And tho' ſome Friends of the <hi>Girles</hi> oppos'd the Match, as unwilling that any thing ſhould Marry a <hi>Baboon,</hi> but what had been begotten by a <hi>Monkey;</hi> yet the Devil's two Broker, the <hi>Holder Forth;</hi> and the <hi>Solicitor,</hi> having Melted down the Mother with <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Exerciſes,</hi> long Prayers, Fat <hi>Loins</hi> of <hi>Veal,</hi> and Repeated <hi>Drams</hi> of the <hi>Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> and ſetting up the <hi>Fop</hi> as a Stiff-Rumpt <hi>Whig,</hi> and a Zealous <hi>Conventicler,</hi> the <hi>Smithfield</hi> Bargain was ſtruck up with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58572:34"/>the Mother, and the young Lump of <hi>Wapping</hi> Zeal, and Breeding, finding ſhe had no other choice but the <hi>Collier,</hi> or a <hi>Shipleſs</hi> Saylor, ſhe conſented the former ſhou'd enter her Poop, and ſteer her, for <hi>Better</hi> for <hi>Worſe,</hi> into the fatal Port, of an empty <hi>Wood Wharf,</hi> where tho' repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſoon after, by tranſmuting the Saylor's <hi>Mettle</hi> into a full ſtock of <hi>Wood</hi> and <hi>Coals;</hi> carrying a greater <hi>Sail</hi> than the ſlender <hi>Smack</hi> would bear, the Veſſel ſprung a <hi>Leak</hi> in her <hi>Bread Room,</hi> and the crazy <hi>Maſt</hi> ſtanding bent a while, at length <hi>Snapt</hi> aſunder, the Veſſel <hi>Sunk</hi> in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the Quarter part <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Owner,</hi> from the hopes of a <hi>Livery Hood</hi> and <hi>Gown,</hi> which was the height of his <hi>Ambition,</hi> was confin'd within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of a <hi>Leather Jacket,</hi> ecchoing about the ſtreets <hi>Great hard dry Faggots, five for Six pence, Faggots.</hi> This Employ not agreeing with his <hi>Body,</hi> and being alſo above the reach of his <hi>Brain</hi> to manage; with his <hi>Horſe,</hi> and <hi>Cart,</hi> his <hi>Wife</hi> and other <hi>Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of the Houſe, he retired to <hi>Faſt</hi> and <hi>Pray</hi> in the Country, for a Tranſlation of his <hi>Sires</hi> into their Original <hi>Duſt</hi> and <hi>Aſhes,</hi> that he from a <hi>Broken Trades Man,</hi> might have a Reſurrection into <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The blind Baud <hi>Fortune,</hi> according to her uſual Method of obliging <hi>Fools,</hi> with the help of a <hi>Whig Doctor,</hi> and the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58572:35"/>of the <hi>Canting</hi> Tribe, ſends his Grand-Sire and Father to their places, and and removes the <hi>Whifling Whig</hi> out of <hi>W—Shire</hi> into <hi>Hert</hi>—Shire, and <hi>Palmes</hi> him upon that Country for a <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> without any other qualification than a large Stock of <hi>Whiggiſm, Hypocriſy,</hi> and <hi>Confidence.</hi> Now he ſets up for a man of figure, <hi>Whig, Beau</hi> and <hi>Spark,</hi> and uſes all the modern Arts to accompliſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for ſomething to be talk'd on; and whereas in the days of his <hi>Retrogradation,</hi> he kept <hi>Sneaking</hi> company, ſuch as had ſome remains of <hi>Conſcience</hi> about them; that were afraid of being <hi>Damn'd,</hi> that went to <hi>Hear,</hi> Lay with their <hi>Own Wives,</hi> ſaid Grace of an <hi>Ell Long</hi> before two <hi>Eggs</hi> and a <hi>Sallad;</hi> and in ſhort, were Errant <hi>Whig Chriſtians,</hi> without the leaſt tinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Beau, Bully</hi> or <hi>Bravo</hi> among them: He now pearches up into <hi>Squire,</hi> and <hi>Worſhipful,</hi> and <hi>Drinks,</hi> as <hi>Bloodily; Swears,</hi> as <hi>Damnably;</hi> and <hi>Whores,</hi> as like a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> as is poſſible for a <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers</hi> Apprentice to attain to. He bids Adien to the <hi>Droaniſh</hi> Cuſtom of Sober <hi>Whigs,</hi> in Kennelling at <hi>Twelve,</hi> and Riſing at <hi>Eleven;</hi> and now ſays the night was made for <hi>Beaſts</hi> to Reſt in, and <hi>Sparks</hi> to be <hi>Pox'd</hi> and <hi>Revil</hi> in; and therefore never Nods in <hi>London,</hi> but when there comes out a <hi>Proclamation</hi> againſt <hi>Sleeping,</hi> and then he takes a Nap of Nine hours
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58572:35"/>long to <hi>Affront the Government he lives by Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Temperance</hi> he reckons among the number of the <hi>Seven Deadly Sins,</hi> and to diſtinguiſh himſelf from the <hi>Lower Rate of Whigs,</hi> boaſts how often he has been <hi>Flux'd,</hi> and the great ſtore of <hi>Buboes</hi> and <hi>Shankers</hi> he has had about him. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he ſhews you his <hi>Face</hi> Broke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Poſts of a <hi>Tavern Door,</hi> his <hi>Coller Bone</hi> diſlocated, by being kick'd down ſtairs in a <hi>Baudy-Houſe,</hi> and there's no queſtion but one time or other, he'l have his <hi>Brains</hi> beat out to inform his <hi>Judgment,</hi> or be Run through the <hi>Guts</hi> by the <hi>La—Shire</hi> Knight, for <hi>Cracking</hi> and Lying of the favours he has received from his Vertuous <hi>Lady,</hi> and then the World will be Rid of one of its greateſt Incumbrances.</p>
               <p>Having made this ſtart into <hi>Gentleman,</hi> his next Affair is to keep up that <hi>Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> among the Party, by herding with all <hi>Factions</hi> againſt the <hi>Government,</hi> Eccleſiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and Civil, and ſets up for a <hi>Drunken Saint,</hi> tho' the immodiſh <hi>Coxcomb</hi> knows Religion is out of <hi>Faſhion.</hi> The Sirname of his <hi>Sect</hi> is unknown in <hi>Alexander Roſs's View of Religions;</hi> and tho' fools, make up the <hi>Gutts</hi> of all Churches, yet his Life is ſo Scandalous he is not own'd as a Member of any. His <hi>Religion</hi> conſiſts in Railing againſt all <hi>Governments</hi> but <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver's,</hi> and curſing the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:58572:36"/>worſe than the ſtrect <hi>Crack</hi> that clap'd him. He would be a <hi>Preſtbyterian,</hi> but for fear of the cloſe ſtool of Repentance. An <hi>Independant,</hi> but that he has neither <hi>Gifts</hi> nor <hi>Graces,</hi> and thinks himſelf not <hi>Fool</hi> nor <hi>Madman</hi> enough yet to be a <hi>Quaker;</hi> tho' he has the Ill manners of 'em all, in <hi>beſpattering</hi> the <hi>Court,</hi> notwithſtanding he Lives upon the <hi>Alms-Baket</hi> of the <hi>Treaſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Stomach of an <hi>Oſtridge</hi> is a Type of his Conſcience, and his pretended <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity,</hi> is like the diſſembled Compaſſion of a <hi>Crocodile.</hi> Whomſoever he <hi>fawns</hi> on he <hi>Devours,</hi> and ſwallows <hi>Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements</hi> and <hi>Stewardſhips,</hi> like a <hi>Jugler</hi> Knives, without ever <hi>choaking</hi> him. Two things he never kept in his life, <hi>Faſt-days,</hi> nor <hi>Promiſes,</hi> and his <hi>Words</hi> being but wind, he never ſcruples breaking 'em <hi>Upwards</hi> in good <hi>Faith,</hi> nor <hi>Downwards</hi> in good <hi>manners. Honeſty</hi> he looks upon as a <hi>Starving</hi> Notion, next Door Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to <hi>Beggary. Conſcience,</hi> like the <hi>Small-Pox,</hi> haunted him when he was young; but ſince he came to years of <hi>Maturity</hi> and <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> ſeeing it <hi>Interfere</hi> with his <hi>Intereſt,</hi> he gave it a <hi>Wring</hi> by the <hi>Noſe,</hi> and <hi>Kickt</hi> it down <hi>Stairs,</hi> that it might not <hi>Diſturb</hi> his company. To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title him to the Office of a <hi>Publican</hi> (which his ſecurity e're long will dearly ſuffer for) he makes a ſhew of good <hi>Husbandry,</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:58572:36"/>which is indeed but the effects of his Neceſſities; and therefore tho' he gives his Brother <hi>Whigs,</hi> their Bellies full of <hi>Bacon</hi> when they come to ſee him, he makes them ſo drunk before they go that they <hi>Spew</hi> it up again, which ſerves his <hi>Dogs</hi> for a <hi>Meal,</hi> and ſo looſes little by his <hi>Entertainments.</hi> He holds the Scale of <hi>Juſtice</hi> as <hi>Blindly,</hi> as the <hi>Goddeſs</hi> that was born ſo; ſhews his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> moſt in his <hi>Silence,</hi> and does his <hi>Country</hi> beſt ſervice in his <hi>Abſence.</hi> His Severity is all againſt <hi>Regretors</hi> and <hi>Fore-ſtallers,</hi> and cares not if they Raiſe the <hi>Devil,</hi> ſo they don't <hi>Raiſe the Market.</hi> His <hi>Servants</hi> are in as many Shapes, and Employments, as if their <hi>Maſter</hi> was a <hi>Magician;</hi> for the ſame perſon that <hi>Rigs</hi> his <hi>Worſhip</hi> for the <hi>Bench,</hi> ſerves the <hi>Dogs</hi> in the <hi>Kinnel.</hi> To ſave the expence of keeping a <hi>Clerk</hi> he writes his <hi>Warrants</hi> himſelf, from an ill Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; but when he has done can't <hi>Read</hi> them, without the aſſiſtance of that <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Utenſil</hi> he calls his <hi>Secretary,</hi> his <hi>Valet,</hi> his <hi>Butcher,</hi> his <hi>Groom,</hi> his <hi>Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper,</hi> his <hi>Every thing:</hi> And therefore hangs him behind his <hi>Coach,</hi> to be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able upon all Publick occaſions; to wipe his Maſter's <hi>Shooes,</hi> or aſſiſt his Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers Worſhip in <hi>Rectifying</hi> Abuſes and <hi>Miſmanagements.</hi> Of all the <hi>Senceleſs</hi> Animals that attend him, his two <hi>Black</hi> Mares have the <hi>Conſtanteſt,</hi> tho' not the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58572:37"/>
                  <hi>Sweeteſt</hi> Imployment, who carry <hi>Dung</hi> to th' field all the <hi>Week,</hi> and to th' <hi>Church, or Church Meeting-houſe</hi> on Sundays.</p>
               <p>Being thus accompliſh'd for a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful <hi>Shuſtice of the Peace,</hi> and the t'other thing too, <hi>Quorum,</hi> tho' he no more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the meaning of it in Engliſh, than if it was <hi>Arabick:</hi> To compleat the Character of a <hi>Finiſh'd Fop,</hi> he alſo ſets up for a <hi>Wit,</hi> by ſwearing with a <hi>Bonne Grace,</hi> telling <hi>Baudy</hi> ſtories, and convincing all the World, that he has no <hi>Sence,</hi> no <hi>Learning,</hi> no <hi>Religion,</hi> no <hi>Good Nature;</hi> but boaſts of being a <hi>Sott,</hi> and having the <hi>Pox</hi> five times, that he may be admired for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Old Fools and Fops that ſet up for <hi>Wits</hi> and <hi>Rakes,</hi> are the Directors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of his <hi>Life,</hi> and he deſpiſes all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that are not arrived at his Pitch of <hi>Gallantry.</hi> He looks upon't as an <hi>Unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable</hi> ſin, to be without a <hi>Ribbon</hi> round his <hi>Waſt,</hi> tho' a Halter would better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his <hi>Neck,</hi> for honeſter men than he have been <hi>hang'd.</hi> He calls all Men <hi>Clowns</hi> that offer to Bruſh the <hi>Powder</hi> from their <hi>Coats,</hi> that han't a Uſeleſs <hi>Sword,</hi> with a <hi>Dangling</hi> Ribbon down to their <hi>Shooes,</hi> and a juicy <hi>Dab</hi> of <hi>Snet</hi> and <hi>Snuſh,</hi> at the end of his <hi>Snout,</hi> and a fine <hi>Silk</hi> Waſtcoat and Breeches to wipe it on, in the abſence of an <hi>Indian Hankerchief.</hi> He is a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirer of all <hi>Women's</hi> Companies but his <hi>Wife</hi>'s, tho' he ſmeils ſo <hi>Rank</hi> that he
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58572:37"/>is ſcarce able to be endured in Mens. He <hi>Chuckles</hi> at the ſight of a <hi>White Peticoat,</hi> like a Turky-Cock at a <hi>Red one;</hi> yet could never attain to any above the degree of a Common <hi>Street</hi> Walker; for the Woman that would grant this <hi>Pole Cat</hi> the favour of a <hi>Run,</hi> without giving him the <hi>Pox</hi> in Requital, would ſcarce deny one to the <hi>Devil.</hi> He has a Hundred ways of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Money, and a hundred and fifty of ſpending it, beſides <hi>Eating, Drinking, and Wenching. viz.</hi> in <hi>Galloping</hi> from Town to Town, and from Conventicle to Conventicle, to buz <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> among Citizens; <hi>Factions</hi> among Country Gentlemen, and <hi>Sedition</hi> among the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People: Coaching it from <hi>Taverns</hi> to <hi>Eating-houſes,</hi> and thruſting himſelf into the company of <hi>Titulado's</hi> at the Price of Paying all the Reckoning. In the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try he lives like a <hi>Hawking, Setting, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Fool,</hi> that rides many a Mile i'th' Dirt for a purchaſe like himſelf, neither worth the time, nor trouble, that I have beſtowed upon him; for ſtriving to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect a <hi>Blockhead</hi> by <hi>Satyr,</hi> which deſcribes him to others, while he turns away his Eyes from ſeeing his own <hi>Picture,</hi> is like rayling to a Deaf-man, and therefore 'twould be a pleaſure to men of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> and for Publick <hi>Vengeance,</hi> if this fool in a Frame, had ſome feeling, and were <hi>Senſible</hi> when he is corrected. However,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58572:38"/>if this don't <hi>Reform</hi> him, and cauſe him to make Reſtitution, the next <hi>Setting</hi> ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his <hi>Effigies,</hi> more to the Life than this is, and give you his Name in words at length, and not in figures. In the mean time I will deſcribe his favourite <hi>Dunce,</hi> which he goes three or four miles to hear, in contempt of the <hi>Worthy Miniſter</hi> of his own Pariſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Church <hi>Whig,</hi> or the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical <hi>Bifarius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IS the Off-ſpring of <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity,</hi> who being Dieted a while in a <hi>Country</hi> School, upon <hi>Rules, Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and redious Repetitions of <hi>Amo's</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> till he had learn'd how <hi>Phaeton</hi> broke his Neck, how many Apples <hi>Tytirus</hi> had for his Supper, and underſtood <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer's</hi> Commendations of <hi>Ach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lles's Toes,</hi> and the <hi>Graecians Bootes;</hi> knew a <hi>Hexameter</hi> from a <hi>Pentameter,</hi> a <hi>Sponde</hi> from a <hi>Dactil,</hi> and could fit them without <hi>Sence</hi> to his <hi>Fingers-end;</hi> tho' his <hi>Parts</hi> were contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, and the <hi>Purſes</hi> of his Friends at too low an <hi>Ebb,</hi> to maintain him like a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: To the <hi>Univerſity</hi> he muſt go for a little <hi>Logick,</hi> and <hi>Ethicks,</hi> and is Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by his Relations to be a <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgy-man,</hi> in hopes that a <hi>Benefice</hi> where <hi>Henry</hi> the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58572:38"/>Eight had not been too buſy with his <hi>Toll Diſh,</hi> but that yet there remain'd ſome <hi>Good-Land,</hi> that Afforded <hi>Milk</hi> and <hi>Honey,</hi> might be the Portion of our Juvenile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Levite. Now that ſucceſs might anſwer the deſires of his <hi>Parents,</hi> and that the <hi>Babe</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> might not Surfeit on <hi>Human Learning,</hi> the <hi>Tutor</hi> employs him in <hi>Bed</hi> making, <hi>Chamber</hi>-Sweeping, and <hi>Water</hi>-fetching, that the <hi>Sizars</hi> Brains might not be over heated with too much <hi>Vain Philoſophy.</hi> Having ſuck'd in about Six or Seven mouthfuls of <hi>Vniverſity</hi> Air, exactly learnt to Reſpond to <hi>Quid eſt Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gica,</hi> and <hi>Quot Sunt Vertutes Morales;</hi> with <hi>Burgurdicius, Euſtachius,</hi> and ſuch Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Help Meets in <hi>Divinity</hi> in his Coat Pocket; down he goes by the firſt <hi>Carrier</hi> on the Top of a <hi>Pack,</hi> into the Country to Propogate the Goſpel, and by that time he can ſay his <hi>Predicaments,</hi> and his <hi>Creed,</hi> you find him in a <hi>Pulpit;</hi> for now he has the Choice of <hi>Preaching</hi> or <hi>Starving: Tho' it had been</hi> Ten times better for the Lad and the <hi>Church,</hi> that he had been made a <hi>Tooth</hi> Drawer, or a <hi>Porter.</hi> Some Poor Starv'd <hi>Vicar,</hi> that ne're could keep a <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> in his Life, gives him a <hi>Title</hi> to <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nation,</hi> and then a Neighbouring <hi>Knight</hi> takes him into his Family, at the Price of <hi>Ten Pounds a year,</hi> and a <hi>Sunday Pudding,</hi> to perform <hi>Holy Offices,</hi> and ſpoil his <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> by making him their <hi>Tutor.</hi> Being
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58572:39"/>a Stranger to the Houſe, and a <hi>Decent</hi> Behaviour, my <hi>Couſin Abigal</hi> out of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and in hope of the <hi>Benefit of her Clergy,</hi> inſtructs him in the knowledge of a <hi>Chaplains Duty,</hi> viz. That he muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeak in the <hi>Parlour</hi> but at <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> time, and be ſure with a Low <hi>Bow</hi> to Riſe in time from the <hi>Table,</hi> take away his <hi>Plate,</hi> and march off with his <hi>Hat</hi> under his <hi>Arm,</hi> and cleave a Logg into <hi>Billets,</hi> for the Parlour Fire, whilſt the <hi>Knight,</hi> my <hi>Lady,</hi> and her <hi>Children,</hi> eat up the <hi>Chickens, Tarts,</hi> and <hi>Cuſtards,</hi> and then calls in the <hi>Chiplin</hi> to <hi>Diſmiſs</hi> them. This obligation upon the young <hi>Levite,</hi> gives him a liking to Mrs. <hi>Abigal,</hi> which ſhe Cheriſhes with the Remains of her <hi>Ladies Caudles,</hi> and the Pills of her <hi>China Oranges,</hi> and lays the Foundation of his <hi>Ruin.</hi> To pleaſe his <hi>Miſtriſs,</hi> and gain the <hi>Vicarage</hi> that is Entail'd upon her Office by the Cuſtom of the <hi>Manner,</hi> he is ſometimes found <hi>Cracking Nutts,</hi> and Reading in his <hi>Study,</hi> and having luckily diſcover'd a <hi>Vacuum</hi> in his Upper <hi>Room,</hi> he fills it with Learned <hi>Jargon, Materia Prima, Occult Qualities,</hi> and <hi>Attoms,</hi> which the <hi>Lady</hi> of the Houſe obſerving, ſhe breaks out in his Commendation. <hi>Truly the Young Man is much improv'd, ſince he came into our Family.</hi> The <hi>Ladies</hi> good Word, the <hi>Knight</hi>'s good Nature, and Mrs. <hi>Abigals</hi>'s Apron Strings growing too ſhort, preferrs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58572:39"/>him at once to a <hi>Benefice,</hi> and a <hi>Belly-piece,</hi> where the All Wiſe <hi>Patron,</hi> and the All Underſtanding adjoining <hi>Juſtice,</hi> being both Severe and Sour <hi>Whigs,</hi> the <hi>Chipling</hi> to gain their Favours, and Reaſſume what he was bred to, ſets up for a <hi>Church Whig</hi> alſo, and leaves nothing unattempted that may ſhew his Reſpects to the <hi>Diſſenting</hi> Party. Now he ſets up for a <hi>Conforming Diſſenter,</hi> and carries the fair <hi>Outſide</hi> of a Man, and is an errant <hi>Knave</hi> in his Heart: One that indifferently divides his Body and his Soul betwixt <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>VVrong:</hi> The Government has his <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t'nances,</hi> and the Schiſm his <hi>Affections.</hi> He is externally a <hi>Church of England-Man,</hi> but inwardly a <hi>Phanatique,</hi> and his own Judgment Condemns his Practice, which he Diſpenſes with, to make Friends of the <hi>Unrighteous Mammon.</hi> At firſt he <hi>bowed</hi> towards the <hi>Altar,</hi> and now if their <hi>VVorſhips</hi> are abſent, to Goodman <hi>VVebb,</hi> and Goodman <hi>Bland,</hi> and the beſt Yeomanry of the Pariſh. He divides his good Wiſhes equally between the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Patron,</hi> but prays for the former in the <hi>Desk,</hi> and the latter in the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> He <hi>Huddles</hi> over the <hi>Prayers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as if he was <hi>Riding Poſt,</hi> and long'd to be at the end of his Journey; but is very Devout and Deliberate in his own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore <hi>Belchings,</hi> as if want of <hi>Sence</hi> made 'em acceptable to <hi>God,</hi> as well as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58572:40"/>to his Ignorant <hi>Auditors.</hi> He ſets his <hi>Face</hi> by their Worſhips <hi>Glaſſes,</hi> caſts his Shapes in their <hi>Mould,</hi> and ſerves the <hi>VVhig Dons</hi> in all Offices. <hi>Prays</hi> and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds in their <hi>Families,</hi> Writes their <hi>Leaſes, Bonds, and VVarrants,</hi> and gives them <hi>Glyſters</hi> when they are <hi>Coſtive;</hi> which with Collecting his <hi>Tyth Pigs, Calves,</hi> and <hi>Geeſe,</hi> and his <hi>Egges</hi> and <hi>Eaſter</hi> Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erings, takes up ſo much of his time, that he has ſcarce Leiſure to ſteal an <hi>Old Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Sermon,</hi> and therefore Stuffs his Memory with harſh <hi>Metaphors,</hi> Childiſh <hi>Similitudes,</hi> and Miſapplied <hi>Tales</hi> of <hi>Tubs,</hi> that ſerve him as well on all occaſions. He has however an Excellent <hi>Knack</hi> (as they call it) in <hi>Preaching</hi> of ſuch Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beriſh as it is, and is always <hi>Provided.</hi> If a Text lies at <hi>Sculk</hi> all the Week, and will not be found to be <hi>Rived</hi> in <hi>Pieces</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Saturday Night,</hi> or <hi>Sunday Morning,</hi> he then Climbs up to it by <hi>Six Steps, as Solomon aſcended to the Ivory Throne,</hi> or elſe goes down to it, as <hi>Moſes from the Hill of Sinai,</hi> and whereever he finds it <hi>Splits</hi> it into <hi>pieces,</hi> to make it look like ſomething. If it be a <hi>Soft</hi> Text, and does not <hi>Drop a ſunder</hi> of it ſelf, he <hi>Crumbles</hi> it into Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels between his <hi>Fingers,</hi> to feed the Brood of <hi>Chickens</hi> aſſembled. If like <hi>Medow Hay</hi> the Text be <hi>long,</hi> he <hi>Chops</hi> it for the tender <hi>Calves,</hi> and gives the <hi>Oarts</hi> to the Strong <hi>Bulls of Baſhan.</hi> If the Text be
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58572:40"/>
                  <hi>Free Timber,</hi> he divides it into as many parts, as there are Words or <hi>Letters</hi> in the whole; but if it prove <hi>Knotty,</hi> he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides it <hi>(Beloved)</hi> into <hi>One</hi> part, and then it looks like <hi>Rachel and Leah,</hi> or like <hi>Abraham at his Tent Door;</hi> like <hi>the Dove that Noah ſent out of the Ark</hi> to look for fair Weather; like a Carpenters pair of <hi>Stradling Compaſſes,</hi> or an <hi>Orchard of Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granets.</hi> He is mighty <hi>Provident</hi> in Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding the Words of the <hi>Text;</hi> and from a Monaſillable, like a Conjurer can <hi>Raiſe</hi> many Points of Doctrine and Obſervation. If the Word <hi>And,</hi> ſits in his <hi>Text,</hi> 'tis like <hi>Mathew at the Receipt of Cuſtoms;</hi> or like <hi>Zoar,</hi> 'tis but a little Word, and obſerves from it, <hi>That ſmall things muſt not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded.</hi> If he encounter the Word <hi>But,</hi> ſtanding or Travelling in his <hi>Text,</hi> 'tis like <hi>the Man going to Jericho,</hi> and it Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to you <hi>Caution</hi> and <hi>Comfort,</hi> firſt <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and ſhews that this <hi>But</hi> is ſuch a <hi>Butte</hi> that you cannot <hi>Hitt</hi> it, unleſs <hi>Free Grace direct</hi> your <hi>Arrow;</hi> and ſecondly for your <hi>Comfort,</hi> 'tis a <hi>Butt</hi> of Excellent <hi>Wine,</hi> and then falls to <hi>Broaching</hi> it. Sometimes he ſhews his Wit in <hi>Jingling</hi> with Words, and his Learning by falſe <hi>Concord</hi> and <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity,</hi> and then opens his Treaſury of <hi>Tales Metaphors</hi> and <hi>Similies,</hi> wherein the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi> himſelf is in danger of being <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phem'd,</hi> if the <hi>Metaphor-Monger</hi> had not the Art of bringing himſelf off, with a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58572:41"/>
                  <hi>Limping, As it were, As I may ſo ſay,</hi> and Salving all by hobling in, <hi>with Reverence be it ſpoken.</hi> Then to humor the Factious he Groans, Leaps, Hurls and lays about him, in Railing Bloodily againſt <hi>Plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and wiſhes the Clergy as many <hi>Wives</hi> as <hi>Benefices. Non Reſidence</hi> he Confutes by that plain Text of Scripture, <hi>Abraham begat Iſaack,</hi> which is as Convincing as Demonſtration it ſelf; for had <hi>Abraham</hi> not Reſided, but diſcontinued from <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife, he could never have <hi>begot Iſaac,</hi> which ſets 'em all a <hi>Groaning</hi> in the <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-Iſle,</hi> worſe than at the Burials of their <hi>Fathers,</hi> or <hi>Husbands,</hi> or at the News of <hi>Cherry</hi>'s miſcarrying of a <hi>White-fac'd</hi> Calf: Which with a <hi>Sober</hi> Word or two againſt the <hi>Government,</hi> and ſetting out his own <hi>Loſſes</hi> by the Tax upon <hi>Births</hi> and <hi>Burials,</hi> which kept young Men from <hi>Gettiug Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and old Men from <hi>Dying</hi> to ſave the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Duty,</hi> he concluded the <hi>Preachment,</hi> and the Maſters of the <hi>Pariſh</hi> in Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feration of his ſuffering, charitably Order the <hi>half-Fac'd Brother,</hi> a Recruit out of the <hi>Poors Rate;</hi> in a grateful Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration whereof, he reſolves at the firſt opportunity to burn the <hi>Cover</hi> of the <hi>Font</hi> to boil his <hi>Leeke Porrage;</hi> to let the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book</hi> fall into the <hi>Dirt,</hi> to ſpare the Trouble of <hi>Reading</hi> it; and to Tare out the <hi>Surplis</hi> into Neceſſaries for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, to ſhew his Zeal againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58572:41"/>his <hi>Averſion</hi> to <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and ſo much ſhall ſerve for this <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Text,</hi> next <hi>Lords-Day</hi> you ſhall have him again with a <hi>New one.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Slaſher,</hi> or a Tirannical Ignorant <hi>Pedagogue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IS an <hi>Eſſence</hi> that ſtands in need of a Double <hi>Definition,</hi> for he is nothing related to the Man he would appear to be. He is a <hi>Tyrant</hi> in a Common-wealth of <hi>Boys,</hi> and arm'd with a <hi>Rod</hi> and <hi>Ferula,</hi> is more inſolent, and <hi>Arbitary,</hi> than a <hi>Univerſal</hi> Monarch with his <hi>Sword</hi> and <hi>Scepter:</hi> And we need not wonder at <hi>Dyoniſius,</hi> the <hi>Tyrant,</hi> who being expulſed his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and getting to be <hi>Maſter</hi> of a <hi>School,</hi> ſhould chooſe that <hi>Sovereignty</hi> for the more <hi>Voluptuous</hi> Dominion. <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of Children about their <hi>Books,</hi> has always been decryed by the wiſeſt <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> when they underſtood it no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the pleaſure of <hi>Revenge;</hi> but what would they have ſaid of a <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> which ſerves a <hi>Viler Affection,</hi> and may be numbted among thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that are not to be named among <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> without borrowing the <hi>Cleanly</hi> expreſſion of the Incomparable <hi>Hudibraſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:58572:42"/>
               <q>
                  <l>The Pedant on the School Boys Breeches,</l>
                  <l>Does claw and curry his own Itches.</l>
               </q>
               <p>A Man cannot ſpeak without <hi>Shame</hi> of this <hi>Abominable Vice,</hi> nor expoſe this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady to <hi>Cure,</hi> without reproaching Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and giving ſuch <hi>Inſtances,</hi> as would render the <hi>Malefactors</hi> the <hi>Hated</hi> Objects of all the World; the Maſter is <hi>Idle,</hi> takes no <hi>Pains,</hi> and has no <hi>Patience,</hi> and the Child is <hi>Chaſtiz'd</hi> for the pleaſure of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying a <hi>Baſe</hi> and <hi>Unnatural Appetite:</hi> And Catches at a fault in a Boys <hi>Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to pleaſe himſelf in Inflicting the <hi>Puniſhment.</hi> The fault once <hi>Sprung,</hi> the <hi>Bird</hi> is ſeized, the <hi>Fleſh</hi> is made <hi>Bare,</hi> and how does the <hi>Jer-Faulon</hi> Pearch over it; and Commit a Sin, beſides that of <hi>Cruelty,</hi> that Nature abhors the thoughts of; and which <hi>Quintilian</hi> aſſigns as a Reaſon for the <hi>Total Abolition</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Barbarous</hi> and <hi>Inhuman</hi> Cuſtom, in words which much affected me: <hi>Jam ſi minor in dilegendis Cuſtodum et Praeceptorum moribus fuit Cura, pudet Diſcere in quae Probra nefandi hominis iſto caedendi jure abutantur, non morabar in parte hominis hac, Nimium eſt quod intilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur.</hi> I will not Engliſh it, becauſe 'tis the <hi>Sore</hi> I would fain have to be <hi>Remedied,</hi> and for the ſake of which I have made this Digreſſion: That the Perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd might <hi>Reform,</hi> before they are more
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58572:42"/>
                  <hi>Expoſed,</hi> or a <hi>Law</hi> be promulged to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain</hi> and <hi>Puniſh</hi> it.</p>
               <p>His milder Character is a <hi>Silly</hi> Animal in <hi>black,</hi> with a <hi>Band</hi> as broad as a <hi>Slab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berring Bib,</hi> and ſerves for that purpoſe; A <hi>Steeple</hi>-Crown'd <hi>Hat,</hi> with <hi>broad</hi> Brims, which ſhews he is flying into <hi>Deacon</hi>'s <hi>Orders,</hi> and with good Friends may be Preferr'd to be a <hi>Reader:</hi> Or he is a Fardle of <hi>Words</hi> (for he never had mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Life) bound up in <hi>Calves Skin,</hi> and <hi>Letter'd</hi> on the back, <hi>Ludi Illiterarij.</hi> His <hi>Soul</hi> is drown'd in <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and is the moſt dangerous Creature in the World, for confirming of an <hi>Atheiſt:</hi> Who would Swear it was nothing but the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature</hi> of his Body: His <hi>Thoughts</hi> never reach beyond his <hi>Eyes,</hi> and all his <hi>Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> like Reſtive <hi>Jades,</hi> cannot be <hi>Spur'd</hi> to the Purſuit of any commendable Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. His <hi>Tongue</hi> always runs before his <hi>Wit,</hi> in <hi>Mood</hi> and <hi>Figure,</hi> and Lilies <hi>Lex in Sermone tenenda</hi> cannot ſtop it. <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and Groſs Feding, are his <hi>Founders; Railing</hi> Rabbies, and wide knee'd <hi>Breeches</hi> are his <hi>Nurſes,</hi> and his Life is but a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed <hi>blaſt of Wind,</hi> for between two <hi>Religions,</hi> as between two <hi>Doors,</hi> he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>was <hi>Whiſtling.</hi> He is averſe to all kinds of <hi>Government,</hi> and yet thinks it no leſs than <hi>Treaſon,</hi> to ſay the <hi>Nominative Caſe</hi> does not Govern the <hi>Verb,</hi> or that the firſt <hi>Supine</hi> has no <hi>Active Signification;</hi> but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58572:43"/>all, ſhould the Laws <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join the wearing clean <hi>Shirts,</hi> he would be <hi>Lowſy</hi> rather than <hi>Conform</hi> to a cleanly Command. His Memory is exerciſed in ſetting his <hi>Phiz</hi> in a Form of good <hi>Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature,</hi> and he neither <hi>Coughs,</hi> nor <hi>Spits,</hi> nor blows his <hi>Noſe,</hi> but by a Rule in <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar.</hi> His <hi>Learning</hi> was thrown into him <hi>Glyſter Wiſe,</hi> and therefore he ſpeaks <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> more Familiarly than <hi>Sence;</hi> Writes true <hi>Latin,</hi> but falſe <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and is a <hi>Stranger</hi> in no part of the World ſo much as in his own Country. He gives Rules for Husbandry from <hi>Virgils Georgicks,</hi> for Breeding Cattle from his <hi>Bucolicks.</hi> Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Stratagems in <hi>War,</hi> from <hi>Caeſars Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries,</hi> and <hi>Keckermans Logick</hi> furniſhes him with an Unanſwerable <hi>Ergo.</hi> His <hi>motion</hi> on Foot is a <hi>meaſure,</hi> on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back a <hi>Gallop,</hi> for his <hi>Legs</hi> are his own, but his <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Spurrs</hi> were borrowed. There went but a Pair of <hi>Sheers</hi> between him and a <hi>Non Con Preacher;</hi> and both their Misfortunes is not ſo much, in being a Couple of <hi>Starch'd</hi> Conceited <hi>Fools,</hi> as in taking ſo much Pains to ſhew it. The extent of his Ambition is Criticiſm, and <hi>Tully</hi> is his Example. He Selects his Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by the Sound, and not by the Sence; and the Eight parts of Speech are his Menial Servants, which he employs on all occaſions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:58572:43"/>
               <head>A Politick, Tricking, Over-Reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Trading <hi>Whig.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IS a true <hi>Copy</hi> of a Wicked <hi>Original,</hi> where <hi>Arrogance</hi> ſupplies the Place of <hi>Birth, Inhumanity</hi> of <hi>Sincerity,</hi> and <hi>Cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>Wit.</hi> His <hi>Cap</hi> and his <hi>Knee,</hi> his <hi>Smiles</hi> and good <hi>Words,</hi> are all at a Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utes Warning, to be dealt about upon all neceſſary occaſions. All his <hi>Actions</hi> are <hi>Tipt</hi> with fair pretences, yet are directed to himſelf, and he never looks any further. He ſupplies his own <hi>Neceſſities,</hi> by asking others what they <hi>want.</hi> No Man Speaks more, and to leſs purpoſe; for his <hi>Words</hi> are like his <hi>wares,</hi> Twenty of <hi>One</hi> Sort, and he turns them over alike, to all his <hi>Cuſtomers.</hi> Whatſoever he ſhews you, is the <hi>Neweſt</hi> and beſt thing in all the <hi>Town,</hi> tho' it be the <hi>worſt</hi> in his <hi>Shop</hi> or <hi>Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe.</hi> His <hi>Conſcience</hi> was a <hi>Commodity,</hi> that would have lain upon his Hands, and therefore 'twas the firſt thing he <hi>Put off,</hi> and the <hi>want</hi> of it, ſerves him better than the <hi>uſe</hi> on't. His <hi>Religion</hi> is but <hi>Skin deep,</hi> it may appear in his Codled <hi>Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> but ne're comes near his <hi>Heart;</hi> 'tis Writ upon <hi>Changeable Taffaty,</hi> and like folded <hi>Pictures,</hi> makes him look one way
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58572:44"/>like a <hi>Saint,</hi> and another way like the <hi>Devil.</hi> In his Shop he is a <hi>Tradeſman,</hi> in the Coffee-houſe a <hi>States-man,</hi> and like an <hi>Earwig</hi> is always Creeping into peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>Ears,</hi> to breed <hi>Maggots</hi> in their <hi>Heads,</hi> and <hi>Filth</hi> in their <hi>Mouths</hi> at the Election of <hi>Mayors</hi> and <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> and <hi>City Officers.</hi> When he feels his <hi>craft</hi> is <hi>expoſed,</hi> his <hi>Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Detected,</hi> and his Cheating Tricks diſcover'd and made puniſhable by Law, he cries out his <hi>Diana Trade</hi> is endanger'd; and if the <hi>Holder forth</hi> is bribed to <hi>whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> ſome Ugly <hi>Suggeſtion</hi> about the <hi>loſs</hi> or <hi>Decay</hi> of <hi>Trade,</hi> which always was, and always will be the Complaint of <hi>Shop</hi> and <hi>Conventicle,</hi> 'tis carried about with <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> and Tragical <hi>Declamation;</hi> the Noiſe of <hi>Perſecution</hi> Propogates like <hi>Thunder,</hi> ſpreads like <hi>Lightning,</hi> and every mouth is fill'd with <hi>Dreadful</hi> Apprehenſions, that the Government are blowing up the <hi>Thames,</hi> Raiſing a <hi>Marian Perſecution</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> and their <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> And that their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Seven-Pence i'th' Shilling,</hi> would be brought to the <hi>Stake</hi> together, if care was not taken by them to prevent it; and then the <hi>Trad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Mob like <hi>Wild Aſſes,</hi> having ſnuff'd in theſe <hi>Prejudices,</hi> 'tis but natural they ſhould <hi>Bray,</hi> and be impatient, when they find their <hi>Credit</hi> Low, and <hi>Fancy</hi> Trade a ſinking, tho' there's no cauſe for this <hi>Complaint,</hi> only the People are <hi>Hair'd</hi> and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58572:44"/>
                  <hi>Jugled</hi> out of their <hi>Senſes,</hi> by the Dictates of a <hi>Faction,</hi> and the <hi>Venom</hi> of a Seditious Club of <hi>Common-Wealth's-men.</hi> He ſeems more <hi>Holy</hi> than others, to gain the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of being more <hi>wicked.</hi> He avoids <hi>Taverns</hi> and <hi>Ale-Houſes</hi> by Daylight, only to <hi>Drink</hi> and <hi>Whore</hi> in Private. He knows there's Field room enough to play the <hi>Knave</hi> out of the reach of the <hi>Statute,</hi> and to act the Part of the <hi>white</hi> Devil in <hi>Hugger Mugger,</hi> and the Civil Magiſtrate be never the Wiſer; and therefore does his <hi>Cheating</hi> Jobs <hi>Diſcreetly,</hi> and <hi>Juggles</hi> and <hi>Defrauds</hi> under the <hi>Viſor</hi> of a Good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. He has too much Wit to play the <hi>Fool</hi> in ſome <hi>Scandalous</hi> Caſes, and Pleads Liberty of Conſcience, for <hi>Biting</hi> his very <hi>Brethren</hi> in another; and ſo is honeſt by <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> and a Knave by <hi>Inclination.</hi> His ſeeming Sanctimony is made up of <hi>Negatives:</hi> If he does not take the <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> from the <hi>Hungry</hi> and <hi>Thirſty,</hi> Uſe <hi>Strangers</hi> like <hi>Doggs,</hi> nor ſtrip <hi>Poor People Naked,</hi> he calls himſelf a <hi>Saint,</hi> and while he keeps his Hands from <hi>Picking</hi> and <hi>Stealing,</hi> lets his Tongue looſe to <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Slandering.</hi> He <hi>Fawns</hi> like a <hi>Spaniel</hi> upon every <hi>New Cuſtomer,</hi> and a <hi>Puking Wambling</hi> Conſcience, is his Cloak to hide his <hi>Knavery.</hi> Oaths of <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> are hard things to <hi>Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low;</hi> but rather than loſe an Office of <hi>Profit,</hi> or a <hi>Poſt</hi> to <hi>Plague</hi> the Government,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58572:45"/>he can digeſt them with as much eaſe as <hi>Lucatella's Balſam,</hi> and be as upright a <hi>VVhig</hi> ſtill, as any in the <hi>Linſey-wolſey</hi> Club of buſy <hi>Intermedlers;</hi> and ſo in <hi>Diſſenting</hi> or <hi>Complying</hi> carries on the ſame Deſign of <hi>Miſchief,</hi> to the <hi>Publick,</hi> and ſecurity to his own Mothers Child. He riſes by <hi>Degrees</hi> from one kind of Miſchief to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and makes one <hi>Solaeciſm</hi> in the Ground work, produce a thouſand in the <hi>Superſtructure.</hi> He advances from <hi>Zeal</hi> to <hi>Jealouſy,</hi> from Jealouſy to <hi>Practice,</hi> from <hi>Fearing</hi> Faults to <hi>finding</hi> them; from <hi>Reforming</hi> Grievances, to the Diſſolution of <hi>Laws,</hi> and from removing Evil <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> to the higheſt degree of <hi>Diſaffection</hi> to <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Shifter, or Jacobite <hi>Whig.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving caſt the Slough of <hi>Jacobite,</hi> with a deſign of doing further <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheif,</hi> he Herds with <hi>Republicans,</hi> and has <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> in his Mouth, whilſt <hi>Arbitrary Power and Slavery</hi> is Reigning in his Heart, and the whole deſign in <hi>coming over,</hi> is to promote them. All his former <hi>Intrigues</hi> againſt the Government being baſſed, he lies like a <hi>Tyger</hi> or <hi>Wolf</hi> in the way, till he finds an Opportunity of Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58572:45"/>his <hi>Prey,</hi> and then he makes a <hi>Leap</hi> at it. He has chang'd his <hi>Name,</hi> but not his <hi>Nature,</hi> and ſhews his Face at Court as a <hi>Convert,</hi> that in the croud he may Paſs <hi>Unſuſpected.</hi> He has worn his Eſtate to <hi>Rags</hi> in the Service of his <hi>Old Maſter,</hi> and now indeavours to get a <hi>New One,</hi> to repair his <hi>loſſes:</hi> Tho' there can be greater Indignity to Men of <hi>Merit,</hi> or a more pernitious <hi>Solaeciſm</hi> in Politicks, than to recommend this <hi>Counterfeit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> to Preferment, till he has given as convincing <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> of his <hi>Fidelity,</hi> as he has formerly done of his <hi>Diſaffection.</hi> He has chang'd his <hi>Colour;</hi> but ſtill wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Marks of <hi>Hyprociſy,</hi> you may read him in his <hi>Countenance;</hi> for as the Government is <hi>Healthy</hi> or <hi>Sickly,</hi> you will find his <hi>Complexion</hi> and <hi>Converſation</hi> juſt the contrary. He <hi>Clubs</hi> among the <hi>Whig Republicans,</hi> and keeps up his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with his <hi>Old Acquaintance,</hi> and employs all his <hi>Intereſt</hi> to help a <hi>Lame</hi> Dog o're the Stile, in the Service of that <hi>Party.</hi> He Compounds with the <hi>State</hi> for a bare <hi>External Conformity,</hi> with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Poſture of Affairs, and Compounds with the <hi>Jacobites</hi> to expiate the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency of that Cold and <hi>Formal</hi> Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, with Aſſurances that he is <hi>Theirs</hi> upon the <hi>firſt</hi> occaſion. His diſcourſe is a New ſort of <hi>Cant,</hi> betwixt <hi>Oracle</hi> and <hi>Riddle,</hi> and never ſpeaks any thing of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58572:46"/>
                  <hi>Moment</hi> but under a <hi>Cover</hi> that will bear <hi>two</hi> meanings, a <hi>Better</hi> and a <hi>Worſe,</hi> and the one ſtill ſerves as a <hi>Cloak</hi> to the other. Ask him <hi>Who he's for?</hi> He anſwers, <hi>for the King and Government,</hi> meaning the <hi>Wrong</hi> King all the while, and another ſort of <hi>Governors.</hi> He ſee's his Party cannot carry it by open <hi>Force, Battery</hi> or <hi>Aſſault,</hi> and therefore he is <hi>come</hi> in to Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine it, while the reſt are employed as <hi>Spies</hi> upon the <hi>Government,</hi> and creep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to th' <hi>Gariſon</hi> to betray it if they can into the hands of the <hi>Enemy.</hi> He has fail'd in his firſt <hi>Eſſay</hi> by force, and now is at it by <hi>Jugling</hi> and <hi>Fawning:</hi> There's not a <hi>Fang,</hi> or a <hi>Talon,</hi> now to be ſeen; the <hi>Wolves</hi> are all turn'd into <hi>Lambs,</hi> and the <hi>Vultures</hi> into <hi>Pigeons.</hi> All our Enemies are either <hi>Dead</hi> upon the <hi>Spot,</hi> or <hi>Come over</hi> to us; which, is Alaſs, but the laſt <hi>Shift</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> a Doſe of <hi>Opium</hi> to lay us a ſleep, for the cauſe is ſtill alive, as errant a Counterfeit as the World affords; and will riſe again, unleſs more weight be laid upon it, to keep it under. This kind of <hi>Trimming,</hi> is but the laſt effort of a <hi>Faction,</hi> that is well nigh <hi>hunted down,</hi> which if they have time to <hi>Recover</hi> it will be with a <hi>Vengeance.</hi> Their <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> riſe up in Judgment againſt their <hi>Pretences,</hi> and are <hi>Overt Acts</hi> to expound the <hi>Secret</hi> purpoſes and Intenſions of their Hearts againſt the Government, and that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58572:46"/>they have a mind to <hi>Trick</hi> us out of our <hi>Legal Settlement.</hi> The <hi>Diſhonour</hi> and <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> of which proceedings, will double our Calamities; for it is a much more ſupportable <hi>Affliction,</hi> for a Government to be maſter'd by <hi>Force,</hi> than to be chous'd by <hi>Credulity.</hi> The one is <hi>Fortune</hi>'s fault, the other is our <hi>Own;</hi> and 'tis more <hi>Shameful</hi> to be <hi>Out-witted</hi> than to be <hi>Overcome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Republican <hi>Whig</hi> Jacobite</head>
               <p>IS an <hi>Individuum Vagum,</hi> an <hi>Unkle Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> a Man of no Principle either of <hi>Honour,</hi> or <hi>Conſcience,</hi> any further than it ſquares with his own <hi>Advantage.</hi> He is a common <hi>Enemy</hi> to all kind of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and prefers <hi>Plotting</hi> againſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is <hi>Uppermoſt,</hi> above any other kind of <hi>Lechery.</hi> Under the Monarchy of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Secand,</hi> he was a profeſt <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths-Man,</hi> and employ'd himſelf, and his <hi>Pen,</hi> as deſperately againſt that <hi>King and Court,</hi> as if he had been weary of his <hi>Life,</hi> courted a <hi>Halter,</hi> and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Dying</hi> with his <hi>Shooes</hi> on: Which he had certainly done, if there had not been an Underſtanding between him and <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Jenkins;</hi> who order'd <hi>Mr. Legate,</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:58572:47"/>the <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> tho' his Name was in all Warrants againſt the <hi>Whigs</hi> not to <hi>Seize</hi> him, for fear, I ſuppoſe of Diſcovering him to be a <hi>Treacherous Jack of both Sides.</hi> In the Reign of <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> he ſet up for a <hi>Monmothean,</hi> to ſcandalize the <hi>Action,</hi> and at the <hi>Loſs</hi> of honeſter men's lives, eſcaped from a <hi>Hog-ſty</hi> with his own into <hi>Holland.</hi> In the <hi>Prince</hi>'s glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious expedition to Redeem our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> his <hi>Highneſs</hi> was pleas'd (as well he might) to deny this <hi>Boutfeau</hi> a Paſſage among thoſe that offer'd him their Service, and the <hi>Worthy Gentleman</hi> that Over-perſwaded the <hi>King</hi> he might paſs in the <hi>Throng</hi> without any <hi>Reflection</hi> upon that <hi>Honourable</hi> Enterpriſe, has repented it ever ſince, that he open'd his Mouth for ſo vile a <hi>Wretch.</hi> In this happy Reign, tho' obliged beyond his Deſert, he has plaid the <hi>Devil</hi> for the <hi>Devil</hi>'s <hi>ſake,</hi> and has put <hi>Hell</hi> to its <hi>Shifts,</hi> to Invent <hi>Plots</hi> ſo faſt as he could utter them. He had an <hi>Office</hi> under the Government, and Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the <hi>Jacebites;</hi> beg'd money of the <hi>Independants</hi> to Relieve their <hi>Poor,</hi> but gave what he could ſpare from <hi>Symond</hi>'s <hi>Tap,</hi> to the <hi>Non Jurant Parſons.</hi> Under the <hi>Viſor</hi> of a <hi>Common-Wealth-Compounder,</hi> he made his Court at <hi>St. Germans,</hi> which ſhews the <hi>Credit</hi> of their Cauſe was ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when they laid hold on this <hi>Rotten Stick</hi> to keep it from <hi>Drowning.</hi> Lord
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58572:47"/>
                  <hi>Melford</hi> found the <hi>Plot Mettle,</hi> and he the <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Furnace,</hi> to <hi>Forge,</hi> or Caſt it into <hi>Tooles</hi> for the ſervice of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> and in every Conſultation to promote the Intereſt of that <hi>Party</hi> he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways propos'd the moſt <hi>Bloody</hi> Methods to obtain their Ends. There has been no Plot againſt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> ſince his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Acceſion to the <hi>Throne,</hi> in which he has not had a <hi>conſiderable</hi> ſhare, either in <hi>Acting</hi> in it, or <hi>Shamming</hi> it, when it came to be <hi>Diſcover'd.</hi> He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents our <hi>Allies</hi> and <hi>Confederates</hi> as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,</hi> that make advantage by our <hi>loſſes,</hi> and our profeſs'd Enemies as <hi>True-Friends</hi> to <hi>England. When</hi> he had got <hi>Hundreds</hi> by his Office, he turn'd Tail upon the Government, and herded with the <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents</hi> to make it <hi>Twice</hi> as much; and then tells the People in his <hi>Printed Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets,</hi> how ſtrangely the King is <hi>Miſled</hi> by evil <hi>Councellors,</hi> and that there's ſcarce a man at <hi>Court</hi> fit to <hi>Adviſe</hi> him. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he appears in <hi>Print,</hi> as one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's <hi>Beſt Subjects,</hi> and in the Concluſion takes way the King's <hi>Honour,</hi> for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his <hi>Life; Undermines</hi> the Eſtabliſh'd Church for the ſecurity of our <hi>Roligion;</hi> and ſets up <hi>Democratical</hi> Principles for the Maintenance of the <hi>Monarchy.</hi> He has Modell'd his Looks into a <hi>Form,</hi> that is taking among the <hi>Seperating Preciſians,</hi> and has his <hi>Eyes</hi> lifted up to <hi>Heaven,</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58572:48"/>while his <hi>Hands</hi> are in their <hi>Pockets.</hi> He never Remembers <hi>Benefits,</hi> nor forgets <hi>Unkindneſes,</hi> nor never is at a <hi>Loſs</hi> for new Projects to plague the World, and <hi>Ruin</hi> Mankind. <hi>Aquinas</hi> does not more abound with <hi>Diſtinctions</hi> and <hi>Salvo</hi>'s, than he with corrupted <hi>Texts</hi> to excite Men to <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion;</hi> and expounds the preſerving the <hi>King</hi> in his <hi>juſt Right,</hi> to be the <hi>Aſſaſſinating</hi> his Royal <hi>Perſon,</hi> in which as he had his <hi>Share,</hi> 'tis pitty he miſs'd the <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> for if he has not himſelf <hi>Brued</hi> all the <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> theſe <hi>Ten</hi> years; yet he has been the common <hi>Advocate</hi> of the whole <hi>Rebellious Party,</hi> and has eſpous'd their <hi>Crimes</hi> as well as their <hi>Intereſts;</hi> for Writing for the Generality of <hi>Offenders,</hi> implies an Approbation of their <hi>Treaſons,</hi> and that he is influenced by the ſame <hi>Evil Spirit,</hi> and wants a <hi>Power,</hi> not a <hi>Will,</hi> to commit the moſt <hi>Barbarous</hi> Murder. He ſcruples more the breaking one <hi>Oath of Conſpiracy,</hi> than Twenty of <hi>Allegiance.</hi> His life is govern'd by a <hi>Phanatical</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, that Emancipates him from the Servile and <hi>Pedantick</hi> Obligation of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity</hi> in his <hi>Life</hi> and manners, and Stages him as one of the <hi>Antipodes</hi> to mankind, made up of <hi>Croſsneſs</hi> and <hi>Oppoſition.</hi> His Chriſtian <hi>Liberty</hi> is <hi>Thwarting Authority,</hi> and advancing an <hi>Antichriſtian Anarchy:</hi> In placing the <hi>Sovereign Power</hi> in the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and making as many <hi>Kings</hi> as there
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58572:48"/>are Men in <hi>England.</hi> He is the <hi>Spider,</hi> in the Emblem, he fetches <hi>Poiſon</hi> out of every thing, and had rather go to <hi>Hell</hi> in a Rebellious Road of his own <hi>Finding,</hi> than to <hi>Heaven</hi> in the way of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Like a <hi>Mole</hi> he works under-ground, to throw up <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> and when they have once taken <hi>Air,</hi> if <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> himſelf ſounded the <hi>Trumpet,</hi> it could not give a ſtronger <hi>Alarm</hi> to <hi>Inſurrections</hi> and <hi>Aſſaſſinations.</hi> He has commonly a <hi>Bible</hi> in his <hi>Hand,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in his <hi>Mouth,</hi> and yet 'tis legible by his <hi>Actions,</hi> that he quarters his <hi>Coat</hi> with the <hi>Atheist</hi> in the <hi>Pſlams,</hi> that ſays in his <hi>Heart there is no God.</hi> He makes a <hi>Conſcience</hi> of every thing and <hi>Nothing.</hi> What the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, he <hi>Pukes</hi> at like a <hi>Breeding</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; but to promote his own <hi>Traiterous Deſigns,</hi> the ſeven <hi>deadly Sins,</hi> paſs whole through him without ſo much as <hi>Kecking.</hi> He is by Complection, <hi>Sower</hi> and <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine;</hi> but half a Dozen <hi>Bottles</hi> will wind him up to the Pitch of <hi>Jest</hi> and <hi>Buffoonery;</hi> but either <hi>Drunk</hi> or <hi>Sober, merry</hi> or <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, Grave</hi> or <hi>Frolickſome;</hi> he is ſtill a Malcontented <hi>Whig;</hi> but whether 'tis <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> of our ſide, or t'other, is not yet Determin'd; and therefore <hi>Reader, croſs thy ſelf, and have nothing to do with him;</hi> for if all the Wickedneſs of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind were <hi>lost,</hi> there's enough in him to Repleniſh the <hi>World</hi> with <hi>Vices,</hi> and <hi>crow'd
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58572:49"/>Hell</hi> with Obſtinate, and Impenitent Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Scurrilous and Seditious <hi>Whig</hi> Writer</head>
               <p>IS generally ſpeaking, either an Unim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed Needy <hi>Lawyer,</hi> a <hi>Proſcrib'd</hi> Field Conventicler, a <hi>Caledonian Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> or a <hi>Renegado Popiſh Priest,</hi> new Lick'd into a <hi>Socinian Tubſter;</hi> and under ſome or all theſe <hi>Qualifications,</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a Member Politick of an Incorporate <hi>Faction,</hi> a Formal Pedantick <hi>Fault-finder</hi> in Government, and a <hi>Pamphleteer</hi> for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Malcontended <hi>Clubbers.</hi> His <hi>Stile</hi> is either a <hi>Bluſtering</hi> Noiſe of Inſignificant pompous Words, that threaten to kill ſix Opponents with his Pen, and Six and twenty with his <hi>Inkhorn,</hi> or elſe a Fardle of <hi>Obſolete</hi> Phraſes, or <hi>Moth-eaten</hi> Adages, that were in uſe when Men wore <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets,</hi> and wip'd their <hi>Noſes</hi> on their <hi>Sleeves,</hi> for want of <hi>Handkerchiefs.</hi> The Scope of his Pamphlets (if they have any) is to poſſeſs the People with Fears of <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> to reflect <hi>Scandal</hi> upon the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to pelt the <hi>Court</hi> with Lean and Meager <hi>Reproaches,</hi> and the Miniſtry with ſuch <hi>Audacious</hi> Suggeſtions, as may give
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58572:49"/>the Multitude a Loathing of the Men and the <hi>Conſtitution.</hi> He is always provided (at the Charge of the Common Stock of buſy <hi>Intermedlers</hi>) to write for that <hi>Party,</hi> who are ſtill affrai'd of <hi>Loſing</hi> what cannot be <hi>Taken</hi> from them, and upon thoſe <hi>Fantaſtical</hi> apprehenſions, care not if the Government be <hi>Diſſolv'd,</hi> to gratify their Scruples. He is full of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Hints</hi> againſt <hi>Miſmanagements,</hi> and Wounds <hi>Royal</hi> Authority through the ſides of pretended <hi>Evil Counſellors.</hi> He is ſometimes a <hi>Droll,</hi> and always a <hi>Sceptick,</hi> and there's ſcarce any thing ſo certain or <hi>Sacred,</hi> that he does not expoſe to <hi>Queſtion</hi> or <hi>Contempt:</hi> Inſomuch, that betwixt the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> and the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Morallity</hi> is ſhaken, the Two Tables of the <hi>Decalogue</hi> daſh'd to pieces: The Laws of <hi>Government</hi> Subject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Fancies of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Authority</hi> to the Private <hi>Paſſions</hi> of the Fickle Multitude. He is ſo fond of being <hi>Publick,</hi> that he will rather be a <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> or a <hi>Rediculous</hi> Incendiary, than not be taken Notice of as a <hi>Whiggiſh Author.</hi> If there be a <hi>Libel</hi> in Town againſt the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> ſome <hi>One,</hi> or a Club of them <hi>All,</hi> are ſure to be the <hi>Compoſers</hi> of it, and are Celebrated among the <hi>Seditious,</hi> as Men of extraordinary <hi>Merit,</hi> meerly for being <hi>miſchievious.</hi> Nothing comes amiſs to make him <hi>Alarm</hi> the <hi>Mobile</hi> with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58572:50"/>
                  <hi>dangers.</hi> What a Fury will he raiſe about <hi>Nothing,</hi> and counterfeit a Fooliſh <hi>Melancholly</hi> upon improbable dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to excite the brutiſh paſſions of the Rabble, upon every <hi>ſlight</hi> and <hi>frivolous</hi> ſuggeſtion. The Oration of the old Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard in <hi>Apuleius,</hi> would be leſs <hi>Rediculous</hi> than ſome of their doleful, and <hi>tragical</hi> Harangues about a <hi>Standing Army.</hi> The old Fellow comes forth with hideous <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowings,</hi> and with all the Solemnities of <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and a <hi>diſcompoſed</hi> Mind, to declaim in the preſence of the whole <hi>City,</hi> againſt a <hi>Little Boy;</hi> and as ſoon as he could for <hi>Sighs</hi> and <hi>Groans,</hi> begins with weeping <hi>Teares,</hi> to let them know that he had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to communicate that required all their <hi>Attentions,</hi> as they tender'd the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Common-Wealth;</hi> and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to conjure them, by all things <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred</hi> and <hi>civil;</hi> by their <hi>Gods</hi> and their <hi>Altars,</hi> not to let the <hi>Murtherer</hi> eſcape un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed; and having ſcrewed up the Peoples expectations even to impatience, he was earneſtly deſired to declare the <hi>Crime,</hi> that ſo they might attone the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the <hi>Gods,</hi> which otherwiſe they might expect upon their <hi>City,</hi> if they ſhould ſuffer ſuch a horrid <hi>Villany</hi> to paſs <hi>Unrevenged.</hi> At laſt (after he had moved all this indignation,) he produces <hi>Three Bottles</hi> broken all to pieces by the <hi>Lad; Here, Here,</hi> (ſays he) behold the Cruel
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58572:50"/>
                  <hi>Murtherer.</hi> At which (you may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) all the Audience fell a laughing then, as all Wiſe men do at our Pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Authors now, for endeavouring, with ſo much <hi>Seriouſneſs</hi> and dreadfull Apprehenſions, to raiſe a <hi>furious Paſſion</hi> out of Nothing. To keep him within the Limits of his own Sphere, was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine a <hi>Wild Boar</hi> with ſober words. There has been no peace upon Earth ſince he was in it, and a Man might as well at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the <hi>Converſion</hi> of the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> as reconcile him to his <hi>Duty.</hi> He is the moſt Savage Creature in the world, and no leſs uncapable of Diſcipline than <hi>Rats</hi> and <hi>Swallows;</hi> and ſmells ſo rankly of <hi>Confuſion</hi> and <hi>Diſorder,</hi> that no <hi>Towardly</hi> Chriſtian can approach him without an <hi>Antidote.</hi> He ſuriouſly combats every <hi>Trifle;</hi> raiſes a Tempeſt from the leaſt <hi>Drop</hi> of Water; either commends or diſpraiſes to the laſt degree of <hi>Rigour,</hi> and cenſures without <hi>Judgment</hi> or <hi>Authority:</hi> And there's no way to perſwade him from repeating his <hi>follies,</hi> and <hi>Mudling</hi> himſelf in <hi>Ink,</hi> but to turn him to his old Trade of <hi>Lampoons, Ballads</hi> and Grubſtreet <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-making,</hi> or make him forſwear the uſe of <hi>Pen, Ink</hi> and <hi>Paper.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>For he'l proceed, come on't what will,</l>
                  <l>There is no middle-Courſe in doing Ill,</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:58572:51"/>
               <head>A Whig Trimmer, or a Jack of all Sides</head>
               <p>IS a <hi>Will</hi> with a <hi>Wiſp.</hi> a Man of no <hi>Principle</hi> either of <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> any further than it ſquares with his <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Profit.</hi> You may reckon him among the common <hi>Enemies</hi> of the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and Mankind. His Countenance is like a <hi>Prognoſtication</hi> in an <hi>Almanack:</hi> When his Eyes ſparkle with <hi>Joy,</hi> you muſt look upon the <hi>Dancing</hi> of thoſe <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> like the Play of <hi>Porpoiſes</hi> before a <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> and when <hi>All is Well there,</hi> 'tis a fore-boding of <hi>Troubles,</hi> and <hi>Storms</hi> in the <hi>Publick:</hi> As a <hi>Cloud</hi> on his <hi>fore-head</hi> (on the other ſide), is an Infallible ſign of <hi>Fair weather</hi> in the <hi>State;</hi> for that which makes the one <hi>fat,</hi> makes the other <hi>Lean,</hi> and common <hi>Diſſaſters</hi> are not only his <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> but his <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Nouriſhment.</hi> and the reaſon of ſo much contariety is this: That <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and a <hi>Popular Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eignity, Law</hi> and <hi>Licenſe, Order</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,</hi> can never ſtand together. He talkes aloud of <hi>Grievances, Abuſes</hi> and <hi>Miſmanagements,</hi> and makes it his buſineſs to <hi>Enlarge</hi> upon them. He talks of <hi>Dangers,</hi> and fills Peoples heads with <hi>fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> ſtories of them, and at the ſame Inſtant
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58572:51"/>is ſo put to't for <hi>Want</hi> of Proof that he is faint at leaſt to <hi>magnify,</hi> if not to <hi>Create</hi> them, and ſupply the Defect of <hi>matter,</hi> with <hi>Impoſture</hi> and <hi>Invention.</hi> There's not a <hi>Whimſical</hi> Story paſſes the <hi>Town,</hi> that is capable of being improv'd into a <hi>Scandal</hi> or <hi>Illuſion,</hi> but it's preſently <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh'd</hi> up, for the Service of the <hi>Malcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended:</hi> And when there wants matter of <hi>fact</hi> for a ground to work upon, 'tis his care to ſupply it with <hi>Fancy</hi> or <hi>Suggeſtion.</hi> He has a new way of Politick <hi>Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rading,</hi> under a <hi>Coat</hi> that fits all <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Opinions,</hi> goes round like a <hi>Mill-Horſe</hi> in the ſame <hi>Track</hi> of <hi>Hearing, Telling</hi> and <hi>Dividing,</hi> and under pretence of <hi>Triming,</hi> at laſt removes, and with his own <hi>Weight</hi> over-ſets the <hi>Wherry.</hi> The <hi>Gentleman</hi> that has indeavour'd to give him a fairer <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,</hi> has forgot what he is, and repreſents him what he ſhould be. He <hi>Inclines</hi> too much to a <hi>Party</hi> to carry himſelf <hi>Uprightly,</hi> and approves the Sence of the <hi>Law,</hi> no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than it aſſerts his <hi>Intereſt;</hi> and thinks them no longer <hi>Jewels,</hi> than they hang at his <hi>Ears,</hi> or Adorn his <hi>Fingers.</hi> Tho' <hi>Monarchy,</hi> when the Adminiſtration falls into Wiſe and good Hands, is approved by all <hi>Judicious</hi> Men, as the beſt form of <hi>Government,</hi> he is no longer in <hi>Love</hi> with it, than it keeps him in humor with a <hi>Profitable Employment,</hi> and when that is taken away, yet by <hi>Trimming</hi> when he
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58572:52"/>held his <hi>Office,</hi> he has Secur'd his Intereſt in a <hi>Party,</hi> and then ſets up for a <hi>Jacobite,</hi> or a <hi>Republican;</hi> either for <hi>Another King, or no King at All,</hi> as he ſees the Beam turning to his own <hi>Advantage.</hi> He is for a <hi>Liberty</hi> that is inconſiſtent with his <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and calls every Government <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> where he cannot Act the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> over all below him, and <hi>Checkmate</hi> all above him. He is not ſo <hi>Diſpleaſed</hi> with any thing, as our own <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> where <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> are ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily reconcil'd, that they Friendly Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace each other. He is angry that <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of Conſcience is eſtabliſh'd by <hi>Law,</hi> becauſe he has loſt an opportunity of <hi>Quarrelling</hi> about it; for he had rather want his <hi>Right,</hi> than not gratify his <hi>Spleen,</hi> and humor his <hi>Perverſneſs.</hi> He is a Friend to <hi>Zeal,</hi> and an Enemy to <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and Cheats himſelf by a falſe Oſtentation of the <hi>Power of Godlineſs,</hi> without being in the <hi>form</hi> of it. He thinks himſelf of the <hi>True Religion,</hi> becauſe he has been of <hi>All he could hear of,</hi> and having <hi>Pin'd</hi> himſelf to the Principles of <hi>Neutrality,</hi> had rather undergo the <hi>Laodicean Fate,</hi> than enjoy the Reward of <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance.</hi> The Noiſe of <hi>Fire</hi> at <hi>Midnight,</hi> does not ſo much <hi>Affright</hi> him, as a Diſcourſe of <hi>Accommodation</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> for to be all of a <hi>Peice</hi> would ſpoil his <hi>Market,</hi> in being for, and againſt every thing, by
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58572:52"/>way of <hi>Debtor</hi> and <hi>Creditor.</hi> He always ſhifts for the <hi>Warm</hi> ſide o'th the <hi>Hedge,</hi> and rather than run any <hi>Riſque</hi> in his <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> or <hi>Fortune,</hi> he'l leave his <hi>Prince,</hi> his <hi>Country,</hi> his <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Friend</hi> in the <hi>Lurch,</hi> to ſave but the worth of a <hi>Cockle-ſhell.</hi> In your Proſperity over a <hi>Bottle</hi> of <hi>Wine,</hi> and a Diſh of your <hi>Meat,</hi> he'l load you with <hi>Careſſes</hi> and <hi>Civilities;</hi> but if you come to have the <hi>Wind</hi> and <hi>Tyde</hi> in your <hi>Teeth,</hi> and the Vogue of the <hi>Town</hi> againſt you, he'l be one of the <hi>firſt</hi> ſhall <hi>deſert</hi> you in ſtark <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs;</hi> till you have <hi>ſtrugled</hi> your way through the <hi>Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty,</hi> and then he's again <hi>your moſt Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Humble Servant,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If our <hi>Trimming Whig</hi> is a man of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, he will Ruin you with <hi>Truſt</hi> and <hi>Confidence;</hi> and draw out your laſt blood in pretences to do your <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> when he never in the leaſt <hi>Intends</hi> it. Ask his favour for an <hi>Employment:</hi> He allows you to be a very <hi>Honeſt</hi> man, and well <hi>quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> for any thing, one that has faithfully ſerv'd the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and he is glad, <hi>heartily Glad,</hi> that he has an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſerving you. He has <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four</hi> pretty things in's <hi>Eye;</hi> there are <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three Vacancies</hi> at preſent, and you may aſſure your ſelf he is your <hi>friend</hi> to all <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents</hi> and <hi>Purpoſes.</hi> you may intirely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon any <hi>Good Office</hi> he can do you, and that he will never leave you, <hi>till he
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58572:53"/>has done ſomething, or other, that, is Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for you:</hi> And now betwixt the <hi>Credit</hi> of the <hi>Pretence</hi> on the one ſide, and the <hi>Snare</hi> of the <hi>Truſt</hi> and <hi>Confidence</hi> on the other, you are entred upon the <hi>Road</hi> that leads to your <hi>Undoing.</hi> Now you have a <hi>Waiter</hi>'s <hi>Place,</hi> and having danced <hi>Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> on him till you have hardly <hi>Shooes</hi> to follow him longer, you have for anſwer, <hi>That he has done what he can;</hi> but there was ſo many <hi>Buts</hi> and <hi>Exceptions</hi> in the way, he could not accompliſh <hi>his Wiſhes</hi> for you. <hi>But if you can find out any thing, you ſhall be ſure of it.</hi> This puts you upon a new charge of <hi>Enquiring,</hi> and when you bring him an account of <hi>Three things Undiſpoſed of,</hi> he falls into a <hi>Paſſion,</hi> and chides your <hi>Negligence;</hi> for if you had but ſpoke of it a <hi>Quarter of an hour ſooner,</hi> he had done your buſineſs effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually; for one of them was <hi>juſt given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> and the other <hi>Two</hi> are <hi>Promiſed,</hi> and you muſt have <hi>Patience,</hi> and hunt about for more <hi>Diſcoveries,</hi> till he grow as <hi>Shy</hi> of you, as a ſculking <hi>Citizen</hi> of a <hi>Serjeant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as oft as you come, he is <hi>Sick, Buſy, Abroad,</hi> or not to be ſpoken with. If you <hi>Way-lay</hi> and <hi>Surprize</hi> him, he is in great <hi>Haſt,</hi> cannot <hi>Stay;</hi> but when you have found out ſomething for your <hi>Turn,</hi> come to him, and you ſhall be ſure, in Engliſh, <hi>To go without it.</hi> And now put all his <hi>Proffeſſions, Proteſtations,</hi> and <hi>Promiſes,</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:58572:53"/>into one Scale, and his <hi>Doublings,</hi> his <hi>Put-off</hi>'s, <hi>Shams</hi> and <hi>Pretences</hi> into another, and you'l find your very <hi>Soul</hi> upon the moſt painful ſort of <hi>Torture.</hi> Depend, ſays the Whiggiſh <hi>Trimmer.</hi> Aſſure your ſelf, Upon my <hi>Honour,</hi> I will ſerve you; when there's no more in't at laſt, than ſo much <hi>Air</hi> thrown into the mouth of a <hi>Credulous fool,</hi> toward the ſatisfying of an <hi>Empty Stomach.</hi> One while the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> will not bear it. The <hi>Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency</hi> of the Perſon; 'tis too <hi>Little,</hi> or too <hi>much;</hi> 'tis too <hi>ſoon</hi> or 'tis too <hi>late,</hi> 'tis out of your <hi>Way,</hi> or unſuitable to your <hi>Humour;</hi> and, in a word, an honeſt man may as well lay his finger upon an <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Inſtant,</hi> as <hi>Nick</hi> the preciſe time of doing his buſineſs, by the Mediation of a falſe <hi>Trimming-Whig,</hi> who does nothing but <hi>Delude,</hi> and <hi>Bretray</hi> you; and his laſt <hi>Shift</hi> is, removing you out of his way into th' <hi>Country,</hi> and when he has found out ſomething, he will <hi>ſend</hi> for you: <hi>And that will be when the Devil's Blind, who's Eyes are not ſore yet,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſpent all your <hi>Money, Wearied</hi> out your <hi>Self,</hi> and <hi>Worn</hi> out your <hi>Clothes,</hi> you procure a <hi>Friend</hi> to ſolicite for you, and at firſt ſight the <hi>Whig Trimmer</hi> tells him; Sir, your friend is a <hi>mighty Good Man,</hi> pray tell him I don't <hi>forget</hi> him tho' he's <hi>abſent. I have him here upon my Minutes, for the firſt buſineſs that falls;</hi> but
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58572:54"/>you would do well however, to mind me now and then on't; for I have many things in my <hi>Head,</hi> you know, and now I cannot talk with you about it; <hi>but if you could ſtay a little here about, or come again a matter of an hour or two hence; or rather if it would ſtand with your convenience, let me ſee you upon Monday next, preciſely at Twelve, then I may Chance to tell you more.</hi> Your friend replies I'le not fail your <hi>Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> at the very moment; but what hopes, ſays he, ſhall I give my friend in the mean time. <hi>My Lord,</hi> I beg this freedom from you; do you think 'twill do at <hi>Laſt?</hi> for a man had better Ten times be hang'd <hi>Once</hi> for <hi>All</hi> till he's Dead, than be ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the <hi>Air</hi> the Lord knows how long, under the Anxiety of a lingring <hi>Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> 'Tis ſome caſe to a Man yet, to know the <hi>worſt</hi> of a thing, and to be at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, whether it be <hi>Off</hi> or <hi>On.</hi> This Plain Dealing of your Friend, <hi>Ruffles</hi> and <hi>Diſcompoſes</hi> the little great man of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and he anſwers with ſome Emotion: I am extreamly preſs'd, you ſee: But I'le borrow half a Dozen words at any time from common Buſineſs, for the ſervice of an honeſt man, and a friend; but to be plain with you, Sir, <hi>you are a little too Warm, and too Quick upon the Point. Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars muſt not be Carvers: Affairs of this Nature muſt be brought about by Patience and Opportunity. 'Tis not for a man in his
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58572:54"/>Circumſtrnces, to talk of being off, or on; as who ſhould ſay; if I may'nt have it when I would, I won't have it at all, 'Tis too Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and peremptory, let me tell you: Your beſt way is to let matters and Humours work in their due ſeaſon:</hi> Not but that all you have ſaid to me is as ſafe, as if the words were in your own mouth again. This ſmart <hi>Common-Place Reprimand,</hi> puts your friend to'th' expence of two or three <hi>Low Bows</hi> and <hi>Cringes,</hi> and an Apology to <hi>ſmooth</hi> him, ſaying, <hi>my Lord,</hi> I dont <hi>direct,</hi> or <hi>expoſtulate,</hi> but my humble meaning, with <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> is, that the <hi>frankneſs of the Diſpatch doubles the favour.</hi> To conclude, in all this <hi>Trimming Whigs Promiſes,</hi> there is not one grain of <hi>Down right Integrity,</hi> but apparent marks of a <hi>deliberated Fraud,</hi> to put men upon the <hi>torture</hi> of <hi>Vexatious, expenſive, endleſs</hi> and <hi>contemptuous Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,</hi> that the amus'd Multitude may reckon the number of their <hi>Slaves</hi> by the number of theſe <hi>Dependencies;</hi> and the world will never be better, till <hi>Generoſity</hi> and <hi>ſincere Honeſty</hi> become more <hi>Faſhionable.</hi> Offer him a Civility he ſcorns, he ſays, to be <hi>Brib'd;</hi> he is none of thoſe that <hi>ſell Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and at the ſame time expects you ſhall <hi>Fee</hi> his <hi>Servants,</hi> and makes his own <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> allow his <hi>Steward</hi> and <hi>Butler</hi> a Salary out of his Profits, towards the Payment of their Wages, beſides Cramming his hungry Footmen, who are almoſt Famiſh'd for
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58572:55"/>want of their promiſed Five Shillings a Week, to procure them Belly-Timber.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Whiggiſh falſe pretending Friend</head>
               <p>IS an Inſect that under the Diſguiſe of <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> will do you more miſchief than the worſt of your <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</hi> If you are in <hi>Proſperity,</hi> he'l flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and undermine you; if in <hi>Adverſity,</hi> he'l betray you, and creep out at your <hi>Sleeve</hi> when you think you have him <hi>ſafe</hi> in your <hi>Boſom.</hi> He's the meer Spirit of <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> a general Diſperſer of nauſeous <hi>Scandal;</hi> that never ſpeaks <hi>Well</hi> of any man behind his <hi>back,</hi> nor <hi>Ill</hi> of any man before his <hi>Face,</hi> and cares not tho' the Subject be his <hi>Father,</hi> his <hi>Brother,</hi> or the <hi>beſt</hi> Friend he has in the World, if he thinks it will not reach his <hi>Ear;</hi> for he has an equal kindneſs for all he names his <hi>friends,</hi> and would go fifty mile on <hi>Foot</hi> to ſee any of them <hi>hang'd.</hi> His for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Character was a maſs of <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Lying,</hi> under a veil of ſeeming <hi>Sanctity;</hi> but now he is grown as great a proficient at <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Whoring,</hi> as the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd <hi>Bully</hi> at a Baudy houſe; and can no more <hi>Riſe</hi> without a <hi>Wench,</hi> than go to <hi>Bed</hi> without a <hi>Bottle.</hi> He boaſts much of his Company, and there's none ſo <hi>bad</hi> he will not keep, nor ſo <hi>Good</hi> he wo'nt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58572:55"/>to. He ſwears he has been with <hi>my Lord ſuch a One,</hi> and had three Quarts of <hi>Champain</hi> to his ſhare; that he had much ado to get away, and is going to three other <hi>Lords</hi> about buſineſs of Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Diſſimulation</hi> is the Adjunct of his Quality. He always lies at <hi>Catch</hi> to inſnare you, and there's no ſafer truſting him with a <hi>Secret</hi> than your <hi>Money,</hi> for no mortal ever knew <hi>a Sour Whig True to any man.</hi> He is all for getting <hi>Money,</hi> for that he knows will make the <hi>Pot Boil,</hi> tho' the Devil <hi>Piſs</hi> i'th' fire. When he has nothing elſe to talk on, <hi>Religion</hi> and his <hi>Green Pew with Red Inckle,</hi> is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: And treats it with as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as if <hi>Eikon Baſilike</hi> was the <hi>Tubſter.</hi> He has always a lying, ſneering, ugly merry face when he is deſigning <hi>Miſchief,</hi> and that gives him a Name in the <hi>Party, for a very honeſt fellow;</hi> and if theſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous <hi>Moles</hi> that work under ground, were not as <hi>Blind</hi> as they are <hi>Buſy,</hi> an honeſt man could not be ſafe in a <hi>Cell,</hi> with all the <hi>Honeſty</hi> in the world about him. He is as <hi>Impudent</hi> as he is <hi>Troubleſome,</hi> and like a <hi>Weezle</hi> runs ſqueaking from houſe to houſe, that no man can cat his Bread at quiet for him. In every thing he ſeeks his own <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and cares not if the whole Kingdom were in a <hi>Flame,</hi> if he can but roaſt his <hi>Eggs</hi> by it. He thinks no gain unſavory. All is Good that brings <hi>Profit.</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:58572:56"/>He ſerves <hi>God</hi> to get <hi>Money,</hi> and would ſerve the <hi>Devil</hi> for better Wages. <hi>Biting, Sharping, and Shamming,</hi> is his whole Employment, and 'tis ſo riveted in his <hi>Nature,</hi> that you may as well take him to <hi>pieces,</hi> as hope to <hi>Mend</hi> him. His Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery is habitual, he is paſt <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Remedy,</hi> and he that throws away a <hi>Teſter,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>falſe Friend,</hi> looſeth but <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</hi> in the whole. And now having ſhew'd you the <hi>men,</hi> I ſhall (to keep their Favour) Oblige them with a <hi>Female</hi> to keep them Company, under the Name and Character of</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Preciſe Hypocritical Coquet.</head>
               <p>WHo is one ſhe knows not <hi>What</hi> if if you ask her, and conſequently is neither <hi>Fleſh,</hi> nor <hi>Fiſh,</hi> nor good <hi>Red Herring; but what you pleaſe to make her.</hi> She values her ſelf for being neither in, nor out, of the <hi>faſhion.</hi> She wears the beſt of <hi>Silks</hi> and <hi>Linen,</hi> that ever Pinns were put in; but dreſſes ſo <hi>Odly,</hi> that ſhe ſpoils her <hi>Shape,</hi> and the make of her <hi>Face</hi> by ſcrewing it into the Model of <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity.</hi> She reckons nothing ſo <hi>vicious</hi> as going to <hi>Church,</hi> and wearing <hi>Lace</hi> is a greater Sin in her eſteem, than <hi>Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:58572:56"/>or <hi>Adultery.</hi> While ſhe is <hi>Uncoupled</hi> and in <hi>Company,</hi> ſhe's as Demure as a <hi>Saint;</hi> but take her alone, ſhe's as game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom as a little <hi>Cat</hi> in a <hi>Corner,</hi> and will <hi>Tee-Hee</hi> at a <hi>Smutty Jeſt,</hi> and be as brisk and obliging as the <hi>Rankeſt Sinner.</hi> 'Tis true, ſhe rails at the <hi>Beau</hi>'s, as Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate <hi>Vermine,</hi> and a known <hi>Bully</hi> ſcares her as wickedly at the firſt Aſſault, as a <hi>Mad Ox</hi> docs the Women in a <hi>Market;</hi> but if he has the Wit to approach her <hi>Civily</hi> at firſt, after a little warm hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, he ſoon raiſes a place to reſt her hands upon; which her indulgent <hi>zealous</hi> Father ſuſpecting, he ſalves up her <hi>Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with the addition of another <hi>Hundred Yellows,</hi> and <hi>Tacks</hi> her to a <hi>Needy</hi> but <hi>Hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Thriving <hi>Brother,</hi> which new Dyes her <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Chaſtity;</hi> and ſhe's received into his Bed, as a <hi>pure Virgin Sacrifice.</hi> Being now a ſpick and ſpan <hi>new Wife,</hi> ſhe looks as Demurely, as if <hi>Almond But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> would not <hi>Melt</hi> in her mouth, tho' <hi>Suffolk Cheeſe</hi> won't choke her. She is now ſo <hi>Innocent</hi> among her Neighbours, that ſhe even <hi>Bluſhes</hi> to ſee her <hi>Own Hand</hi> naked, and has ſunk her voice to ſo <hi>low</hi> a Key, that ſhe can ſcarce hear her ſelf; but er'e ſhe had been married a <hi>Week,</hi> like a <hi>Larum-Clock,</hi> the whole houſe <hi>Rang</hi> of her. A <hi>Spot</hi> upon her new <hi>Gown</hi> rais'd a Tempeſt, and her Husband <hi>Riſing</hi> in his own <hi>Defence</hi> before ſhe was <hi>awake,</hi> made
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58572:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:58572:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:58572:58"/>ſuch a <hi>Thunder</hi> as <hi>Deafned</hi> all the family. Her Devotion at the <hi>Conventicle</hi> is in turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the <hi>Eggs</hi> of her <hi>Eyes</hi> to the <hi>Tub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> and turning down the <hi>Leaves</hi> of her <hi>Book,</hi> without regard to the <hi>Quotation.</hi> When the <hi>Holder-forth</hi> ſhews how <hi>Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> he can <hi>grunt</hi> out the buſineſs of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> ſhe is full of ſickly Qualms, tho' if the Executioner be but <hi>Man,</hi> ſhe ſays no <hi>Martyr</hi> ſhall ſuffer with greater Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. She abounds with more <hi>Texts</hi> than a <hi>Concordance,</hi> and will not <hi>flap</hi> her Maid o're the <hi>Chaps,</hi> without a <hi>Scripture</hi> Authority; nor correct her Husband's <hi>Coxcomb,</hi> but by a choice Preſident out of ſome of the <hi>Diſſenter's Sayings.</hi> She ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thinks a Sermon good, unleſs ſhe <hi>ride</hi> five Mile to <hi>hear</hi> it, becauſe it covers an <hi>Aſſignation</hi> upon the way, which is much more Edifying than the <hi>Lecture.</hi> She is much in love with the <hi>Quakers Silent Meetings,</hi> becauſe it gives her time to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit,</hi> and ſhe makes amends for't at <hi>Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> and <hi>Prattles</hi> more than any at the <hi>Table</hi> againſt <hi>Sence, Antichriſt,</hi> and her <hi>Husband,</hi> till a fat Gob of Mother <hi>Tripe</hi> and <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard,</hi> puts her to <hi>Silence.</hi> When ſhe has almoſt <hi>Dined,</hi> ſhe complains of a <hi>Tender Conſcience,</hi> the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of her <hi>Stemach,</hi> and her want of <hi>Appetite;</hi> and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately a piece of <hi>Tart</hi> that, by accident was bottom'd with a Leaf of the <hi>Apocripha,</hi> made her <hi>puke,</hi> and had certainly brought
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58572:58"/>up all her <hi>Dinner,</hi> if a luſty Soke of <hi>Right Nans,</hi> had not qualified her <hi>Antipathy</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon.</hi> She i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as full of <hi>Faith,</hi> as an Egg is full of Meat, but has no room for <hi>Charity,</hi> and underſtands no <hi>Good Works</hi> but thoſe, which, when a <hi>Child,</hi> ſhe wrought upon her <hi>Sampler,</hi> and ſpoils them too by often <hi>ſhewing them.</hi> She is a perfect Enemy to all <hi>Church Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick</hi> but the <hi>Chimes,</hi> which kindly call her to <hi>four Meales</hi> a day, and refreſhes her <hi>Spirits</hi> with the comfortable Melody of <hi>Wiſdom, Hopkins,</hi> and <hi>Sternhold.</hi> She <hi>Rails</hi> at the Women of the World as <hi>Damn'd,</hi> for wearing <hi>Fringes</hi> on their <hi>Petticonts;</hi> and wears her own <hi>plain,</hi> that ſhe may take them up with <hi>leſſer trouble</hi> and <hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience. High Heads</hi> and <hi>Laced Shooes</hi> puts her into horrible exclamations; ſhe calls them all <hi>Jezebels, Dalilahs,</hi> and <hi>Whores of Babylon</hi> that wear them; and accounts it as a <hi>Mark of Grace,</hi> that ſhe can <hi>Do</hi> as well without them. She is no leſs Skill'd in <hi>Policies</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> and is an earneſt Contender for the <hi>Rights</hi> of Woman-kind, which ſhe claims as her <hi>Due,</hi> and not as a <hi>Benevolence</hi> from the good Man's <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> She oppoſes the <hi>Monarchy</hi> of a <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> with the <hi>Undeterminable</hi> Privileges of a <hi>Wife,</hi> and maintains the <hi>Sovereignity</hi> of her <hi>Sex,</hi> by keeping the <hi>Keys</hi> of the <hi>Caſh</hi> at her Legiſlature <hi>Girdle,</hi> and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying her <hi>Husband</hi>'s Neceſſities with a
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58572:59"/>
                  <hi>Bit</hi> and <hi>Knock,</hi> as ſhe thinks convenient: And as ſhe gives him with <hi>One</hi> hand, will be ſure to take <hi>Something</hi> from him with the <hi>Other,</hi> that he may never grow to <hi>Big</hi> for her <hi>Management. Freedom</hi> of <hi>Speech</hi> ſhe claims as her <hi>Birth-Right,</hi> be it never ſo <hi>Arrogant</hi> and <hi>Supercillious.</hi> Doing <hi>what ſhe Liſts,</hi> is her <hi>Liberty;</hi> a ſeperate <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> is her <hi>Property,</hi> and claims them by her <hi>Original Contract, for Better for Worſe,</hi> and as agreeable to her Native <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in quality of a Wife, <hi>Dutiful</hi> and <hi>Dominering.</hi> The Man that cloſes with her upon theſe <hi>Principles,</hi> of checking the <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Powers of <hi>Husbands,</hi> tho' a meer <hi>Rake,</hi> has won the <hi>Fort</hi> of her feigned <hi>Vertue;</hi> ſhe ſurrenders upon <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> and will <hi>lye</hi> with him upon an <hi>Impulſe</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to reclaim him from the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar uſe of <hi>Whores,</hi> and <hi>Wicked Women.</hi> And now having gotten her <hi>Heart,</hi> the Devil on't is, he can't be <hi>Rid</hi> of the Reſt of her <hi>body,</hi> but like a <hi>Rattle</hi> at a <hi>Dogs Tail,</hi> let him go where he will, ſhe will follow him, till <hi>Impotency</hi> procures him a <hi>Releaſe,</hi> or <hi>Incurable Claps</hi> bring him to a Death Bed <hi>Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Preciſe She-ſinners are by Nature Guilty,</l>
                  <l>For whether Young or Old Whores they'l Jilt yee.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58572:59"/>
               <head>A Covetous Griping <hi>Uſurer</hi> and <hi>Extortioner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IS the <hi>degenerated</hi> Iſſue of a cruel <hi>Jaylor,</hi> his Eſtate is in heavy <hi>Bonds,</hi> and legal iron <hi>Shackles,</hi> which he never knocks off, but at the price of the Debtor's ruin. He was like <hi>Hemp-ſeed,</hi> ſown into the World in a ſhower of bitter <hi>Curſes,</hi> went Nine times to the Devil before he ſhew'd his Head above Ground, and his Thriving empoveriſh'd all that grew near him. His God is his <hi>Gold,</hi> and he the Idolatrous <hi>Prieſt,</hi> that Sacrifices his <hi>Soul</hi> to his <hi>Profit.</hi> He is a Friend to none, for thoſe he has moſt Intereſt in he <hi>Devours,</hi> and only dreads the day of <hi>Judgment</hi> ſhould come before he has taken the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures</hi> of his <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Morgages,</hi> tho' he has <hi>Ten</hi> in the <hi>Hundred</hi> beſides <hi>Procuration,</hi> and <hi>Continuance</hi> Money, at a <hi>Hundred</hi> in the <hi>Thouſand.</hi> He puts his Money to the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> Act of Generation, and his <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vener</hi> is the Superviſor Cock <hi>Baud</hi> to it. He aſſumes the name of <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> becauſe 'tis the <hi>Cheapeſt</hi> Religion, of <hi>Diſſenter</hi> for the ſake of <hi>Contradiction,</hi> and forbears Whoring only for fear of the <hi>Charge</hi> of keeping <hi>Baſtards.</hi> A <hi>Capitation Tax</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves him to a <hi>New</hi> Lodging, and if he's
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58572:60"/>found out, he ſwears himſelf off, and ſays will truſt God with his <hi>Soul,</hi> rather than the <hi>Collectors</hi> with his <hi>Money.</hi> His Study is how to cheat the <hi>Prodigal,</hi> to cozen this <hi>Landed</hi> Neighbour, <hi>Defraud</hi> that <hi>Widdow,</hi> and <hi>Beggar</hi> thoſe <hi>Orphans.</hi> Debts he owes none but <hi>ſhrew'd</hi> turns, and thoſe he'l be ſure to pay without <hi>Suing.</hi> He loves the <hi>Common-Law,</hi> but ſwears at the Sight of the <hi>Chancery-Court,</hi> and a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paena</hi> would make him <hi>Hang</hi> himſelf, were it not to ſave the charge of a <hi>Haltar.</hi> He is (in ſome ſort) worſe than the <hi>Devil,</hi> he never <hi>Gives</hi> but <hi>ſells</hi> his Days of <hi>Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Bloods</hi> you by Degrees, till the <hi>Spirits</hi> of your Eſtates are inſenſibly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, and then makes <hi>Dice</hi> of your <hi>Bones</hi> to play at <hi>Size-Ace</hi> with his <hi>Scrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> He ſeldom lends Money but in a Forenoon, which ſecures him a <hi>Diner</hi> at the <hi>Tavern,</hi> where he'l drink <hi>freely,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knows you muſt pay the <hi>Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> but at all other times Preaches up <hi>Temperance.</hi> He keeps a Houſe would fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh a <hi>Cricket,</hi> and his Servants do not <hi>Live</hi> but <hi>ſtarve</hi> with him. His <hi>Chimney</hi> is unacquainted with <hi>Fire,</hi> for fear of <hi>Miſchances,</hi> and if he's a <hi>Cold,</hi> he gets himſelf <hi>Heat</hi> by removing an old <hi>Wood-Pile.</hi> He Allows his Servants no <hi>Candle,</hi> That they may break <hi>Glaſſes</hi> for want of <hi>Light,</hi> which they muſt doubly pay for in their <hi>Wages.</hi> His good Name always
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58572:60"/>
                  <hi>Dies</hi> before him, and to ſave the Expence of a <hi>Funeral</hi> for it, he ſuffers it to <hi>Rot</hi> and <hi>ſtink</hi> above ground; and when he falls <hi>Sick</hi> himſelf, he ſends two or three <hi>Pawn-Brokers</hi> before him to the <hi>Devil</hi> for a <hi>Bribe,</hi> to uſe him more <hi>kindly</hi> when he ſhall fall into his <hi>Clutches;</hi> or in hopes he will be ſo buſy about them, and a <hi>Rott</hi> of <hi>Stock-Jobbers,</hi> that he may be a while neglected.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Wheedling Cheating <hi>Scrivener.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IS a Creature begot by a <hi>Pen,</hi> hatch'd in a <hi>Standiſh,</hi> nurs'd by a <hi>Sand-Box,</hi> and the <hi>Wing</hi> of an old <hi>Gooſe</hi> will ſet up half a Score of 'em. In his thread-bare <hi>Baies Gown</hi> and <hi>Furr'd Cap,</hi> he looks like the <hi>By-blow</hi> of a Country <hi>Attorney,</hi> from whom he differs as a <hi>Botcher</hi> from a <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> or the Yeoman of the <hi>Halter</hi> from the <hi>Hangman.</hi> His <hi>Eares</hi> are the Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his <hi>Religion</hi> in Text-hand, and like <hi>Rotten</hi> Fruit hang ſo looſely on his <hi>Head,</hi> that the next <hi>Seſſions</hi>-Wind will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the blowing them off on a <hi>Pilory.</hi> With Relation to the <hi>Publick</hi> he is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>Evil,</hi> for without him Men would become <hi>Honeſt</hi> Neighbours and good <hi>Friends,</hi> and then the body <hi>Politick</hi> would
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58572:61"/>diſſolve, being no longer compounded of Different <hi>Elements</hi> and <hi>Humors.</hi> Better <hi>Scholars</hi> there are many, but few greater <hi>Writers,</hi> and thoſe that curſe the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Preſs</hi> for others ſakes, may more juſtly curſe the <hi>uſe</hi> of the <hi>Pen</hi> for his. I ſhould gueſs his Trade was of great Antiquity, ſince I reade <hi>Indentures of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants</hi> made with <hi>Adam,</hi> but that we know <hi>Adam</hi> had no <hi>Money,</hi> and the <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vener</hi> would not do it <hi>Gratis.</hi> Had <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veners</hi> been in the Antedeluvian World, the <hi>Deluge</hi> might have been <hi>ſpared,</hi> for Mankind would have <hi>deſtroyed</hi> one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without any other help than theirs; and therefore we muſt not look upon them as part of the <hi>Creation,</hi> which was wholly good; But as a <hi>Surreptitious</hi> Race of Men, <hi>bred</hi> out of the <hi>Corruption</hi> of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ages, or like ſome <hi>Africk</hi> Monſters, are the Amphibious <hi>Product</hi> of a <hi>Heterogeneous Copulation;</hi> or when <hi>Pawn Brokers, Tally-Men, and Stock-Jobbers,</hi> met together in different <hi>Humours, Intereſts</hi> and <hi>Contracts,</hi> this Jarring Conjunction begat <hi>Scriveners;</hi> who Viper like Devour their <hi>Parents,</hi> and gnaw their <hi>lively-hoods</hi> out of the <hi>Bowels</hi> of thoſe they hang upon. Methinks they being ſo <hi>Reſty</hi> that the ſevereſt Laws can't reſtrain 'em from doing <hi>Miſchief,</hi> they ſhould be baniſh'd all <hi>Well-Govern'd</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; or at leaſt like <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> wear a <hi>Red-Hot,</hi> or <hi>One Green Stocking</hi> for a
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58572:61"/>mark of Diſtinction, that endanger'd Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers might avoid them; for where once they get in, they ſpread like <hi>St. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony's Fire,</hi> and deſtroy like the <hi>Plague.</hi> Had one of theſe kind of <hi>Scriveners</hi> been among the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> there would have needed no other pretence to have driven them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> themſelves had been the greateſt <hi>puniſhment,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would have <hi>fled,</hi> and not purſued them into the bottom of the Sea. A Generation of Men more inſatiate then <hi>Hell,</hi> and thoſe that pretend to <hi>fear</hi> or <hi>honour</hi> them, are but like Men making <hi>Court</hi> to their <hi>Hangman</hi> for a more favourable <hi>Execution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes he plays the <hi>Baud,</hi> and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes the ſame <hi>Title</hi> to all comers, and if you <hi>Fee him ſoundly,</hi> will not ſtick at Morgaging the ſame <hi>Eſtate,</hi> to ſeven ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Lenders.</hi> Sometimes he <hi>Solders</hi> up a <hi>Crack'd</hi> Title, and paſſes it away for a pure <hi>Virgin.</hi> If it be <hi>weak,</hi> he will ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then it by <hi>Forgery,</hi> and ſecure but his <hi>Ears,</hi> his <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>He</hi> will out ſwear the <hi>Devil.</hi> If you would make a ſafe <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe,</hi> you muſt ſpend half the Value of it in <hi>Enquiries</hi> about the <hi>Title,</hi> and when he has ſecured half of it to himſelf, he tells you it is <hi>Unqueſtionable.</hi> Whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he finds a <hi>Flaw,</hi> it may be ſtopt with <hi>Mony</hi> from the Adverſe Party; and if both <hi>Greaſe</hi> him in the <hi>Fiſt,</hi> he will deal equally between <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:58572:62"/>make them alike Irrecoverably <hi>miſerable,</hi> drawing the <hi>Conveyances</hi> on either ſide ſo <hi>weak,</hi> and yet ſo <hi>ſtrong,</hi> that neither Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall have the <hi>Advantage;</hi> but both en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to <hi>Recover</hi> what <hi>each</hi> knows to be his <hi>Own,</hi> and he to be <hi>Neithers,</hi> they at laſt conſume their <hi>Eſtates</hi> like a <hi>Snow-Ball</hi> with handling it, <hi>Spend</hi> double the <hi>Purchaſe</hi> Mony to ſecure the <hi>Land,</hi> and at length the <hi>Uſurers</hi> to end the Strife, ſeizes on that which each of them have <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged,</hi> and neither of them can <hi>Redeem,</hi> and then part the Stakes, and <hi>Limn</hi> and <hi>Canton</hi> out a brave Eſtate like <hi>Alexanders</hi> Empire into <hi>Petty</hi> Lordſhips.</p>
               <p>If he Trade in <hi>money,</hi> his <hi>Uſurer</hi> and he anſwer one another like the <hi>Hunter</hi> and his <hi>Dog,</hi> or like the <hi>Counter part</hi> and the <hi>Original Ipdenture,</hi> and walk up and down, ſeeking whom they may Devour. Firſt he does his utmoſt to make you <hi>Poor,</hi> that you may be forc'd to addreſs your ſelf to him for a <hi>Supply,</hi> which is the laſt <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and indeed <hi>worſe</hi> than the <hi>Diſeaſe.</hi> If you are neceſſitated to <hi>Borrow,</hi> he marches among your Neighbours, ſmells after your <hi>Reputation,</hi> Enquires into your <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and <hi>Ruins</hi> your Good name to gain you <hi>Credit.</hi> He is vigilant in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taing <hi>Old</hi> Cuſtoms, eſpecially that of <hi>Ten</hi> in the <hi>Hundred,</hi> and what you abate the <hi>Uſurer</hi> you muſt pay to the <hi>Scrivener,</hi> or go without the Sum deſired.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:58572:62"/>
               <p>If his <hi>Uſurer</hi> and <hi>He</hi> ſtart a young <hi>Heir,</hi> this <hi>Blood-Hound</hi> is laid upon the <hi>Scent,</hi> purſues the <hi>Game,</hi> and ne're gives o're the <hi>Chaſe</hi> till he has given him a <hi>Mortal Gripe,</hi> and then like the <hi>Lion</hi> and <hi>Jackel</hi> they divide the Prey; the <hi>Uſurer</hi> gnaws off the the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Scrivener</hi> Picks the <hi>Bones.</hi> To ſtrike the greater <hi>Terror</hi> into the Landed <hi>Novice,</hi> he ſeats himſelf in all his <hi>Formalities,</hi> his Furrrd <hi>Cap</hi> and <hi>Gown,</hi> his <hi>Pen</hi> in one <hi>Ear,</hi> (if both are not off for <hi>Forgery,)</hi> in the midſt of abundance of <hi>VVritings,</hi> which contain the Caſes of ſo many <hi>Ruin'd</hi> perſons. A <hi>Sight</hi> worſe than the <hi>Gallows,</hi> and ſhews the <hi>Youngling</hi> what he muſt come to. Compoſing his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance after the <hi>City cut, ſeriouſly Grave, Dreadfully Rediculous,</hi> and moſt <hi>Majeſtical Simple;</hi> after a tedious Harangue, like a <hi>Dog</hi> making a circle before he lies down, he ſets forth the great misfortune of many <hi>Young Gentleman,</hi> in falling into the hands of <hi>Knaviſh Scriveners,</hi> where he reads him his own <hi>Doom</hi> in the third Perſon, whilſt he is ſhewing him his <hi>Happineſs</hi> in Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him, who is deſirous of nothing but his <hi>Goods.</hi> At laſt he falls upon what he has moſt mind to, his <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and bids him deal truly and plainly with him, that he may do him right; which the <hi>Youngſter</hi> performs very <hi>Simply</hi> and <hi>honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and lays open his <hi>Breaſt,</hi> that this <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> with more eaſe may <hi>Prey</hi> upon his
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58572:63"/>Liver. Having thus gently <hi>wrack'd</hi> him into a <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> the <hi>Scrivener</hi> draws up a Sentence miſcall'd a <hi>Bond</hi> or <hi>Conveyance,</hi> and makes him <hi>ſign</hi> and <hi>ſeal</hi> the Warrant of his own <hi>Execution,</hi> and then by Law Condemns and Executes him.</p>
               <p>This unmerciful <hi>Thief,</hi> like Death, ſpares no Body; he robbs the very Beggars, and will pick a <hi>Courtier's Pocket</hi> tho' he knows 'tis the <hi>King's Money.</hi> He ſtretches the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> upon the <hi>Wrack,</hi> and for an hours <hi>failure</hi> ſiezes upon the <hi>Forfeiture.</hi> He prays for <hi>Non-performance</hi> of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> that he may take the Advantage of the <hi>Penalty,</hi> and ſo far exceed the cruelty of that curſed <hi>Jew,</hi> that he will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> but the <hi>Blood</hi> alſo. When you have incurr'd a Forfeiture, he tells you the <hi>ſtrickneſs</hi> of the Law; and to be free from the <hi>Uſurer,</hi> you muſt compound with the <hi>Scrivener,</hi> and almoſt pay the <hi>Penalty</hi> to be quit of trouble. All the Comfort you have left, is, that when he has bound you ne're ſo <hi>faſt,</hi> for Money he'l <hi>Releaſe</hi> you; teach you how to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the <hi>Articles</hi> he himſelf compoſed, and ne're refuſes to prove himſelf a <hi>Knave,</hi> when ever he can <hi>gild</hi> the Epithet.</p>
               <p>Thus he plays <hi>faſt</hi> and <hi>looſe,</hi> breaths <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>cold,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Devil</hi> that binds the <hi>Charms,</hi> unties 'em alſo. 'Tis a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſight to ſee them running about the <hi>Exchange,</hi> ſmelling at the <hi>Merchants,</hi> juſt
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58572:63"/>like a <hi>Dog</hi> fawning upon ſome, and Snar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at others. He is <hi>one</hi> Miſery after the very <hi>laſt,</hi> the Cauſe of your <hi>Ruine,</hi> and the <hi>Effect</hi> too. When all other <hi>Miſeries</hi> have deſtroy'd you, he follows as a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</hi> and after Execution will <hi>Quarter</hi> you; nay, ſuch is your <hi>Plague,</hi> that when all the World has <hi>ſhaken</hi> you off, <hi>Lice</hi> and <hi>Scriveners</hi> will ſtick to you when you are <hi>Beggar'd.</hi> That you may go to Heaven the lighter, he disburthens you of your <hi>Earth,</hi> your <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and then perſwades you out of <hi>Deſpair</hi> to <hi>Dye,</hi> having parted with all the <hi>World,</hi> and nothing left you to <hi>forſake</hi> but your <hi>Body.</hi> For a <hi>good Fee</hi> he will oblige a Friend, and leave the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Heir</hi> ſo diſputable, that the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Teſtator</hi> may as ſoon interpret his own Mind, as the <hi>Lawyer;</hi> inſerting ſuch <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocal</hi> Terms, as may be any Man's Will more than his that ſent for our <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vener</hi> to make it. He begins a <hi>Will</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>piouſly,</hi> and gives your <hi>Soul</hi> to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty with abundance of <hi>Complement,</hi> and of your worldly <hi>Goods</hi> he will not fail to give himſelf a good <hi>ſhare,</hi> and then turns you over to the <hi>Divine,</hi> before whom he has commonly the <hi>Honour</hi> to be preferr'd: And there leaves you like a <hi>Chriſtmaſs Box,</hi> expecting no more from you till you are broke into pieces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:58572:64"/>
               <head>The Reverſe, or the Charcter of a True <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> in Quality of a <hi>States-man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AS</hi> a <hi>States-man</hi> he is well <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Deſcended,</hi> a Branch of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> Family, and a true <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot</hi> of his Country. One that loves and ſerves God for Goodneſs ſake, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours the King as God's <hi>Repreſentative</hi> on Earth, a <hi>Monarch</hi> that Governs <hi>England</hi> Uprightly, and preferrs the <hi>Glory</hi> of God, and the <hi>Good</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> above any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to his own Glory. As a Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor he ſuggeſts nothing to the King that may look like <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> or by favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Siniſter <hi>Faction,</hi> would make his <hi>Majeſty</hi> appear as the <hi>Head</hi> of a Party, rather than the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>All</hi> his People, who ſhould neither know nor make any <hi>Diſtincton</hi> of his Subjects, but by their <hi>Vertuous</hi> or <hi>Vicious</hi> Practices, and Encourages or diſapprove of them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. He is as tender of the Kings <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative,</hi> as of his own Life, Eſtate, or Honour: Is no leſs <hi>Zealous</hi> for the Legal <hi>Liberty</hi> and Rights of the <hi>People,</hi> and carries ſo juſt and Equal a hand, between <hi>Sovereignity</hi> and <hi>Subjection,</hi> as creates a
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58572:64"/>Mutual <hi>Love,</hi> and an Intire <hi>Affection,</hi> without <hi>Claſhing,</hi> or <hi>Incroaching</hi> upon the Dignity of the <hi>Monarch,</hi> or the Birth-Rights of <hi>Engliſh-men.</hi> He Studies for the Honour of his Country, to make the King <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Rich,</hi> and his Subjects the <hi>Wealthieſt</hi> and beſt <hi>Natur'd</hi> People in the Worl'd; as the ſureſt <hi>Defence</hi> againſt Forreign and Domeſtick <hi>Enemies.</hi> Our States-man's Religion, is Read in the <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency</hi> of his Life, the <hi>Exactneſs</hi> of his Morals, the <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> of his Words, and the <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Honesty</hi> of his Converſation. <hi>Bigottry,</hi> and Screw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up <hi>Forms</hi> of Worſhip beyond the Bounds of <hi>Moderation,</hi> is his Utter Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; yet is he Zealous for good <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> and ſhews an Equal Love and kindneſs to all <hi>Good Men,</hi> that Diſſent out of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and not <hi>Humor</hi> from him. To <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Parties</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> he is a Profeſs'd Enemy, as knowing Unanimity and Concord, is the Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Cement of <hi>Societies.</hi> He Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends no Man to the King for an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,</hi> but upon the account of his <hi>Merits,</hi> and being Regularly <hi>qualified</hi> for the diſcharge of his Office, without which, the neareſt <hi>Alliance</hi> and Tyes of Nature cannot <hi>Byaſs</hi> him. He is a <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to the little <hi>Tricks,</hi> and <hi>Artifices</hi> of ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh <hi>Courtiers,</hi> and will either oblige a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didate <hi>Heartily,</hi> or tell him <hi>Freely</hi> and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58572:65"/>
                  <hi>Speedily</hi> he either <hi>will</hi> not, or <hi>cannot</hi> do it, without keeping him in a <hi>Dilatory</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſive Attendance</hi> to his Ruin. In brief he is the King's <hi>Faithful Counſellor;</hi> the honeſt Man's <hi>Friend,</hi> the Poor and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Man's <hi>Advocate</hi> and <hi>Support;</hi> and the Shame and <hi>Scourge</hi> of the <hi>Double</hi>-minded and <hi>Griping</hi> Courtier. He is well read in the <hi>Policy</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> and by his Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional <hi>Prudence,</hi> Countermines <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiraces.</hi> He knows all the <hi>Maxims</hi> in Governments, but the Laws of the Land are his Rule, and promotes none but thoſe that agree with them, and are <hi>Safe,</hi> and <hi>Honeſt.</hi> His chiefeſt Study is the <hi>common Good,</hi> and is leſs concern'd for his own <hi>Intereſt,</hi> than that of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Private Subject.</head>
               <p>IS one that <hi>Quietly</hi> and <hi>Conſtantly</hi> moves in his own <hi>Sphere,</hi> without Intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Secret</hi> Matters of <hi>State,</hi> that are out of his <hi>Reach,</hi> and Inconſiſtent wit his <hi>Duty.</hi> That Heartily obeys the <hi>King</hi> in all his Commands, that do not Thwart the Laws of <hi>Nature,</hi> or his <hi>Country:</hi> That <hi>Honours, Loves</hi> and <hi>Defends</hi> the King's <hi>Perſon, Crown</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58572:65"/>Chearfully contributes to the ſupport of his <hi>Grandeur</hi> and <hi>Government:</hi> That makes his <hi>Private</hi> concerns ſtoop to the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> and ſuſtains thoſe <hi>Loſſes</hi> with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that he ſuffers for the common <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi> He is one that can diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Slaviſh Fear,</hi> and <hi>Religious Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> Betwixt the <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Cauſe</hi> of a whole <hi>Nation,</hi> and the <hi>Clamours</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents</hi> of a Litigious and Incorrigible <hi>Faction.</hi> A Man that will be <hi>True</hi> to his <hi>King,</hi> without being <hi>Falſe</hi> to his <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Treacherous</hi> to his <hi>Country,</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, is One that (like the Poets Dyal) always ſtands <hi>True,</hi> tho' the Sun of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> or <hi>Favour</hi> never Shines upon him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Clergy-man.</head>
               <p>IS a <hi>Holy-man</hi> in his Converſation, and gains Souls to God, as well by the Integrity of his <hi>Life</hi> as the Purity of his <hi>Doctrine.</hi> He is Univerſally <hi>Learn'd,</hi> See's with his own <hi>Eyes,</hi> and is able to Diſcern <hi>Truth</hi> from <hi>Error</hi> by Underſtanding the <hi>Originals:</hi> While others are impoſed upon for want of thoſe <hi>Lights,</hi> which a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Education</hi> and hard <hi>Study</hi> has Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily Bleſs'd him with. His Religion is the Ground of his <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and the Rule
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58572:66"/>he preſcribes to others. His <hi>Companions</hi> are his <hi>Books,</hi> his <hi>Appartment</hi> his <hi>Study;</hi> and unleſs upon the Diſcharge of his Office, in Relieving the <hi>Poor,</hi> viſiting the <hi>Sich,</hi> or Reconciling <hi>Differences</hi> among his Neighbours, he is ſeldom to be found out of it. His <hi>Recreations</hi> are doing <hi>Good Works,</hi> and ſhews the ſteadfaſtneſs of his <hi>Faith,</hi> by making the Holy Scriptures the Rule of his Life, and in <hi>Practiſing</hi> what he Preaches. He <hi>Reads</hi> before he <hi>Writes,</hi> Writes before he aſcends the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and leaves nothing to a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous <hi>extempory</hi> Invention. He performs the <hi>Offices</hi> of the Church with a decent <hi>Gravity,</hi> and by his own Example <hi>Awes</hi> his Congregation into a praying Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or hearing Poſture, and puts them in mind of what they are doing. His <hi>Sermons</hi> are adapted to the <hi>Capacity</hi> of his Auditors, and he makes it his Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to <hi>Inſtruct,</hi> and not to <hi>Amuſe</hi> or <hi>Pleaſe</hi> them. He knows ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin in decent Expreſſions, without Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of <hi>Wit</hi> is the Buſineſs of a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and that his Learning is better ſeen in the ſubſtance of his Matter, than in <hi>Elegant</hi> Harangues. He is a Stranger to all manner of <hi>Affectation</hi> either in his Words or Geſture, and commands At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention only by the ſeriouſneſs of his Diſcourſes, which are all ways confin'd to what we ought to <hi>Believe</hi> or <hi>Practice,</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:58572:66"/>without Wandring into unneceſſary <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes,</hi> or impertinent Digreſſions. If Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence raiſes him to be a Governor in the Church, he is ſo much the more <hi>Humbler,</hi> the higher he is Exalted; for he ſees his Work and Account to be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and requires the Exerciſe of his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt care and Induſtry to diſcharge it Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly. His Authority in his <hi>Dioceſs</hi> does not make him forget that the Inferior Clergy are his Brethren, and he treats them accordingly: And the augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Eſtate, reminds him that he is only a <hi>Truſtee</hi> for the Poor, and muſt be given to Hoſpitality. If any under his Juriſdiction offends, and by repeating his Crimes after a Fatherly Admonition, he is conſtrain'd to puniſh his Contumacy, it is done with ſo much Meekneſs, as ſhews him neceſſitated to it by the Rules of Juſtice, and not his own Inclination to <hi>Severity;</hi> and therefore upon his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere <hi>Reformation</hi> receives him again into his Boſom. If he has only a Competency in a <hi>ſingle Cure,</hi> without any other addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional <hi>Preferments.</hi> he lives peaceably a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Neighbours, contentedly in his Family, diſcharges his Duty conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and Dies much Lamented.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:58572:67"/>
               <head>An Upright <hi>Lawyer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IS a Man truly Learn'd in the Laws of the Land, and ſquares his Life by the Rules of <hi>Equity</hi> and <hi>Juſtice:</hi> That can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>Bribed</hi> to Act unjuſtly, or betray his <hi>Clyent</hi> for filthy Lucre: That preferrs the Goodneſs of a Cauſe before the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Fee, and perſwades his <hi>Clyent</hi> to <hi>deſiſt,</hi> as ſoon as he perceives his Cauſe is Unjuſt or Litigious. A <hi>Pauper</hi> in the <hi>Right,</hi> is more Welcome to him than a <hi>Lord</hi> in the <hi>Wrong</hi> Box, and treats him as <hi>Humanly</hi> as the <hi>Richeſt</hi> Clyent. He eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his Cauſe, <hi>Dwells</hi> upon the point of <hi>Right,</hi> and no Frowns, or the Interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a more Beneficial Cauſe, can make him give it over, till the Law has done the Poor-man Right, and deliver'd him from vexatious Delays, and the Tyranny of a Litigious and Purſe-proud Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. He is the poor Man's Patron, the Widow's Protector, the common Friend, and Father of diſtreſſed Orphans, and the Honour of his Profeſſion. He troubles not the Court, nor waſts their time with impertinent Addreſs; but inſiſts only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what is <hi>material,</hi> and in that has the Ear of the Court, and the Satisfaction of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:58572:67"/>his own Conſcience. He is zealous for the Prerogatives of the Crown, and with equal Freedom and Courage Aſſerts the Liberty of the People, and in both the Law is the Standard. In the <hi>Church</hi> he behaves himſelf agreably to his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, and the Integrity and Juſtice of his Life, Proclaims him <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and ſincere in his <hi>Religion.</hi> In ſhort, he is a faithful Friend, a kind and loving Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; Hoſpitable to the Rich, Charitable to the Poor, and <hi>Beneficial</hi> to all Men: Whoſe perſonal <hi>Merits,</hi> and the King's Favour, will e're long promote him to the Honour of a Judge, to the Satisfaction of whole Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Learned Phyſician.</head>
               <p>IS a true <hi>Friend,</hi> a careful Aſſiſtant of <hi>Nature,</hi> and from her Indigitations, Collects a Method for his <hi>Practice.</hi> By a regular courſe in his Univerſity Studies, he is able to converſe with the <hi>Arabian, Graecian,</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Phyſicians, his dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent enquiry into the Nature and Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Plants and Minerals, and his Anatomical Speculations into Human Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, has methodically accompliſh'd him for the <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and his Degree
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58572:68"/>of <hi>Doctor,</hi> is a Teſtimonial of his <hi>Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency.</hi> He knows the value of Life, the Greatneſs of his Truſt, and his Care is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to the Account, he muſt give to God for the Death of every <hi>Patient.</hi> Phyſick has been too long accounted the <hi>Mother</hi> of no leſs monſtrous a Birth than that of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and the Adage is in every ones mouth, <hi>Ubi tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Medici, duo Athui, where there are Three Phyſicians, there are two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts;</hi> and becauſe ſome Pops that wart a <hi>Name,</hi> are fond of that Ill one, our <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> by a ſerious religious Life, and the Exerciſe of Vertue, endeavours to wipe off that Scandal from the Profeſſion, and proves from every Leaf, Herb and Flower, and the ſtupendious <hi>Scite</hi> of Man's compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Knowledge of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and Ignorance of the <hi>Exiſtence</hi> of a <hi>Deity,</hi> is wholly impoſſible, ſince beyond all other men they have undeniable Proofs of it.
<q>Praeſentemque refert quaelibet Herba Deum.</q> and the deeper they ſearch into the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Nature,</hi> the more will they be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to confeſs and ſay, <hi>This is the Lords doing.</hi> He knows he has to do with Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures, and lives in an Age not to be impoſed upon by <hi>Authoritative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, or Opinionated Neſtrums,</hi> and therefore propoſes the Satisfaction of mens <hi>Reaſons</hi> by the Rationality of his Method,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58572:68"/>before he attempts the <hi>Care</hi> of their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes. He does not always follow the common <hi>Tract,</hi> but varies his <hi>Preſcriptions</hi> accoridng to the <hi>different</hi> Conſtitutions of his <hi>Partients,</hi> and follows the Dictates of <hi>Nature,</hi> in all her ſymptomatical diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of <hi>Deſpair</hi> or <hi>Amendments.</hi> He deſpiſeth the common Cheat, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Practice of adminiſtring Phyſick upon the ſight of a <hi>Urinal;</hi> but will <hi>See</hi> the Patient, tho' he is ſure to have ſcarce Thanks for his Viſits, and is as careful of the <hi>Poor</hi> as the <hi>Rich,</hi> tho' at the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of maintaining them with Food, while he is giving of them Phyſick. If he is invited to a <hi>Conſult,</hi> he delivers his Judgment freely, and will not ſuffer his Reaſon to be blinded by a Nominal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; Solid Reaſon is his Rule, and a well eſtabliſh'd Experience, both enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens his Judgment, and ſatisfies his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Above all things he abhors trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men out of their Lives; to try the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of a Chimerical Medicine, nor Flatters Mons hopes againſt evident Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of an impoſibility of recovering; but gives every Patient, early notice of his <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> that before he leaves this World, he may be prepared for a <hi>Better.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:58572:69"/>
               <head>A true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Country Gentleman.</head>
               <p>IS the <hi>Stack</hi> upon which our Nobility is grafted, the <hi>Tree</hi> from which <hi>Sciens</hi> are gather'd to be inocculated into the moſt <hi>Illuſtrious Families;</hi> there are none of them but owe their Originals and Bearing to the <hi>Ancient Gentry</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and many of them are ſtill more <hi>ancient</hi> Families, than thoſe that have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired additional <hi>Titles.</hi> The Gentry of <hi>England</hi> are the <hi>Treaſury</hi> of the Nation, the <hi>Support</hi> of the <hi>Crown,</hi> the <hi>Safaty</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Walls</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Bench,</hi> the <hi>Credit</hi> of the <hi>Barr,</hi> the <hi>Hero</hi>'s of the <hi>Camp,</hi> the <hi>Learning</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots</hi> of their <hi>Country,</hi> and the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of <hi>Honour, Arts,</hi> and <hi>Arms.</hi> In his Country Manſion Houſe, he lives like a <hi>Petty Prince,</hi> and his own <hi>Deweans</hi> furniſh his Table plentifully, with <hi>Fewl, Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Fiſh,</hi> and his Orchard and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with <hi>Flowers, Herbs</hi> and <hi>Delicious Fruits;</hi> of which few Men have more, no Man can have <hi>better.</hi> He is not plagu'd with a Nurſery of <hi>Beggers</hi> call'd <hi>Footmen;</hi> does not keep an Hoſpital for <hi>Curres</hi> and <hi>Kites,</hi> nor a Seraglio of <hi>Wheres,</hi> which
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58572:69"/>Sluce the Blood and Brains out. He does not daily Muſter a Regiment of <hi>Sharkes, Fools,</hi> and <hi>Knaves,</hi> at his Table, which Surfeit on his Folly, and empty his Celler with the Gluttons Prayer, <hi>God Bleſs the Founder;</hi> but keeps a conſtant <hi>Table</hi> for his Friends and Family, and unexpected <hi>Viſitors</hi> can never ſurpriſe him. His <hi>kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to his Friends, or <hi>Civility</hi> to Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, does never <hi>Interrupt</hi> his <hi>Devotions,</hi> and thoſe that <hi>Sit</hi> with him at his <hi>Table,</hi> muſt <hi>kneel</hi> with him in his <hi>Chappel;</hi> his <hi>Recreations</hi> are generous and Manly, and he uſes them for his <hi>Divertiſement</hi> and his <hi>Health,</hi> but his <hi>Study</hi> is his Buſineſs. His Servants Thrive, his Tennants grow <hi>Rich,</hi> and the <hi>Poor</hi> in his Pariſh are employ'd, and well provided for. He Adminiſters <hi>Juſtice</hi> with an equal hand: Honeſt Men <hi>Love</hi> him, and none but ill Men <hi>Fear</hi> him; he is careful in the diſcharge of his <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Duties, and is a ſtranger to the fooliſh and Faſhionable <hi>Vices</hi> of the Age, which conſume the <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> of all that purſue them. He neither ſells nor Mortgages his <hi>Old Land,</hi> to build a <hi>New Houſe,</hi> but reſolves to leave them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor as he found them: He delights in the <hi>Country</hi> Air, and Innocent Diverſion, Spends his Rovenue in <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> among his Neighbours, and has no buſineſs in <hi>London</hi> unleſs his Country ſend him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58572:70"/>as a <hi>Member of Parliament,</hi> and as ſoon as the <hi>Seſſion</hi> is over, he returns to enjoy <hi>himſelf</hi> and his <hi>Friends</hi> in the <hi>Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>NINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 47. l. 1. for <hi>Pendantick,</hi> read <hi>Pedantick</hi> Page 47. l. 11. read <hi>to make him look like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Page 62. l. 11. for <hi>Watſallen,</hi> read <hi>notſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>W.</hi> Page 64. l. 15. for <hi>Broken</hi> read <hi>Broking.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
